<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Devils patriarck, or, A full and impartial account of the notorious life of this present Pope of Rome Innocent the 11th wherein is newly discovered his rise and reign, the time and manner of his being chosen Pope, his prime procession, consecration and coronation, the splendour and grandeur of his Court, his most eminent and gainful cheats, by which he gulls the silly people, his secret and open transactions with the papists in England, Scotland, France and Ireland, and other Protestant countreys to this very day : together with the rest of the hellish policies and infamous actions of his wicked life / written by an eminent pen to revive the remembrance of the almost forgotten plot against the life of his Sacred Majesty and the Protestant religion.</title>
            <author>Ness, Christopher, 1621-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12040148</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12040148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 572:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Devils patriarck, or, A full and impartial account of the notorious life of this present Pope of Rome Innocent the 11th wherein is newly discovered his rise and reign, the time and manner of his being chosen Pope, his prime procession, consecration and coronation, the splendour and grandeur of his Court, his most eminent and gainful cheats, by which he gulls the silly people, his secret and open transactions with the papists in England, Scotland, France and Ireland, and other Protestant countreys to this very day : together with the rest of the hellish policies and infamous actions of his wicked life / written by an eminent pen to revive the remembrance of the almost forgotten plot against the life of his Sacred Majesty and the Protestant religion.</title>
                  <author>Ness, Christopher, 1621-1705.</author>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[17], 134 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Dunton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Christopher Ness.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: T.O. which Halkett and Laing and BM indicates is Titus Oates.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Innocent --  XI, --  Pope, 1611-1689.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:52972:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Innocnt the 11 Pope of Rome. London Printed for J: Dunton at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> black Raven in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poultrey</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52972:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>DEVILS PATRIARCK,</hi> OR A Full and Impartial Account Of the NOTORIOUS LIFE Of this Preſent <hi>Pope of Rome <hi>INNOCENT</hi>
               </hi> the 11th.</p>
            <p>Wherein is <hi>newly</hi> Diſcovered his <hi>Riſe and Reign;</hi> The <hi>Time and Manner</hi> of his being choſen Pope; His Prime Proceſſion, Conſecration and Coronation; The <hi>Splendour</hi> and <hi>Grandeur</hi> of his Court; His moſt <hi>Eminent</hi> and <hi>Gainful</hi> Cheats, by which he Gulls the <hi>ſilly</hi> People; His <hi>Secret</hi> and <hi>Open</hi> Tranſactions with the Papiſts in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and other Proteſtant Countreys to this <hi>very</hi> day; Together with the <hi>Reſt</hi> of the Helliſh Policies and Infamous Actions of his wicked Life.</p>
            <p>Written by an <hi>Eminent Pen</hi> to Revive the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the <hi>almoſt</hi> forgotten Plot againſt the Life of his Sacred Majeſty and the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Entered according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Black-Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52972:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52972:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid and Curteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen a ſuddain and ſurprizing <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion</hi> is made upon us by a <hi>Foreign Power,</hi> every Right-thinking Mind cannot but Judg it high time to <hi>Fire our Beacons. Aeſops</hi> Witty Wiſdom, (in his <hi>Fable of the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd-Boy,</hi> that cry'd out falſly, as well as frequently, <hi>[The Wolf comes, the Wolf comes, Help, Help.]</hi> to the People,) hath in the <hi>Apologues Moral</hi> a very ſhrewd <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity,</hi> with our preſent Caſe, though there wants not alſo ſome <hi>Diſparity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>(1.)</hi> The <hi>Congruity</hi> conſiſts in theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Every Shepherd ſhould be careful to preſerve the Flock committed to his Charge; ſo ought every <hi>Myſtical,</hi> as well as the <hi>Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Shepherd, (whether <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>aut</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Young or Old,) to be.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:52972:3"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Both ought to cry out of <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>Approaching Dangers.</hi> It was not at all Improbable, that the Wolf was a coming, becauſe he us'd frequently to do ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When <hi>Dangers</hi> be both <hi>Probable</hi> and <hi>Approaching,</hi> (for 'tis the Nature of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> to <hi>worry the Sheep,</hi>) then 'tis the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y of <hi>Both,</hi> not only to <hi>Cry out,</hi> but to <hi>Crave Help</hi> from the <hi>Peoples</hi> Hands, yea to quicken up <hi>their</hi> Aſſiſtance with ſtrong and Reiterated Outcrys, That the <hi>Abaddon,</hi> (a bad one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,) the <hi>Apollyon,</hi> or Devouring Beaſt, is juſt a coming.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> All Hands are few enough to <hi>Help the Lord</hi> againſt this <hi>Mighty,</hi> (yea in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> phraſe, <hi>Almighty,) Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> All private Works muſt be left, (both in <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi>) for ſtopping the ſtrong Current of a Publick and Common Calamity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> As the Sheep of <hi>Aeſops</hi> Shepherd were Grazing, <hi>[in eminentiori Loco,]</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Lofty Mountains, yet not <hi>Inacceſſible</hi> to the <hi>Wolf:</hi> So the Sheep, which <hi>Goſpel-Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds</hi> are feeding, and which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Wolf would Worry, are likewiſe Grazing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Holy-Hill of <hi>Zion,</hi> the <hi>higheſt of all Hills,</hi> yet not ſo high, but, when the Sins of the Sheep do open a paſſage, becomes <hi>Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> to the Wolf alſo. Where the Beaſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:52972:3"/>
been before, <hi>Treading down the Green Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and fouling the Reſidue with his foul Feet,</hi> he hath ſome hope for returning thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again, eſpecially, ſeeing the <hi>Neſt-Egg</hi> of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Reliques is ſtill left behind to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his Return: Bloody Biſhop <hi>Bonner</hi> could once Briskly Brag, <hi>Such as like to Sup our Broth, we will make them love to Eat our Beef too:</hi> God grant us a good Deliverance from ſuch Barbarous Butchers, and Beaſtly Butcheries, from that <hi>Brutiſh People, Skilful to Deſtroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>(2.)</hi> As to the <hi>Diſparity,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Outcry of <hi>Aeſops</hi> Shepherd-Boy was only, <hi>[Joci gratià,]</hi> a <hi>falſe</hi> Holloe for Sport-ſake, a Boyiſh-Trick, playing the Wag with the Maſters of the Sheep, to whom he was but an Hireling-Servant: But the Outcry of our Shepherds have been ever more Real and Serious, from the many Eſſays and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, which <hi>Rome</hi> has really made to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce (as <hi>Colemans</hi> Phraſe is,) this <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Hereſie to her Obedience: <hi>She</hi> hath all along, ever ſince the <hi>Reformation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> here, with all her <hi>Fraud</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> with all <hi>Her Craft</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter with her <hi>Deformation</hi> of it, and to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover both her <hi>Neſt,</hi> and her <hi>Neſt-Egg,</hi> from which ſhe was forced.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:52972:4"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Our Outcry hath not been made by ſome one <hi>Novice,</hi> or of many <hi>Novices</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo of the moſt Grave, moſt Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and moſt Thinking Diſcerning <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Sheepfold, who, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> could eſpye the very firſt Outgoings of Wrath, and, with <hi>Elijah</hi> could Obſerve a Black Cloud, though no bigger than a Mans Hand: All theſe at Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Times, and in Divers Manners, have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as with one Mouth Sounded Loud Alarms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Though thoſe call'd in to be Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants againſt the Wolf, in the <hi>Fable, [nihil eſſe comperiebant,]</hi> found nothing of real Danger. Yet thoſe call'd together to Aſſiſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Wolf of</hi> Romes Incurſions, have upon undenyable grounds found out a Real Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Witneſs His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Privy-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> Reiterated <hi>Proclamations,</hi> the <hi>Unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Votes</hi> of <hi>Four Succeſſive Parliaments,</hi> (all call'd upon for their Aſſiſtants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) The <hi>Forms of Prayer, Compoſed</hi> and <hi>Impoſed</hi> by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> for the Faſt appointed by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, upon the Account of the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> as alſo the Murder of <hi>Juſtice Godfrey,</hi> and the Juſt Execution of ſome Grand Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Sheep-worrying Beaſt in the Fable, is expreſly call'd a <hi>Wolf</hi> only, though there be other Beaſts as obnoxious to Sheep.
<pb facs="tcp:52972:4"/>
But this <hi>Molock</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſuch a Bloudy Beaſt, as no Name could ſufficiently expreſs his Bloud-Thirſtineſs. Hereupon <hi>(1.) Daniel</hi> calls the <hi>Firſt Beaſt,</hi> (or <hi>Aſſyrian Empire,</hi>) a <hi>Lyon.</hi> The <hi>Second,</hi> (the <hi>Medo-Perſian,</hi>) a <hi>Bear.</hi> The <hi>Third,</hi> (the <hi>Graecian,</hi>) a <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard.</hi> But the <hi>Fourth,</hi> to wit, (the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire,</hi>) he calls a <hi>Beaſt</hi> in general, (without any name,) as if <hi>Exceeding,</hi> (as well as <hi>Including,</hi>) the Savage Nature of all the Three former, <hi>Dan. 7.4, 5, 6, 7, 23. (2.) John</hi> alſo, (as well as <hi>Daniel,</hi>) calls him a <hi>Beaſt</hi> in the general, (<hi>without,</hi> becauſe <hi>above</hi> any Name,) yet makes he <hi>him</hi> a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Beaſt, Compounded of all the Three Beaſts aforeſaid, as having the <hi>Feet of a Bear,</hi> the <hi>Mouth of a Lyon, Himſelf like a Leopard,</hi> and <hi>the Dragon giving him Power,</hi> Revel. 13.2. And though <hi>Rome Heathen</hi> hath done much againſt <hi>Chriſts Sheep, Slaying its Thouſands,</hi> yet <hi>Rome Anti-Chriſtian</hi> hath done more, and far out-done <hi>it</hi> in <hi>Slaying its Ten Thouſands:</hi> So that this <hi>Beaſt,</hi> (above all Names,) is a <hi>Beaſt</hi> with a Witneſs, an Hyperbolical <hi>Behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth,</hi> as if many Beaſts made up One, (ſo the <hi>Hebrew Plural Faeminine</hi> ſignifies,) far beyond the moſt Bloud-Thirſty <hi>Wolf,</hi> yea the moſt Savage <hi>Cannibal,</hi> for Eating the Fleſh and Drinking the Bloud of <hi>Poor Proteſtants,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:52972:5"/>
even to an high Inebriation, as the Sequel will more fully Demonſtate: Take but this Taſt here, 'Tis credibly Related, That in the ſpace of Eight Hundred Years, this <hi>Monſtrous Beaſt,</hi> (who hath all Cruelties Concentred in him,) hath been the Death of Twelve Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtians. <hi>Idaea Reform. Antichr. Tom. 1. Part 2. Sect. 2. Cap. 6.</hi> To Inſtance only one Specimen of this <hi>Pourtray'd Beaſt</hi> in this place, to wit, <hi>Pope Julius the Second,</hi> (who was turn'd up Trump, and Triumph'd in the Chair of Peſtilence, in the Fifteenth Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) that made a ſhift to Worry (in Seven Years ſpace of his Papacy) no fewer than Seven Hundred Thouſand <hi>Sheep.</hi> See <hi>Baleus de Actis Rom. pontif. lib. 7.</hi> 'Tis one of <hi>Luthers</hi> Divine Raptures, that <hi>Cain</hi> (the Firſt-Born of the Devils Patriarks) ſhall be Murdering his Brother <hi>Abel</hi> to the end of the World: and the Older he groweth, the more Bloud-Thirſty he becometh: This <hi>Romiſh Runnet</hi> (as is commonly ſaid of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in Dairy Houſes) the Older it is, it grows ſo much the <hi>Stronger.</hi> If the <hi>Beaſt</hi> were ſo Bloudy in that Century aforementioned, how much more may he be expected in this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Pope.</hi> Seeing <hi>[Morſus moribundae Beſtiae ſunt maximè mortiferi,]</hi> The loſt Bitings of a Dying Beaſt are moſtly moſt Dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and whether this be yet paſt, <hi>Sub Judice
<pb facs="tcp:52972:5"/>
lis eſt,</hi> 'tis a matter of Controverſie, and if not, I would ask my <hi>Countrymen Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> Is this a Beaſt fit to be <hi>Courted into England?</hi> which is indeed the Bloudy <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let-Colour'd Whore,</hi> that better deſerveth to he <hi>Carted out of it,</hi> and out of the World alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It doth not appear, that the <hi>Wolf</hi> in the <hi>Fable</hi> was ever reſtrained from any At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts by thoſe frequent outcries for Aſſiſtance, ſeeing the Report of his approaching was falſe until the laſt. But this <hi>Beaſt of Rome</hi> hath had many ſignal and ſingular reſtraints by <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. But above all, by an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible and an Over-ruling Hand; ſo that ſhe hath been conſtrained to alter her Methods, and to take new Meaſures, Foiſting her dead Brats into the Boſom of <hi>Innocent Proteſtants,</hi> which though it need not the Wiſdom of a <hi>Solomon</hi> to Diſcover, yet requireth it the Power of a <hi>Parliament</hi> more fully to Determine, in a way of Vindicative Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixtly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I wiſh with all my Soul, that there may be found more <hi>Diſparity</hi> than <hi>Congruity</hi> in the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> and Cloſure of the <hi>Fable,</hi> as Relating to our preſent <hi>Caſe.</hi> The <hi>Apologue</hi> indeed concludeth thus, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Husbandmen</hi> had been oft abuſed by the falſe Alarms of the Boy, leaving their Ploughs ſtanding Idle in the Field to deliver the Sheep
<pb facs="tcp:52972:6"/>
when there was no Danger, then the <hi>Wolf</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in good earneſt, the <hi>Boy</hi> cries out, but was not believed by them, whom he had ſo oft deceived, hereupon the <hi>Wolf</hi> prevails againſt the <hi>Boy,</hi> Worries the Sheep without reſiſtance, Gluts himſelf with their Fleſh and Bloud, and eſcapes away ſcotfree, without ſo much as a blow for that unparallel'd miſcheif: The <hi>Moral</hi> of this laſt part is, as <hi>Solomon,</hi> with his wonderful Wiſdom, helps us to Interpret it, ſaying, <hi>Woe be to that Land,</hi> that hath [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ovium Paſtorem] no wiſer than a Child,</hi> Eccl. <hi>10.16.</hi> Alas, He is not able, (though never ſo willing) to Deliver his Flock, <hi>&amp;c. Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith alſo, But <hi>in multitude of Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors there is ſafety,</hi> Prov. <hi>11.14.</hi> This <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds Boy</hi> had ſo much Wit in him, as to call in more helping Hands to his own, though he did oft cry ſo <hi>Childiſhly,</hi> and at laſt (through his own fooliſh fraud) <hi>fruitleſly</hi> without ſucceſs. We have had many loud Alarms Trumpeted out, crying, <hi>[The Romiſh Wolf is coming, Help, Help,]</hi> and though none of the many have been falſe outcries, as before, yet would to God the <hi>Helping Husbandmen</hi> may not (through ſo many Diſappointments) grow wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Appearing, ſo let the <hi>Devouring Beaſt</hi> have his Blond-Thirſty Luſt ſatiated upon the <hi>Proteſtant-Sheep,</hi> and all this without any reſiſtance and oppoſition. But though this
<pb facs="tcp:52972:6"/>
               <hi>Apologue</hi> of <hi>Aeſops</hi> be thus ſignificantly ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in its <hi>Moral,</hi> yet have we a <hi>Divine Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> (to Wit, that of <hi>Jothams,</hi> Judg. <hi>9.</hi>) that infinitely Tranſcends it in its ſignal and ſingular Signature as to our preſent Calamitous Condition. Bloudy <hi>Abimeleck (a baſe Baſtard)</hi> Uſurps the Kingdom, which by ſubtle practiſing upon his <hi>Kinsfolk</hi> and the <hi>Men of Shechem</hi> he <hi>craftily compaſſed,</hi> and (by the help of his vile Vagrants and Villanous Followers, Hired with the Treaſure of <hi>Baal-Berith</hi>) as <hi>cruelly conſtituted</hi> the Foundation of it, in Murdering (like a bloudy Tyrant) Seventy Innocent, and all Legitimate Competitors to make his way to the Throne, <hi>Good Jotham</hi> onely eſcaping, <hi>He</hi> takes the boldneſs (notwithſtanding his Perſonal Danger) to make <hi>his mind</hi> (yea and <hi>Gods</hi> too) known to the <hi>Men of Shechem</hi> from the <hi>top of Mount Gerizim</hi> (that <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> not <hi>Mount Ebal</hi> that <hi>Curſing Mountain</hi>) Before he took to his Heels, and fled from the Tyrant. As this Sacred <hi>Apologue</hi> of <hi>Jotham's,</hi> (who, though but a young Man, was <hi>vir bonus, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi peritus,</hi> a good Man, and a <hi>good Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> one that <hi>could declare his Mind fitly,</hi> and <hi>durſt do it Freely,</hi> being [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] Inſpired of Gods Spirit) doth therefore far (I ſay) Tranſcend the aforeſaid Fable of <hi>Aeſop,</hi> ſo it <hi>more highly</hi> merits a larger Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant upon it, were I not bound up to the Narrow
<pb facs="tcp:52972:7"/>
Limits of a Short and yet Succinct <hi>Preface.</hi> Hereupon, all that I am Allowed to Add, is, to let the Iugenious Reader know, that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Doctors do Underſtand by the Fig-Tree in the Parable, Renowned <hi>Deborah</hi> their <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs,</hi> as by the <hi>Olive-tree Othniel,</hi> or <hi>Ehud,</hi> and by the <hi>Fruitful Vine, Gideon</hi> with his Numerous Off-ſpring; what is meant by the <hi>Bramble</hi> needs not much Explication, it being not a <hi>Tree,</hi> but a <hi>Shrub</hi> (the Product of <hi>Gods Curſe upon the Earth,</hi> Gen. <hi>3.17, 18.</hi>) <hi>Prickly, Barren, Baſe, Abject,</hi> good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but to <hi>Stop Gaps,</hi> or <hi>Kindle a Fire: Abimeleck</hi> was a <hi>Right Bramble</hi> indeed, who grew in the baſe Hedg-Row of a Contemptible Concuhine, who horribly ſcratch'd and drew Bloud to purpoſe, when once he had (by the help of <hi>Baal-Beriths</hi> Treaſure) ſcrambl'd up to a Dominion over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whereunto he was Handed by his hired Beggerly Raſcals, and Debauched Deſperado's: The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Moral</hi> Hereof (as to us) is obvious to every common Underſtanding, and neither the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,</hi> nor the <hi>Application</hi> is any matter of Difficulty: I ſhall therefore conclude my Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liminary part with this pathetical <hi>Epiphone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> as a <hi>Golden Key</hi> to open the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity:</hi> Oh <hi>England, England,</hi> Thou haſt had thy Delivering <hi>Deborah (Queen Elizabeth)</hi> who ſaved thee in Gods Hand from
<pb facs="tcp:52972:7"/>
the <hi>Curſed Canaanites,</hi> that delt cruelly with thee in the <hi>Marian Days,</hi> Thou haſt alſo had thy <hi>Othniels, Ehuds</hi> who did ſtab the <hi>Red Letter Cauſe</hi> with their very <hi>Pens</hi> (as <hi>King James</hi>) excellently and unanſwerably Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, though <hi>he</hi> was but <hi>left handed</hi> for the Sword, having for his <hi>Motto [Rex pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus]</hi> which one wittely Engliſhed <hi>[put up thy Dagger Jamy]</hi> And ſome Abuſive wits limn'd his Picture with a Padlock upon his Sword, yet his <hi>Learned Writing</hi> did ſo effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually vindicate his undoubted Right againſt <hi>Pope Paul the Fifth,</hi> that there was no need of <hi>Martial Warring (Cedant Arma Togae,</hi> &amp;c.) There was no occaſion for <hi>Mars,</hi> where <hi>Minerva</hi> was his <hi>Bellona;</hi> which made his <hi>Un-Holineſs</hi> Decline the Encounter: <hi>Thou</hi> haſt likewiſe had thy <hi>Gideon</hi> with a fruitful Ofspring, ſtout Aſſertors of the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſhouldſt thou? now forſake the <hi>Fitneſs,</hi> the <hi>Fatneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Fruitfulneſs</hi> of thy Truly. Noble <hi>Figtree, Olive</hi> and <hi>Vine</hi> (which indeed hath <hi>cheered God and Man</hi>) and at laſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a <hi>Baſe Bramble,</hi> that <hi>exotick, dry, empty, Saples Kex</hi> and <hi>Weed</hi> of a <hi>Forraign Power,</hi> to wit, that of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> the <hi>Son of Perdition</hi> and the <hi>wicked one,</hi> which is the threefold Black-Brand, wherewith <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> is Stigmatized by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> How far this threefold Character agreeth with
<pb facs="tcp:52972:8"/>
the <hi>Pope;</hi> See the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> lib. <hi>1,</hi> chap. <hi>4. Foulis Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Romiſh Treaſons</hi> and <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations</hi> per totum, and <hi>Neſſes Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> pag. <hi>55.</hi> to <hi>63. &amp;c.</hi> what their own Authours Report of <hi>them</hi> may be beſt believed: That this <hi>Babyloniſh Brat</hi> is a <hi>Baſtard</hi> like the <hi>Bramble Abimeleck,</hi> and and not <hi>Legitimate,</hi> or Heaven-born, their own very Creatures are conſtrained to Confeſs.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Firſt, Platina,</hi> who was the <hi>Pope</hi>'s own Secretary, and Keeper of the <hi>Vatican-Library,</hi> yea a Writer by Commiſſion from <hi>Pope Sixtus</hi> the <hi>Fourth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Benno Uſpergenſis,</hi> one of <hi>Romes</hi> own Cardinals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And <hi>Math. Pariſienſis</hi> a <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictin Monk</hi> of the Monaſtary of St. <hi>Albans</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> All theſe three (none of them writing out of Prejudice, ſo they would have bewray'd their own Neſt, but Imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and in Truth) doe Unanimouſly Deſcribe the <hi>Popes</hi> to be Limbs of the Devil; the laſt of which Relates, How [<hi>Diabolus, &amp; Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum Contubernium,</hi> &amp;c.] that the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and All his Helliſh Crew Wrote Gratulato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Letters to the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Clergy, for ſending more Souls to Hell, than ever went before,</hi> Math. Paris Hiſt. Angl. Guil. Conqueſt. Anno. <hi>1072.</hi> pag. <hi>10.</hi> Yea none of them can deny, but that ſome of the Popes ſold themſelves
<pb facs="tcp:52972:8"/>
to the Deuil for their obtaining of the Popedom by his Craft. Therefore the <hi>Men of Shechem</hi> or <hi>England</hi> need no <hi>Jotham</hi> to Proclaim to them, (ſeeing the very <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves ſay enough) that <hi>if in Truth ye Anoint this Pope to have Dominion over you,</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again to <hi>put your Truſt in his shadow,</hi> ye will be not onely Notoriouſly diſapointed in your <hi>Shelter</hi> under ſuch a <hi>Shadow</hi> (for the <hi>Bramble-Buſh</hi> cannot yeild any good Shade; the ſilly Sheep flying to it for ſhelter, are ſure to loſe part of their <hi>Fleece,</hi> if not of their Fleſh too) But alſo a Fire will flow fiercely forth from this <hi>Baſe Bramble</hi> to Devour you, and your talleſt Cedars: This one <hi>Terrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filius</hi> or <hi>Baſtard</hi> will deſtroy all your true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Sons: He that hath but half an eye, may both <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>foreſee</hi> the Matchleſs miſcheifs that muſt be its Conſequences, which they that are ſo Hot for a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſour</hi> (while they yet profeſs themſelves to be good Proteſtants) doe not Duly and Truly Conſider. But I muſt not detain you too long in the <hi>Porch,</hi> for fear of your catching cold. Having Diſpatched the <hi>Prologue,</hi> conſiſting of a Double <hi>Apologue,</hi> (which may be further Illuſtrated and Applyed in the <hi>Epilogue</hi>) Let me now hand you to the Houſe it ſelf, wherein you may take a plain Proſpect of this <hi>preſent Pope</hi> limn'd to the life in his Right Red Vermilion Colours.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52972:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52972:9"/>
            <head>The Notorious LIFE Of this preſent POPE of <hi>ROME, [INNOCENT,</hi> XI.]</head>
            <p>THis preſent <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> was <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Odeſchalchi</hi> of <hi>Come</hi> in the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Millaine,</hi> when called to the <hi>Roman-Chair,</hi> whether we wrong him in reckoning him among the Baſe Brambles of the Curſed Earth, is the [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Poſtulatum,</hi> or <hi>Grand Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> In the General let <hi>Dr. Prideaux</hi> give the Anſwer for me, who Writes a <hi>Compendious Hiſtory</hi> of the Lives of all the <hi>Popes,</hi> and after he hath paſt the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> (and the tollerable Popes) <hi>He</hi> begins at <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 606. with <hi>Uſurping Nimrods,</hi> (a worſe Name than <hi>Brambles</hi>) and Reckons <hi>Thirty Eighth Popes (Cruel Hunters all,)</hi> from that Year, to 847.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52972:10"/>The <hi>Firſt</hi> of which Black Bed-Roll, was <hi>Boniface</hi> the <hi>Third,</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> was the Laſt.</p>
            <p>His next Rank were (as he Stiles them) <hi>Rank Luxurions Sodomites,</hi> whereof <hi>He</hi> Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons <hi>Forty,</hi> from the Year 855. to 996. the <hi>Firſt</hi> of them was <hi>Pope John</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> (in plain <hi>Engliſh, Pope Joan,</hi> the <hi>Rank Whore,</hi> which God would have, to Declare to all the World, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Whore,) and the Laſt of that Number was <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Fifth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Third</hi> ſort of <hi>Popes,</hi> from the Year 999. to 1240. that He preſents to our View, are another Bundle of <hi>Forty Popes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, whom He Dignifies with that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Title of <hi>Aegyptian Magicians;</hi> the Firſt of this Black Regiment was <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> and the Laſt was <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> the <hi>Fourth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Fourth Proſpect</hi> of Popes <hi>He</hi> giveth, is another lovely Cluſter of Sower Grapes, conſiſting of <hi>Eight</hi> and <hi>Thirty Popes,</hi> from the Year 1243. to 1503. The Captain where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Fourth,</hi> and the Lieutenant (that brings up the Rear) is <hi>Pius</hi> the <hi>Third,</hi> All which he Brandeth for a Company of <hi>Devouring Abaddons,</hi> All <hi>Bad-ones</hi> beyond Bounds.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52972:10"/>Yet ſtill there be <hi>worſe</hi> behind, <hi>[Occupat extremum Scabies,]</hi> which as ſome do <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> not only the <hi>Scab,</hi> but the <hi>Devil</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hindermoſt. 'Tis the Divine Doom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, to be <hi>waxing worſe</hi> and <hi>worſe,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may the leſs be wondred at, that the <hi>laſt Claſſis of Popes,</hi> (which are the very <hi>Dregs</hi> of Time,) muſt be the worſt, and thereupon are worthily Stigmatiz'd with the worſt Appellation. The Words of the Reverend Author aforeſaid, Run thus, [after the <hi>Devouring Abaddons,</hi>] To fill up the <hi>Myſtery</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable Babylonians</hi> do next ſtep upon the Stage, [<hi>Curavimus Babylona, &amp; non eſt Sanata,</hi> Jerem. 51.6.] <hi>We would have Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> Babylon, <hi>but ſhe could not be Cured,</hi> for the reſt of the Men that were not Killed by thoſe Plagues, Repented not of their (1.) <hi>Murthers,</hi> (2.) <hi>Sorceries,</hi> (3.) <hi>Fornications,</hi> (4.) <hi>Thefts,</hi> Revel. 9.20, 21. This <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>worſt</hi> Rank reaches from the Year 1503. to this preſent 1683. betwixt which Two Periods the Number of Popes are <hi>Twenty-Five,</hi> (the <hi>feweſt Number</hi> of all the Five Claſſes, yet have the <hi>Fouleſt,</hi> both <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi>) whereof <hi>Julius</hi> the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> leads the Van, and this preſent <hi>Pope,</hi> (the ſubject of our Diſcourſe,) brings up the Rear.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52972:11"/>I would have given ſome ſhort Remarks upon theſe ſeveral Claſſes, (thus dignified and diſtinguiſhed with thoſe Five aforeſaid Honourable Titles,) and upon the ſeveral Popes, as they ſtand in Rank and File, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſeveral Banners in every Claſſis, had it not been beſide my preſent purpoſe, and would it not have ſwoln this Diſcourſe too much. I ſhall therefore ſatisfie my ſelf, and the Reader with <hi>Two Remarks</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt Remark</hi> is, That the Leader of the Van in the Second Rank, is a <hi>Virago</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a <hi>Virgo,</hi> a Pope of the <hi>Faeminine Gender,</hi> that Taught Gramarians to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline <hi>Papa</hi> with <hi>Haec</hi> not <hi>Hic:</hi> The name of this <hi>Female Pope, (John</hi> or <hi>Joan)</hi> both in a Literal and Myſtical Senſe, ſheweth that <hi>Rome</hi> may well be called the <hi>Whore of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, Romiſh</hi> Chronologers have not Inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Name in the Catalogue of Popes, which <hi>Marianus Scotus</hi> Renders this Reaſon for, <hi>[Propter Turpituidinem Rei, &amp; Sexum Muliebrem,]</hi> becauſe the wrong <hi>Gender</hi> would be a Reproach to them. Wherefore to avoid the like Diſgrace, the <hi>Porphiry Chair,</hi> (or Groping-ſtool) was Ordained, <hi>Ubi ab Ultimo Diacono,</hi> &amp;c. Where the loweſt Deacon muſt make the Experiment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hence it is, That theſe Popes who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52972:11"/>
have called themſelves <hi>[Johns]</hi> are ſo ill ordered in their common Catalogues, ſome making that <hi>John</hi> which Succeeded [<hi>Adrian</hi> the Second] in the Year 872. to be <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> and others <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Ninth:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious <hi>Platina</hi> forequoted, doth only (of all the <hi>Romaniſts</hi>) Recken <hi>Pope Joan</hi> as the Eighth of the <hi>Johns,</hi> and ſo farward: And 'tis proboble enough (ſaith Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> a Man Fair and Favourable enough) that God ſuffer'd that Proud See of <hi>Rome</hi> to fall into ſuch a profound Reproach, the more to cut the Coxcombs of the Succeeding <hi>Popes</hi> in their Higheſt Ruff and Riotings, and the better to beat down their Big Brags of a continued Succeſſion, whereof they are frequently Boaſting. As <hi>[Remember</hi> Lots <hi>Wife]</hi> is a due Caution to us, ſo I ſee not why [<hi>Remember Pope</hi> Joan] ſhould not be likewiſe a true Check to them: The Truth of this Story, as to matter of Fact, Mr. <hi>Alexander Cook</hi> (my quondam Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour) in his Book of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it by Irrefragable Arguments, and hath moſt Induſtruouſly batter'd down all the Objections which the moſt Mercurial Wits of <hi>Rome</hi> could raiſe againſt it. See his Book, and Dr. <hi>Heylins Coſmography</hi> in Folio the laſt Edition, pag. 107. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Baſtard Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck</hi> aforementioned did Deſperately grudg,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52972:12"/>
that it ſhould be ſaid <hi>[a Woman had Braind him]</hi> Judg. 9.54. Sure I am, <hi>this baſe born Brat of</hi> Rome (the <hi>Head</hi> of the Church) hath Received (were <hi>He</hi> ſenſible) a <hi>Deadly Wound</hi> by the hands of a Woman likewiſe, with this difference only, the <hi>former</hi> was <hi>Active,</hi> and Deſigning, the <hi>latter</hi> was <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi> and never purpoſed the Wounding: 'Tis ſuch a Reproach to the <hi>Roman</hi> Chair as will never be wiped off; this is the <hi>Semira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> the <hi>Amazoman Queen,</hi> the <hi>She-Captain,</hi> that ſtands in the Front of the <hi>Second</hi> Rank, to wit, of the <hi>Luxurious Sodomits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Remark</hi> is, concerning <hi>Julio</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> who ſtands as a <hi>ſtout Generaliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> of the laſt Rank, to wit, of <hi>Incurable Babylonians,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> is moſt fitly placed in that Station, as having far more of the <hi>Souldier,</hi> than of the <hi>Prelate</hi> in Him, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Italy,</hi> all his Popedom, in continual Wars, and for a pregnant proof, that this <hi>Romiſh God,</hi> was a <hi>Man of Mettal,</hi> This is the <hi>Pope,</hi> who paſſing over <hi>Tyber-Bridg,</hi> firſt Brandiſh'd his Sword, and then threw his Keys into the River, ſaying, If <hi>Peters Keys</hi> would not ſerve his Turn, then <hi>Pauls</hi> Sword ſhould do it Home.</p>
            <p>Such a Thraſonick Bravado would bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter become <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> than <hi>Julius Secundus</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52972:12"/>
               <hi>Rome.</hi> But I have been thinking, that 'tis a Thouſand pities, Famous <hi>Pope Joan</hi> had not her Lot in this Laſt Rank too, yea, and (were it not to Dethrone and Diſpoſſes this <hi>Heroick Hector) She</hi> might have ſtood in the Captains place there, as <hi>She</hi> doth in the Second Rank, <hi>[Detur digniori]</hi> is the Rule, She beſt deſerving it: for where could that <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> (as above) be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter placed? than among the <hi>Incurable Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians,</hi> and where could that <hi>Incurable Whore</hi> have been better order'd? than in the Front of that <hi>File</hi> of <hi>Defiled</hi> and <hi>Defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, this <hi>preſent Pope,</hi> Cardinal <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſchalcho,</hi> (who hath chang'd his Name into <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Eleventh,</hi>) is Repreſented to our View as ſtanding upon the Tail and Fag-end of thoſe <hi>Incurable Babylonians:</hi> We uſe to ſay, Such a perſon as Labors under a Mortal Incurable Diſeaſe, hath a <hi>[Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere Mei Deus,]</hi> writ upon his Door: who it is, that Writes the <hi>Continuation of</hi> Dr. <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi>'s <hi>Introduction,</hi> I know not, yet he Writes an <hi>Epitome</hi> of this our Cardinal <hi>Odeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalcho</hi>'s publick <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>Tranſactions,</hi> ſince his coming to be Groped in the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry Chair:</hi> and we are much obliged to that <hi>Author</hi> (who ever he is) for fixing this <hi>preſent Pope</hi> under the Head of <hi>Incurable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52972:13"/>
Babylonians,</hi> but I know not (in all the World) how to Reconcile the <hi>White Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter</hi> that <hi>Author</hi> giveth <hi>him,</hi> and the <hi>Black Title be</hi> ſeteth <hi>over him.</hi> The Deſcription of his Life there, ſeems to carry no Congruity with an <hi>Incurable Babylonian.</hi> 'Tis great pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that any miſtaking Candour ſhould make ſuch a Diſparity: but to let that paſs, come we now to give a more full and Impartial Account of his <hi>Riſe</hi> and <hi>Begining,</hi> &amp;c. So far as Hiſtorians lends any light <hi>hereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I find that <hi>this Perſon</hi> (ſo ſoon as any Fame found <hi>him</hi>) had his firſt noticed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity at <hi>Come,</hi> a place of note in the <hi>Dukedom of Millain</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> a <hi>Town,</hi> made the more Famous by being the Birth-place of the two <hi>Famous Plinys,</hi> and ſituated on the <hi>South</hi>-ſide of the <hi>Lacus La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius,</hi> which from this <hi>Town</hi> hath now the name of <hi>Lago di Como,</hi> through this Lake the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Addua</hi> runs; yet (as <hi>Geographers</hi> ſay) their two Waters do not mingle: Which two Remarks hath occaſion'd in Me <hi>two Wiſhes</hi> in this <hi>mans</hi> behalf. The firſt is, that as <hi>Pliny</hi> became the more Famous for ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour from perſecuting the poor Chriſtians in the Empire, by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting elegantly to Him, that He found no greater fault laid to the charge of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52972:13"/>
ſave this, that they did <hi>(Cantas Ante-lucanos canere) ſing Pſalms before day;</hi> upon which Letter the perſecution ceaſed: So would to God this <hi>preſent Pope</hi> might write ſuch an effectual Letter to the <hi>French King</hi> in the behalf of the poor perſecuted Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> (ſure I am, he can find no worſe faults in them) ſo ſtop the perſecution there, this would make him more <hi>Famous,</hi> than ever the Recovery of his <hi>Regalitys</hi> (he hath been ſo long contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for) can Render Him: whereas, to be outvy'd by a blind Heathen (ſuch was <hi>Pliny</hi>) in ſuch a good Work of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> (which are Works highly cryed up at <hi>Rome</hi>) may Render Him for ever <hi>Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</hi> Eſpecially if <hi>He</hi> be found to puſh it on and promote it, inſtead of putting a ſtop to it. The <hi>ſecond Wiſh</hi> is, Oh that this pretended Vicar of Chriſt may learn ſome Divine Leſſon, even from the very <hi>Nature</hi> of his own Country-River, which will not <hi>mingle</hi> its <hi>pure Streams</hi> with the puddle wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a <hi>corrupted ſtanding Lake:</hi> not to play the Huxter in Sophiſticating, and Adultera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the truth of the Goſpel, by mingling it with corrupt Traditions. There is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt <hi>Evangelical Doctrine</hi> in that Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Law, <hi>thou ſhalt not let thy Cattle Gender with a diverſe Kind, thou ſhalt not Sow thy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52972:14"/>
Field with a mingled Seed, neither ſhall a Garment mingled of Linnen and Wollen come upon thee</hi>] Levit. 19.19. to ſhew, that <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celanees</hi> in Religious Worſhip are both <hi>hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>hurtful</hi> to <hi>Men:</hi> and not onely the nature of <hi>His River,</hi> but alſo naturaliſts do teach Him not to mingle the <hi>Inventions of Men,</hi> with the <hi>Inſtitutions of God,</hi> for they ſay, that though <hi>Gold</hi> be ſo Ductile, as to be willing to mix and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate it ſelf with <hi>other Mettals,</hi> ſave onely with <hi>Latten,</hi> notwithſtanding, as to its out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Luſtre, it be ſo like it ſelf: ſo the true Church (which is call'd a <hi>golden Candleſtick</hi>) will not mix or embody her ſelf with the falſe (commonly called the <hi>Latin</hi>) Church, which ſtagnateth like a ſtinking Lake, though ſhe reſembleth the <hi>Spouſe,</hi> and <hi>ſits in the Temple of God,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.4. but indeed is the <hi>Apocalyptick Whore,</hi> and the moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Enemy to the Flock of Chriſt, in all the laſt Ages: This <hi>preſent Pope,</hi> while he was in his <hi>publick Capacity</hi> (omitting his <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,</hi> as not worth Recording) at this Town of <hi>Come,</hi> went under the name of <hi>Benedict Odeſchalci,</hi> of the Title of <hi>Saint Onuphrius</hi> and was created a <hi>Cardinal</hi> under <hi>Pope In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the 10th. <hi>March</hi> the 6th. in the year 1645. Upon which take theſe <hi>Remarks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52972:14"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis not eaſie to Aſſign the Reaſon why his proper <hi>praenomen</hi> (that of <hi>Benedict</hi>) ſhould become ſo diſguſtful to <hi>Him</hi> as to change it into <hi>Innocent</hi> (the Name of his Predeceſſours in the Chair) ſeeing it was (as it ſignifies) a <hi>bleſſed</hi> Name, and alſo the Name of ſome <hi>Popes</hi> before him, but more of that change of Names afterwards, when we come to his <hi>Popedom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There may a more probable conjecture be given for the change of his <hi>Sir-Name,</hi> to wit, <hi>Odeſchalcho,</hi> more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when it is Allowable to give an <hi>Italick</hi> Name an <hi>Attick Etymology,</hi> and ſo <hi>[nomen quaſi notamen] that Name</hi> hath an evil ſound, ſent, and ſenſe, ſignifying (not a <hi>Golden</hi>) but a <hi>Brazen Song.</hi> That which ſents and ſavours of <hi>Braſs</hi> (we uſually ſay) is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant to the Palate, and 'tis the more likely this Name might be diſguſtful to his Palate, ſeeing his Predeceſſour <hi>Sergius the Second,</hi> even quarelled with his own Name, which (before he was <hi>Pope</hi>) was <hi>[Bocca di Porco]</hi> ſignifying <hi>Swine-Mouth,</hi> or <hi>Hog-Face,</hi> and thinking that ill-ſounding Name not ſuitable to his Dignity, he therefore chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. And upon ſuch an Honourable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, if <hi>Hog-Face</hi> was ſo odious a Name to the former, why might not alſo <hi>Braſs-Face</hi> or <hi>Brazen-Face</hi> (as a <hi>Face of Braſs</hi> is an
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52972:15"/>
approbrious Phraſe amongſt us) be odious to this latter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to the Title of Saint <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius</hi> he was dignified with at <hi>Come,</hi> I ſhall onely ſay at this time (though much more might be added) what Tradition tells us of this <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> that he was a monkiſh Man, who lived a ſolitary Life for ſixty years, in which ſpace he ſaw no Man: had our <hi>Odeſ. chalcho</hi> Imitated this monkiſh <hi>Patroon,</hi> and trode in this <hi>Pattern's</hi> Steps, he had never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> much leſs a <hi>Pope,</hi> unto which <hi>converſing</hi> with Men, and <hi>conveying Kindneſſes</hi> to them (to oblige their Votes at Election) are neceſſary Ingredients, and which he to the utmoſt improved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As to his being made a <hi>Cardinal</hi> while at <hi>Come:</hi> this is one of the higheſt pitches and pinacles of Pride (the very next to the <hi>loftyeſt Spire</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf) that the Romiſh Clergy Aſpire to, for the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> are the <hi>Popes Senatours</hi> or Privy Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, and are called <hi>Cardinals,</hi> which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from <hi>Cardo,</hi> the <hi>Hinge</hi> of a Door, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon them (as the Door hangs upon the Hinge, and turns which way we will, either for opening or ſhutting) all the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Affairs of the Roman Church hang and are turned which way they pleaſe: thus the word <hi>[Cardinal]</hi> is uſually uſed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52972:15"/>
thus, that whereupon any thing moſt turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and dependeth, as to <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North,</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> are call'd <hi>Cardinal Points of the Compaſs.</hi> Thus alſo thoſe <hi>four principal Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, [Prudence, Juſtice, Fortitude,</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance]</hi> are call'd the <hi>Cardinal Vertues.</hi> And thus the Word is <hi>generally</hi> taken to denote ſomething that is <hi>Chief</hi> and <hi>Principle:</hi> So theſe <hi>Cardinals</hi> are: But the Hinge, upon which theſe <hi>Cardinals</hi> did themſelves at the firſt Hang, was very Low, and their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Extract very Contemptible: For this great Office did creep into the <hi>Roman</hi> Church thus, <hi>Pope Marcellus</hi> in the <hi>Third Century</hi> divided the City of <hi>Rome</hi> into 25 <hi>Pariſhes</hi> (ſome Authors call them <hi>Dioceſſes</hi>) over each of which He appointed a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> whoſe work was Aſſigned to Baptize Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens Converted, and to Bury the Dead within their ſeveral <hi>Precincts:</hi> Theſe were afterward called <hi>Cardinals,</hi> or <hi>Principal Prieſts,</hi> or <hi>Deacons,</hi> becauſe they had <hi>[Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Animarum]</hi> the Cure of Souls com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, and had others (in Sacred Orders alſo) under them: There be Three ſorts of <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> ſo called, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from their Four other Orders, <hi>(Door-Keeper, Readers, Exorciſts, Acolyths,</hi> or <hi>Taper-bearers,)</hi> Theſe are, Firſt, The <hi>Sub-Deacons,</hi> (whoſe Office is the Grope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52972:16"/>
Work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Secondly, The <hi>Deacon</hi> (who, with the <hi>former,</hi> hath the Honour only to kiſs the Biſhops Hand at the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,) See <hi>Roſſes View,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 451. The Third, Is the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> whom the <hi>Biſhop</hi> Kiſſeth to ſhew his <hi>Parity</hi> in Reſpect of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Idem Ibidem.</hi> Theſe ſame 25 <hi>Prieſts</hi> of ſo many Pariſhes in the City, being always ſo nigh the <hi>Pope,</hi> the more that <hi>he</hi> grew up gradually into his Grandeur, the higher did <hi>he</hi> draw up theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> (his Appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances) their poſture all along keeping pace with the <hi>Popes</hi> Pomp, <hi>Adeò ut quod in principio Oneri fuit, Tandem Aliquandò Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri eſſe Caepit.</hi> So, that which at firſt was but a <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Burdenſom</hi> Office, became at length an Employ of Dignity and Honour: Thus Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> Teſtifieth, That <hi>Pope Paſchal</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> cauſed the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the ſeveral Pariſhes in <hi>Rome,</hi> by reaſon of <hi>their</hi> nearneſs to his Perſon, their preſence at his Election, to be Honoured with a more Venerable Title, that is, to be called Cardinals, See <hi>Coſmogr. pag.</hi> 107. at the Top. Thus from a company of pitiful <hi>Pariſh Prieſts,</hi> they account themſelves not only Check-Mates to Princes, but alſo Compeers with Kings themſelves; but indeed they ought to be eſteemed the principal Limbs of the <hi>Beaſt Antichriſt;</hi> yea, they are ſo far Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52972:16"/>
with the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, that they muſt not (forſooth) ſo much as be let Bloud without his ſpecial Licenſe; 'tis (no doubt) for fear leaſt the Head ſhould be ſo concern'd in theſe his Special Members, as to Die with them by Sympathy: The Number of them at their firſt <hi>Roman Conſtitution</hi> (for want of a <hi>Divine Inſtitution</hi>) were, as is aforeſaid, <hi>Twenty Five,</hi> which Dr. <hi>Potter</hi> worthily Obſerves to be the exact Root Number of Six Hunndred Sixty Six, the <hi>Namber of the Beaſt;</hi> but now they are Multiplied like a Numerous Spawn, into much more than Double the Number; that depends wholy and ſolely at the <hi>Popes</hi> pleaſure, who can Blow them out of his Mouth as many as he pleaſeth; he can Breath out a <hi>Cardinal</hi> with as much eaſe, as he Breaths out the Holy Ghoſt; yea, for Doing ſome Notable Jobb in Hand, he can Breath out, or rather Spit out of his Palat or Pallace, a matter of Sixteen Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals at one Spit, as this preſent <hi>Pope</hi> hath lately done; Oh what an Improving Leap &amp; Advance hath <hi>he</hi> now made, whereas while he was but a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> he is then but a <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Creature</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> but now that he is become a God Almighty the Pope, he can be a Creator of his Creatures: <hi>Monſtrum Horrendum,</hi> &amp;c. Prodigious were his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52972:17"/>
(which not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> beſtowed upon him while a <hi>Cardinal,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Firſt, When ever he Rode abroad to take Freſh Air, His (Sir) Reverence was ſo Glorified (yet not ſo much as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was at his Transfiguration) with his Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Red Hat,</hi> and <hi>Rich Robes,</hi> that the Splendor of <hi>Beth</hi> theſe Dazel'd all Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Eyes, yea, the very Blaſt of his Body but paſſing by, Blew off all their Hats, and Bore ſo hard upon them, as to Blow them over, and made them fall down to Worſhip Him, and to ask of Him his Patriarchal Bleſſing, which He rarely beſtowed with that Ingenuity, as He in the Story did, who in ſo doing, ſaid, <hi>[Si Populus Vult De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipi, Decipiatur.]</hi> Light cheap Words make Fools fain. No doubt but His Shadow, (as he is now Pope, and <hi>Peters Succeſſor</hi>) can cure as many Diſeaſes, as that of <hi>Peters</hi> did. <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> the <hi>Fourth,</hi> Graced the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> with a <hi>Red</hi> (Fools <hi>Cap,</hi> or) <hi>Hat,</hi> by his Ordinance in the Twelfth <hi>Century;</hi> and in the Fourteenth, <hi>Pope Pius</hi> the Second Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced their Splendor yet Higher, with moſt Stately Scarlet Gowns, <hi>(Dr. Heylins Coſmogr. pag.</hi> 108. <hi>at the bottom.)</hi> Thus were they Attired in ſuch Antick, Gawdy and Pedantick Dreſſes, as neither <hi>Chriſt</hi> nor his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ever Strutted about in, which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52972:17"/>
muſt Declare to all the World, that this is the <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and none need ſay of <hi>Him,</hi> as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſaid often to Chriſt, <hi>[Art thou He that ſhould come, or may we look for another?]</hi> No, this is the <hi>Red Letter-Man,</hi> in his <hi>Red Hat</hi> and <hi>Scarlet Gown.</hi> This is the <hi>Bloudy</hi> and <hi>Scarlet Coloured Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second eminent priviledge this <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> was dignified with by his Creator the <hi>Pope,</hi> is, that whatever condemned Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor (juſt going to the place of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) could but be ſo happy as to meet this Man in his Ponticalibus in the way of his Progreſs, <hi>He</hi> was immediatly to be Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his Life ſpared, that He might evermore Admire and Adore this his <hi>Romiſh Saviour.</hi> 'Tis pitty his clemency is not more exerciſed out of deſign in this Life-Saving Work: Oh what a choice Act of Mercy might He ſometimes do here in but <hi>croſſing</hi> the way at a right Juncture, betwixt <hi>Newgate</hi> and <hi>Tyburn,</hi> when his Pontifical Preſence is bleſt with ſuch an excellent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue as both to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> the Nations Law, (which is mortally broken) and <hi>Save</hi> alſo the Life and Soul of the condemned.</p>
            <p>A Third <hi>Immunity</hi> He had alſo in that <hi>Cardinal Capacity,</hi> was, that no <hi>Cardinal</hi> can be Condemned for the moſt Capital Crime, except He can firſt be Convicted by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52972:18"/>
the Teſtimony of Seventy Two Witneſſes. By this means, a <hi>Cardinal</hi> may ſafely ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture to be the greateſt <hi>Villain</hi> in the World, not onely becauſe the Canon-Law ſaith <hi>[Eccleſia ſit libera]</hi> let Church-Men be free from ſecular Cenſures, but alſo (though the aforeſaid may fail) if they do but obſerve their own Jeſuitical Rule <hi>[ſi non caſtè, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cautè]</hi> He may without hazard perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate <hi>Whoredom, Treaſon,</hi> the worſt of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, ſo he do it with caution, and he deſerves to be hang'd ſeventy two times over, that will act his Villany in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſeventy two perſons, that may all come in as joynt Witneſſes againſt Him: The Law of the true and onely wiſe God (<hi>ſuppoſing</hi> the Teſtimony of <hi>two or three Witneſſes</hi> ſufficient) is but comparatively an Inſipid Sentence: but the Law of their Lord God the Pope is far more profound, ſaying, two or three and twenty are not enough of Witneſſes, even againſt the <hi>Inferiour Clergy.</hi> There muſt (ſay they) be twenty ſeven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a <hi>Deacon,</hi> ſixty four againſt a Prieſt, and ſeventy two againſt a <hi>Biſhop-Cardinal. Dianae compendium,</hi> pag. 85. No wonder if the Romiſh Clergy be the greateſt Rogues, and vileſt Villains in the World: No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if they carry ſo deep, and ſo Epidemick
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52972:18"/>
a Tincture as the only and unparallel'd Tools to be employed by <hi>Belzebub;</hi> for <hi>Murdering of Kings, Blowing up of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> managing not only Privat and Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Aſſaſinations, but alſo Publick and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Maſſacres, to Aſtoniſhment; to ſay nothing of Burning down Cities and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-Towns, and many more Matchleſs Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, whereof how far this <hi>their Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (both while <hi>Cardinal,</hi> and when <hi>Pope</hi>) in Conjunction with his <hi>Unholy Sons</hi> have been guilty, the Sequel will Demonſtrate; and that <hi>Ex abundanti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Fourth <hi>Priviledg</hi> (or rather a Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative) this <hi>Cardinal</hi> had, while ſo, was, That whoſoever would dare to Offend or Injure (in any kind) his <hi>Worſhip</hi> or <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalſhip,</hi> though the <hi>Offence</hi> were only an opprobrious Word, and though the <hi>Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> were ſo <hi>Lofty</hi> as a King or an <hi>Emperor</hi> (who apprehend themſelves above the comprehenſions of the Law) yet the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Canon-Law</hi> Runs thus ſeverely againſt them, <hi>[Laeſae Majeſtatis Rei Sunt, cujus cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſint Ordinis, Imò Imperator ipſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Et In paenas Bullae Caenae Incurrent.]</hi> Such Offenders againſt a <hi>Cardinal</hi> (yea though it be the <hi>Emperor</hi> himſelf) ſhall be Judged <hi>Guilty of High-Treaſon,</hi> and ſhall Incur the Pains and Penalties of <hi>Excommunication, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52972:19"/>
&amp;c. Was not this a <hi>Lofty Beaſt</hi> then? <hi>Exalting himſelf above all that is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God,</hi> or <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> even of the very higheſt Form, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4. He might, while in <hi>that Capacity</hi> only, challenge the Stouteſt King or Emperor, to affront his Cardinalſhip, while he ſtood thus ſtrongly Guarded by his Canon-Law, to Batter them down with its Horrible and Terrible Canon-Bullets; nay, That <hi>Canon-Law</hi> did not only thus ſecure his Perſon, but it alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to protect his very Houſe, and all his Hang-bys, or Menial Servants, to all his Creatures and Favourites in his Preſence; even all theſe his Appertinances are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with that Diſeaſe called <hi>[Noli me Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere]</hi> They muſt not (forſooth) be <hi>touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> though never ſo Criminal, 'tis an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front of the higheſt Nature, even <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> it ſelf, and therefore (with my conſent) ſhould any of his <hi>Clerks</hi> be affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the <hi>Kings-Evil</hi> (as they are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run with the <hi>Popes-Evil</hi>) a Caveat ſhall be Entred to Debar them of the <hi>Royal-Touch,</hi> leaſt by a Male-Improvement thereof, they turn their <hi>Canon</hi>-Mouth againſt the King: How, neither the <hi>Cardinal,</hi> nor any of his <hi>Attendants</hi> (every one bearing for his Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the ſame with the Baſe Thiſtle, <hi>[Nemo me Impunè laceſſit,]</hi> none can touch me
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52972:19"/>
without Pricking their own Fingers) ſtand Fortified with the <hi>Grand</hi> Diabolo's, or Great Canons of that Canon-Law. See <hi>Dianoe Compendium, pag.</hi> 93.</p>
            <p>The Fifth Prerogative this <hi>Cardinal</hi> had, above all Kings and Emperors, is, That whereas <hi>They, Poor Low Shrubs</hi> (in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of ſuch a <hi>Tall Cedar</hi> as a <hi>Cardinal</hi> is) muſt humble themſelves to the very Foot of the Pope, muſt Honour the very Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of his Shoe-ſtrings, or rather Adore the Sparkling Diamonds, wherewith the Buckles of his Pantofle is moſt Richly E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nambled, and the Higheſt Honour that thoſe <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperours</hi> muſt have vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to them, (a Glorious Vouchſafement and Low Condeſcention in his <hi>Unholineſs</hi> indeed) is only to Kiſs the Stinking Toe of his Gowty Gulls: but when this <hi>Cardinal</hi> came to pay his Viſits, and do his Homage, unto his Mighty God <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the <hi>Tenth,</hi> (his immediate Predeceſſor) he had the Honour (without any proſtrating poſture, ſave only a <hi>ſlight Congee</hi>) to Kiſs his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſes Hands, with a Mental Reſervation too, (Right <hi>Romaniſt</hi> like) wiſhing him well in his Grave, that he might (upon ſuch an Irreſiſtible Reſignation) yeild up his Pontifical Chair to him: Nay, the <hi>Royal Complement</hi> of <hi>Kiſſing the Popes Hand</hi> only,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52972:20"/>
was not all the Honour he had from him, but he is allowed to <hi>Kiſs</hi> the <hi>Popes Mouth</hi> too. <hi>Lorinus</hi> the Jeſuit, in <hi>Act.</hi> 6. doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg this <hi>Ceremony</hi> (as to matter of Fact) to be the <hi>Cardinals Prerogative</hi> above <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperours:</hi> If the Kiſſing of the Biſhop by the Prieſt at his Ordination, do declare a Parity, as above: So this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe muſt be an Indication, that a <hi>Cardinal</hi> is a <hi>Popes</hi> Fellow, yet Advanced above Kings and Emperours, (contemptible Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Offices to his) by this mutual Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracement. The <hi>Hebrew</hi> Rabbins do Read theſe words, <hi>[Gnal Pi Jehovah] Deut.</hi> 34.5. which we Tranſlate <hi>[According to the Word of the Lord]</hi> in this Senſe, That <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Died at the Mouth of Jehovah,</hi> (which indeed the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Words do Genuinely and Gramatically ſignifie,) as if God had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away <hi>Moſes</hi> his Soul out of his Body with a Kiſs in a moſt friendly manner: could this Lord God the <hi>Pope (Clement</hi> the <hi>Tenth)</hi> have done ſo to <hi>Cardinal Odeſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho,</hi> when he Kiſs'd him, it had been no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than <hi>Oſculum Iſcarioticum.</hi> rather a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous, than an Amicable Kiſs, in ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Market, of deſigning to become his Succeſſor upon the Papal Throne, and then had the World wanted him for Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Eleventh,</hi> though both the Place and the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52972:20"/>
Title might have been ſupplied by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon: Had this happen'd ſo, <hi>That Pope</hi> might have cry'd Quits for his wiſhing (in his Mental Reſervation afore mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) the Pontifical Chair before the Time: what loſs this might have been to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, I know not, but this I know upon more Infallible proofs than his own Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that had he <hi>Died at the Mouth of his Lord God the</hi> Pope, when that Complemental Kiſs paſs'd betwixt him and his Predeceſſor, he had undoubtedly paſs'd off the Stage with leſs Guilt, the <hi>Horrid Popiſh Plot,</hi> the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> and a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more <hi>Diabolical Intriegues</hi> ſince that, will lay with weight upon ſome Bodies Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſooner or later. <hi>Veniet, Veniet, qui malè Judicata Rejudicabit Dies:</hi> There is a Day coming, which ſhall Judg Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly all Matters over again, (though at preſent they be Huſh'd up in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and <hi>this may</hi> be done even in this World.</p>
            <p>I add to all the former the Sixth Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, For ſo many muſt be the Number, that it may the better Symbolize, and carry a Correſpondency with the Number of the Beaſts Name, which conſiſts of Three Sixes, [666.] and therefore ſeveral <hi>Popes</hi> bore the Number of <hi>Sixtus,</hi> and had I been
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52972:21"/>
of the Conclave (an Honour I am no way Ambitious of) I would have adviſed the Cabal, that this <hi>Pope Elect</hi> ſhould have taken upon him no other Name, ſave that former Name of <hi>Sixtus,</hi> and I would have preſs'd this Cogent Argument, That ſeeing there had been before, <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Firſt, the Second, the Third, the Fourth, and the Fifth, now One that will be Stiled <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Sixth, not only makes the <hi>Odd</hi> Number <hi>Even,</hi> but alſo the very Name will carry along with it a moſt Grateful Sound and Symphony: This only would have been the miſchief thereof, that it might have Bordered a little too near the <hi>Number of the Name</hi> of the Apocalyptick Beaſt, for this Name would have conſiſted of <hi>Two Sixes, (Sixtus</hi> the Sixth) but that Name conſiſts of <hi>Three:</hi> notwithſtanding this little difference (in an <hi>Unit</hi>) it might have Sounded ſome Alarm to the World: This ſo much neceſſary <hi>Sixth</hi> Priviledg which this Cardinal <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> had, was, That his Cardinalſhip did Conſtitute him an <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Prince,</hi> whereby he became a fit Mate and Side-Fellow (ſtanding upon equal and even Ground) with the moſt Potent Secular Prince in <hi>Europe,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to Comport with this Princely Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Canon Law allows him a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52972:21"/>
Grandeur, Sumptuous Furniture, and all manner of Pompous Splendor for Supporting the Honour of that Dignity, for to be one of the College of Cardinals is the Penultimate Promotion in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, it being the very Higheſt and Uppermoſt Step, from which one or other of theſe Crafty Climbers, Lands at laſt into <hi>Peters Chair.</hi> And ſeeing <hi>Wealth</hi> is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible Perquiſite, as it is commonly call'd the <hi>Sinews of War,</hi> ſo 'tis no leſs the <hi>Nurſe to Honour,</hi> yea, oft times more than <hi>Vertue,</hi> upon this account, Their Canon Law allows them moſt Rich Revenues, moſt Rapacious Offices and Employs, wherein (as if they had got the <hi>Philoſophers Stone</hi>) they turn all they touch into Gold and Guineys: The <hi>Italian</hi> Author of the <hi>Juſt weight of the Scarlet Gown,</hi> gives a Candid and Ingenuous Account, (keeping the Scales <hi>even</hi>) of thoſe <hi>Crafty Intrigues,</hi> and many Subtle Tricks, that thoſe Arch-Politicians do put in Practice to Enrich themſelves, to fill their Coffers by Sale of Offices that are Vacant, by Penſions from the Court of <hi>Foreign Princes,</hi> (both <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi>) who all ſtrive, not only to Counterballance one another, but alſo, by a pretty <hi>Greaſo-Fiſto,</hi> with Yellow Ointment to Tilt the Ballance, and ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52972:22"/>
Advance their own Faction upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, through the prevailing Intereſt of thoſe their cloſely obliged Creatures the <hi>Cardinals,</hi> who have ſuch a mighty Influence upon all Debates and Reſolves in that Pragmatick and Superintendent Court, which <hi>Lords</hi> it, and <hi>Laws</hi> it, (or at leaſt would willingly do ſo) not only over <hi>Gods Herritage</hi> the Church, but alſo over the whole Habitable World.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scarlet Gown</hi> Author, in his <hi>Epiſt. Dedic.</hi> ſpeaks of the ſeveral Applications that are made to this Conſiſtory of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, from all Popiſh <hi>Princes</hi> and States, eſpecially from the Two Mighty Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> by their Ambaſſadors, who ever lay <hi>Ledger</hi> at that Court, and who always Addreſs themſelves to the moſt Politick and Powerful of theſe Cardinals, ſtriving to Outvie each other in their proffer of Fat Penſſons to them, giving them the beſt Spiritual Dignities and Promotions their Two Kingdoms can afford them, (which in either of them are plentiful enough) provided always, they will be engaged thereby to Eſpouſe (as much as ever they may) the Intereſts of their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors Crown, to which they are thus obliged. Herein theſe Court-Penſioners do Try the Trick of a Treacherous <hi>Judas,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:52972:22"/>
(who with his <hi>[Quid Dabitis?] What will ye give me?</hi> and <hi>I will betray my Innocent Maſter,</hi> &amp;c.) rather than play the part of Faithful <hi>Peter,</hi> (whoſe Succeſſors, though unlike him, ſave only in Denying his Lord, they would be reputed) in Defending his Innocent Maſter from thoſe that Aſſaulted him: for notwithſtanding never ſo ſtrong Engagements and Aſſurances; Oh what a ſlippery Hold either or both thoſe great Princes have of theſe their <hi>Cardinal</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, who frequently (and upon very ſlight occaſions) are found to warp into the contrary Faction, which Verifies the Vulgat Proverb, <hi>'Tis Hard to make a Faſt Bargain with a Looſe Chapman:</hi> They how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, in playing thus at <hi>Faſt</hi> and <hi>Looſe</hi> can notably ſerve their own Ends, and like Bad Lawyers can take a Bribe upon both Sides, when they are Courted by both the Kings. Eſpecially thoſe Cardinals that ſit neareſt the Papal Chair, and are in the faireſt Capacity to Climb next into it, as was the Happy Caſe of this our Cardinal, and therefore muſt be Highly Courted by Foreign Agents in the Name of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; The Height of whoſe Ambition it was to oblige him. Thus we ſee this <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detto Odeſchalcho</hi> had fair opportunities for gaining Wealth enough to maintain his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52972:23"/>
Grandeur, the Canon-Law doth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand theſe Cardinals, that, beſides their Living upon the Churches Revenues, to catch what they can for themſelves, (may we Add, <hi>Per Fas &amp; Nefas, Vel Vi, Vel Clam, Vel Precariò,</hi> either by Hook or Crook, to wit, the Croſier Staff,) upon the Account of Aggrandizing the <hi>Roman</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, which Poverty would render Contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, <hi>Dianae Compendium,</hi> pag. 88.</p>
            <p>How far this Cardinal comply'd (as who of that Catholick Faith would not) with that Canon-command, we ſhall have an Account By and By: But before we can come to that, Here are Two miſchievous Stumbling-ſtones lays in our Way like a Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Blockado's, which who ever were able to Roll away out of our Way, would do us a very great Kindneſs; when ſet faſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is this, Suppoſe this Cardinal had been a <hi>Monk,</hi> 'tis not to ſuppoſe what ought not to be ſuppoſed; for ſome <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts</hi> (as his Fore-Name and ſome Popes Name were) had been <hi>Benedictine</hi> Monks, and at their entrance into their Monaſteries had ſolemnly vowed <hi>perpetual Poverty;</hi> how could this Monkiſh Man with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience Relinquiſh his <hi>vowed Poverty?</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Riches ſo faſt that he got the <hi>Devil and all,</hi> (as will appear afterwards) became an
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52972:23"/>
               <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Prince,</hi> Ride his Progreſs in all Prince-like Equipage, never proud <hi>Haman</hi> more Highly Honoured, and never any Triumphant <hi>Caeſar</hi> or Conquerour better Arrayed than He in his Richeſt Robes for Splendour and Glory: Let any Man come forth and tell me the Conſiſtency of theſe two Contraries, <hi>&amp; erit mihi magnus Apollo.</hi> He that can rightly Reconcile them, ſhall be my Oracle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tuſh</hi> (ſaith the Romiſh Caſuiſts, one of the New <hi>Quacks</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits</hi>) I can with a wet Finger make theſe two Contraries Jump friendly into one, <hi>two odds</hi> make <hi>even</hi> (as Two odd Threes make even Six, <hi>ſtill he will harp upon the Number Six,</hi> as above) and why may not <hi>two at odds</hi> meet in <hi>even</hi> alſo. This is the Learned Gloſs of the Popiſh Caſuiſts upon this Caſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the <hi>General,</hi> but more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (he ſaith) this <hi>Vow of Poverty</hi> was taken with a mental Reſervation, that he reſolved to be poor, no longer, than while he could not poſſibly be Rich, and ſo the word <hi>[Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual]</hi> in the Vow muſt be <hi>vox aequivoca,</hi> and to be taken with equivocation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such Dirt-Dawbers (that <hi>Dawb with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper'd Morter</hi>) are the Jeſuitical Caſuiſts, yea, many <hi>Monks</hi> can play the pranks of a <hi>Monkey</hi> (there is not much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52972:24"/>
their Names) who can ſlip his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar on <hi>for his Maſters Pleaſure,</hi> and with as much eaſe, can ſlip it off again <hi>for his own,</hi> The <hi>Monk</hi> can play at faſt and looſe with his <hi>ſtrict Vow</hi> as well as the <hi>Monkey</hi> with his <hi>ſtrait Collar.</hi> But above all Caſuiſts that ſpeak home to this Caſe, hear what an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Pope <hi>(papa in Cathedrà non poteſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare)</hi> and that <hi>Innocent</hi> the 10th, (one of the laſt before this) ſpeaketh; He ſurely, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeak but like a moſt profound Oracle: I have heard ſome Judicious Clients ſay, when I want Councel, I will go to the <hi>Head,</hi> and not to the <hi>Tail,</hi> meaning, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeſt Councellors at Law, and not to the mean, pittiful, underling Lawyers: let us do ſo here, omitting all other ſcribling puny Caſuiſts in <hi>Popiſh Schools,</hi> and hear what this great Oracle ſaith out of <hi>Peters unerring Chair:</hi> This <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> the Tenth, when he was but Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> made a promiſe in the Conclave to Marry his onely Nephew into the Family of the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berinos</hi> (one of the three grand pontifical Factions, <hi>Paulino</hi> and <hi>Pamphilian</hi> being the other two, in that Sacred Colledge or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory) the ſame Promiſe he privatly made to his Nephew alſo; howbeit, he ſoon chang'd his mind (being then not in the Papal Chair and ſo, nor Infallible) and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52972:24"/>
Him to a Scarlet Gown (inſtead of a Wife) which was far better, and which (he thought) would beſt prevent divers Emergent Differencies that were likely to ariſe by Marrying one of the <hi>Pamphilian</hi> Family to a Wife of the <hi>Barberinos,</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Faction, which yet had been whead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into a Beleif of this great Match for their She-Cozen, becauſe it was ſo ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publickly promiſed by the Cardinal (the Unkle of the Gentleman, or in plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Terms, the Father of the Baſtard) in their Sacred Colledge of Cardinals, where there was a dead weight of Living Witneſſes thereof. Notwithſtanding this <hi>Promiſe,</hi> a Sacred thing in it ſelf, made in a Sacred place, and before ſo many ſacred Perſons (according to Popiſh Sentiments) he made a ſhift to <hi>cozen</hi> both <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>She-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen:</hi> whereupon, not long after His Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption into the Papal Chair (no doubt but his Nephew in his new Scarlet Gown, gave his Uncle an heaty lift thither) Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Antonio Barberinos;</hi> having ſtill the grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of his Gizzard for the late cheating affront, makes his Addreſs to his New-Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and Now-Crowned <hi>Holineſs</hi> (expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing but what was Holy Redreſſes ſuitable to his new Title, to ſweeten unto all his new Crown and Dignity) He therefore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52972:25"/>
brake out into thoſe words to this new Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 10th. (into which he had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Name <hi>Pamphylio</hi>) ſaying, <hi>Moſt Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Father, your Tranſactions about your Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew (in Marrying him to a Scarlet Gown, and not to our Cozen) doth not well correſpond with your promiſes made to us in the Conclave, when you was but Cardinal:</hi> Hereupon his new <hi>Un-Holineſs</hi> (with a great deal of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, as became his Place) as Un-Holily An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, thus ſaying, <hi>Tell me my Lord, who was He, that made ſuch promiſes to you? Was it not Cardinal Pamphilio?</hi> Yes, ſaith <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> upon which the Pope turns ſhort upon him, and bids him go challeng his Promiſe of <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> for he was not the Man of that Name now, His Name was <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Tenth,</hi> and not that Man you Imagine me to be: At this, <hi>Antonio</hi> Raged, and like a new <hi>Mongi Bello,</hi> Fire ſtarted out of his Eyes, and like Old <hi>Orlando,</hi> ſtamps with his Feet upon the Ground, when he heard the Infallible Chair ſpeak more Fallibly and Fallaciouſly, than ever the Devil did at his Delphos-Oracle: In this Tranſport his Voice alſo Vomited out ſome ſevere Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives againſt his Lord God the Pope, and in an High Diſguſt, Uncivilly turns his Tail upon his Blaſphemed, as well as Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming Idol, Excommunicates himſelf
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52972:25"/>
from the <hi>Sacred Conſiſtory,</hi> and from the Metrapolitan City of <hi>Rome</hi> (the very place of his own Nativity) flies into <hi>France</hi> to be Protected by the <hi>French</hi> King, at whoſe Devotion he had all along been in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, leaving all his Riches (he had Vaſtly ſcraped together) and Revenues behind him: See the Subſtance of this whole Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the Author of the <hi>Juſt Weight of the Scarlet Gown,</hi> his own <hi>Preface</hi> to his Book; who tells us likewiſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 68. That this <hi>Don Antonio Barberino</hi> (who thus Diſ-reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this profound, more than <hi>Jeſuitical,</hi> the Diabolical Salvo of his Holy Father) was none of the Beſt, who kept for his Miſs or Whore, <hi>La Checa Bufona,</hi> upon whom he waſted moſt Vaſt Sums of Money, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 69.</p>
            <p>Mark here, This Papal <hi>Diſtinction</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Difference (to wit, it was not <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the Pope, but <hi>Pamphilio</hi> the Cardinal, that made the Promiſe, and therefore not at all obliging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is the Beſt Bramble-Buſh, that the Infallible Chair it ſelf can find out, wherewith to ſtop the Gap in a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Conſcience; and if this will ſerve as a ſufficient Salvo for the Supreme Pope himſelf, much more for his Underling, a <hi>Cardinal;</hi> and ſo our <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> is brought off with flying Colours; It was not <hi>Odeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalcho</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52972:26"/>
the <hi>Cardinal</hi> that <hi>Vowed perpetual Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty,</hi> it was only <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> the <hi>Monk</hi> that did ſo, I am not He that made that Vow, 'tis not obliging to me, as a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> but leaſt of all, as now I am <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such ſlippery Tricks of the <hi>Monkey,</hi> we find the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> can play, as well as the <hi>Monks;</hi> for <hi>Caſimer</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> could (by his Fervent Prayers to his Founder <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi>) obtain an effectual Diſpenſation for his Acquitment from his <hi>Holy Orders</hi> to Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a Crown, the Jewels whereof had a Sovereign Vertue to Salve all Wounds of Conſcience, and to give him a <hi>Quietus Eſt:</hi> Hereupon he became the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Poland:</hi> but while I think of it, Take this pleaſant Story, I have ſometimes Read with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency, 'tis this, The Biſhop of <hi>Triers</hi> (I think, but am ſure it was one of thoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that are the <hi>Electoral Princes</hi> of the <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Germany</hi>) was found fault with for ſome Notorious Extravagances in his Publick Miniſtrations, by a very <hi>Grave Senator,</hi> Who told him, Such Groſs Actings were a Scandal to his Lawn Sleeves and Mitre; all the Apology that Proud <hi>Prelate</hi> could make for himſelf, was this, He An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That he did not thoſe things as he was a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> but as he was a <hi>Prince:</hi> But the <hi>Senator</hi> Replies in a cutting Reprimend,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52972:26"/>
ſaying, <hi>If the Devil get the Prince for ſuch Crimes, I pray you; what will become of the Biſhop.</hi> This Non-plus did not admit of a Rejoinder; and is there not <hi>par Ratio</hi> in both theſe Caſes of Conſcience aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, If the Devil get <hi>Pamphilio</hi> the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal for breaking his Promiſe, (contrary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.) what will become of <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Pope;</hi> it may be, he hath got them <hi>Both</hi> together at one Mouthful (being but one Individual Man) already, ſeeing Pope <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the <hi>Tenth,</hi> who was before, <hi>Cardinal Pamphilio,</hi> is now Trip'd off the Stage, and out <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> is got into the Chair in his Room: So likewiſe, If the Devil get the <hi>Monk</hi> for breaking his <hi>Vow of perpetual Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty,</hi> what will become of the <hi>Rich Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> ſure I am, Though the Devil hath not already made one Mouthful of them both, yet, the <hi>Pope</hi> (the Devils Eldeſt Son) hath done it, for both <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> the <hi>Monk</hi> (as ſome ſay) and <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> the <hi>Cardinal</hi> are at once Swallowed up by this preſent Pope, <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Eleventh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Upſhot of the whole in a word is this, I Refer to the Judicious Reader, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this <hi>Grave Senator,</hi> or the Jeſuits (<hi>Azorius, Navar,</hi> &amp;c.) yea the <hi>Infallible Chair</hi> it ſelf, be the better <hi>Caſuiſt;</hi> and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Don Antonio Barberino,</hi> the <hi>Crock-Back</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:52972:27"/>
Nephew to Pope <hi>Urban</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> were not a <hi>Straighter</hi> Man of the Two, that Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hord thoſe wicked Evaſions of Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the <hi>Tenth,</hi> as above.</p>
            <p>But having well wearied both my <hi>Self</hi> and my <hi>Reader,</hi> with lifting at this great <hi>Stone</hi> that lay in our Way, and yet cannot get it Removed out of the Way half ſo well as was <hi>Amaſa</hi>'s Stab'd Body, that ſtop'd the <hi>March</hi> of the Army, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.12. 'Tis high time to leave it, and to try our Strength in a Lift or Two at the <hi>Second,</hi> which in like manner obſtructs our paſſage, in giving a particular Character of this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Objection</hi> is, Whether theſe pretended Governors of the Church, the Popiſh <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Cardinals,</hi> abounding in all manner of <hi>Pride, Pomp</hi> and <hi>Luxury,</hi> can by any ſober Mind be Deemed the <hi>Rightful</hi> Succeſſors of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who all did ſo oft Recommend <hi>Self-Denyal</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To this, in ſhort, I ſhall Anſwer, with a Story that I have Read many Years ago, and which I have lately met with in the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Cardinals,</hi> pag. 46. The Author of <hi>Nipotiſmo di Roma,</hi> (wherein he ſhews how Sedulous every Pope is to promote his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews or Baſtards) Relates the <hi>Matter of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52972:27"/>
Fact</hi> thus, being both an <hi>Eye</hi> and an <hi>Ear</hi>-Witneſs thereof in Perſon himſelf, ſaying, I Remember a certain Sermon I heard in a Covent in <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the preſence of Two <hi>Cardinals,</hi> (it may be our <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> was one of them) and Cardinal <hi>Sacchetti</hi> was the other; The Preacher was a <hi>Bare Footed Franciſcan,</hi> who ſeem'd a poor pitiful Creature to look upon, yet geting into the Pulpit (on the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent</hi>) in a very great Auditory, after an <hi>Ave-Maria,</hi> and Two or Three Cringes (as is uſual) with his Knee, riſing up again upon his Feet, and pulling his Cappuce or Cowle upon his Head, down almoſt over his Eyes, he pauſed a while (in this poſture) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeaking a word, and fixing his Eyes ſtedfaſtly upon the <hi>Cardinals</hi> that ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, without Naming any Text at all, he breaks out abruptly into theſe words, [St. <hi>Peter was a Fool,</hi> St. <hi>Paul was a Fool,</hi> all the <hi>Apoſtles were Fools,</hi> all <hi>the Holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> all the <hi>Primitive Saints of the Church of Jeſus Chriſt our Redeemer, were Fools.</hi>]</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cardinals</hi> were ſtrangely Stun'd with theſe words, and ſtood as Inſenſible as Two Statues, the People alſo, and I among the reſt, Admiring this unuſual Freak, were content enough to Attend the Attendency of it: The <hi>Fryar,</hi> after ſome ſmall ſilence
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52972:28"/>
(which he purpoſely did, to obſerve the Reſentments of his Auditory) began his Diſcourſe as followeth, [<hi>You that are Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, do not you believe, you ſhall be Saved?</hi> I know your Anſwer, <hi>Yes,</hi> Father <hi>Fryar, we do. And you People, you are certain of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe?</hi> without Doubt, you will ſay, <hi>Yes</hi> too. <hi>Yes,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Fryar,</hi> What, will Turning Night into Day, by Feaſting, Sporting and Luxury? Will Frequenting Play-Houſes, Whore-Houſes, and a Living in all manner of Debauchery, bring <hi>you [People]</hi> to Heaven?</p>
            <p>As for <hi>you [Prelates,]</hi> Will your Wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Purple</hi> aad <hi>Scarlet,</hi> Will your Glittering in Gold and Silver, Will your Riding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and Carreeceing about in Gawdy Coaches, and when you come out of them, Will the having your Silken Trains carry'd after you in the Street, bring you to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? Will your Spoiling the Walls of the <hi>Church,</hi> to Adorn the Walls of your <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and will your Subtracting from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to beſtow upon the World, bring you thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thither? Would you Oh <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> be Saved in this manner? Is this the <hi>way to Salvation? which</hi> we are told is not a <hi>Broad</hi> but a <hi>Narrow Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then certainly all the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all the <hi>Saints of the Primitive Church</hi> might
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52972:28"/>
have been Saved in the ſame Way, as well as you; and then as certainly they were all <hi>Mad Men</hi> and <hi>Fools,</hi> to <hi>Wander up and down in Sheep Skins,</hi> and <hi>Goat Skins,</hi> being <hi>Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> and <hi>Afflicted,</hi> to Undergo the <hi>Hard Tryals of Cruel Mockings and Scourgings,</hi> yea, <hi>moreover of Bonds and Impriſonments,</hi> yet higher, they were <hi>Mad Men</hi> and <hi>Fools</hi> to <hi>be Stoned,</hi> to be <hi>Sawn Aſunder,</hi> to be <hi>Slain with the Sword,</hi> and to be <hi>Tortured</hi> and <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented,</hi> not <hi>Accepting Deliverance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35, 36, 37, 38. If <hi>your Way</hi> be the Way to Heaven.</p>
            <p>But the miſtake is on your part, Oh <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> They were all <hi>prudent</hi> and <hi>pious Men,,</hi> 'Tis <hi>You</hi> that are the <hi>Madmen</hi> and <hi>Fools,</hi> and not <hi>They.</hi> 'Tis <hi>You</hi> that propoſe a new way of Salvation to your Selves; which will beſt comport with your own Vanity and Villany, even ſuch a way, as is not onely contrary to the Holy Goſpel, but to the very light of <hi>Right Reaſon</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>This ſingle ſtory is ſufficient of it ſelf, to Demonſtrate what kind of Succeſſours theſe <hi>Cardinals</hi> (and amongſt the reſt our <hi>Odeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalcho</hi>) are to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> The <hi>pattern</hi> and the <hi>portraiture</hi> do correſpond like <hi>Harp</hi> and <hi>Harrow,</hi> which made the <hi>Italian Painter</hi> Draw the Pictures of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> with a very deep Tincture of a Red Vermilion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52972:29"/>
Colour in both their Complexions, and when ſome <hi>Cardinals</hi> blamed him for putting an Abuſe upon their holy Predeceſſours (to Limn them more like <hi>Good Fellows,</hi> who had been taking a Cup of <hi>Nims,</hi> a little too much of the comforting Creature) He Smartly yet Modeſtly Anſwered, No, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, you miſtake my Genuine meaning, for there you may behold thoſe two <hi>Holy Apoſtles</hi> no other than <hi>Bluſhing</hi> at <hi>you</hi> their ſuch <hi>Unholy Succeſſours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Paragraph with that ſtrange Prayer of a <hi>Proteſtant Divine</hi> upon his Reading a <hi>Gazet,</hi> who there found, how in the Vacancy of the <hi>Roman</hi> See, ſome Cardinals were conſulting, that the next Pope when Created, ſhould be bound to diſcard his <hi>Nephews,</hi> thoſe <hi>Suckers of the Churches Treaſure.</hi> He Zealouſly Ejaculated this ſhor, but pithy, Petition, ſaying, [<hi>God Almighty Remove theſe good Thoughts out of the Minds of theſe Cardinals,</hi> for <hi>the Scandal of their Church, are the Edification of ours,</hi> and Diſturbances amongſt them, gives a Sweet Repoſe to us: <hi>Hiſtory of Cardinals,</hi> pag. 132.</p>
            <p>Suitable to that before, is this, that which followeth after. Another <hi>Divine</hi> Diſcourſing with Cardinal <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi>'s Chaplain, and asking him what he was, he Anſwered, <hi>I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52972:29"/>
am a Prieſt,</hi> and pray you, ſaith the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, what is your Maſter whom you Serve, Oh Sir (quoth he) 'tis my <hi>Lord Cardinal:</hi> Go to then, ſaid the Enquirer, pray what is your Work? Oh Sir (ſaith he) <hi>I Say Service</hi> in my Lords Chappel; <hi>Say Service,</hi> (ſaith the other) then you are not ſo good as an <hi>Horſe</hi> or an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> for both theſe dumb Creatures <hi>doe Service,</hi> and <hi>doing Service</hi> is better than <hi>Saying Service:</hi> but the Diſcourſe ended not here, the <hi>Opponent,</hi> a little too Pragmatical, muſt ask ſome more Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being too much Queſtion-ſick, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaying, I pray you Sir, who gave to you the Name of <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Name of <hi>Lord Cardinal,</hi> ſeeing St. <hi>Paul</hi> Names no ſuch Offices among the Officers of the True Church? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. The <hi>Reſpondent</hi> Replys, Oh Sir, Our <hi>Holy Mother the Church</hi> gave to me the Name of <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and to my Maſter the Name of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal.</hi> Upon this, the <hi>Queſtioniſt</hi> makes this brisk Repartee, ſaying, [God Almighty Bleſs me with my <hi>Fathers</hi> Name, for all that Bear only their <hi>Mothers</hi> Name, (as you ſay, <hi>You</hi> and your <hi>Lord</hi> do) be no better than <hi>Baſtards,</hi> or if you will have it in a cleaner Dreſs, that is to ſay, the <hi>Popes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews:</hi> But enough of this <hi>Facetious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:52972:30"/>Now 'tis High time to take a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular View of our <hi>Odeſchalcho,</hi> whom we have Characteriz'd but little as a <hi>Cardinal</hi> hitherto, ſeeing our main Deſign is, to give him a more Ample Character as <hi>Pope,</hi> where the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> muſt be more fully opened in a large Field of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>As <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Divine</hi> gives a Graphical Deſcription of the Picture of his <hi>Double Beaſt in general;</hi> how <hi>He</hi> gradually Roſe, both out of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and out of the <hi>Sea, Revel.</hi> 13.1, 11. So my preſent Task is to Limn to the Life the very Perſon of this preſent <hi>Scarlet Colour'd Beaſt,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, ſhewing, <hi>Firſt,</hi> How he roſe up Step by Step to the <hi>Pontifical Chair,</hi> into which this our Cardinal <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> was Uſher'd with abundance of Pompous and Solemn <hi>Ceremonies:</hi> 'Tis indeed an uſual Saying, That <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are but <hi>Indifferent things;</hi> yet this is a moſt certain and Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Truth, (to the great Detriment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, much Damnified hereby) that though <hi>Ceremonies</hi> be in truth but things <hi>Indifferent</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> yet Experience (the beſt School-Miſtreſs) Teacheth, they are things <hi>Neceſſary</hi> to <hi>Preferment.</hi> None can Climb up (not <hi>Jacob</hi>'s, but) <hi>Antichriſt</hi>'s Ladder, ſave ſuch as have the <hi>Cheveril</hi> Conſcience of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52972:30"/>
a <hi>Latitudinarian,</hi> who can ſtretch out and Gape wide as the Greedy-gut once did, (in his Eating a Fiſh Dinner) who ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed down Bones and all, till he had like to have been Choaked: We muſt ſuppoſe our <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> had a Throat wide enough, he was not at all ſo <hi>Scrupulous</hi> as the <hi>preciſe</hi> Ones among us, but could Gulp down any <hi>Romiſh Ceremony</hi> (though never ſo Corrupt and Unſcriptural) provided it might but give him an Hearty Lift into the <hi>Seat of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility:</hi> 'Tis as much beyond Queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the moſt Received <hi>Maxim</hi> in Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, That ſuch as are moſt <hi>Defective</hi> in their <hi>Morals,</hi> are moſt Zealous to ſupply <hi>it</hi> with <hi>abundance</hi> of <hi>Ceremonials:</hi> How far this our <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> was <hi>Deficient</hi> in <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> let the Author of the <hi>Scarlet Gown</hi> (his own Countrey-man, the <hi>Italian</hi>) be heard to ſpeak, His Relation Runs thus, <hi>Benedetto Odeſchalcho</hi> was a very <hi>Rich Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> who a long time Courted <hi>Don Baerbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rino</hi> for preferring him to be <hi>Clerk</hi> of the <hi>Chamber,</hi> which place he was Ambitious of, (that he might be the better Acquainted with all the Grand Intrigues of the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory) and which the <hi>Don</hi> had promiſed him upon his paying down upon the Nail a Round Sum of Money for it: But find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his Purchaſe proved nothing, ſave
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52972:31"/>
only a company of Court Complements, and that this <hi>Crooked-back Don Antonio</hi> dealt but <hi>Crookedly</hi> with him, in making the Fool fain with Fair Words without Deeds, he (being weary'd with a little ſprinkling of Court Holy Water only,) began to think of the Proverb too late, <hi>That a Fool and his Money is ſoon parted:</hi> He hereupon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to take new Meaſures, and to try whether (againſt, and to Confute all <hi>Gramer</hi> Rules,) the <hi>Faeminine Gender</hi> might not prove more Worthy than the <hi>Maſculine,</hi> and whether the <hi>Gray-Mare</hi> might not prove the better <hi>Horſe;</hi> ſo makes he his Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that Famous Strumpet, that Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Jezabel,</hi> Siſter in Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Tenth, Don Olympia,</hi> wherein 'tis Remarkable, that he deals in both with the <hi>Dons,</hi> and with the Greateſt <hi>Dons</hi> too, the one an Ambitious, and (as to the Court Faction in <hi>Rome</hi>) a very <hi>Potent Cardinal;</hi> but the other (when he ſhifts his Sails unto, and makes his Second ſhift) was no leſs than an Omnipotent Creatreſs; for ſhe could Create what <hi>Cardinals</hi> and what <hi>Popes</hi> ſhe pleaſed, with her Irreſiſtible Charms: No wonder then, if, when at a loſs, he falls upon this new Expedient, and Turns <hi>Don Antonio</hi> into <hi>Don Olympia,</hi> yea Turns from the former to the latter, as being better
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52972:31"/>
furniſhed with Conveniences for him: he now thought it nothing ſo Commodious to <hi>Court a Lord,</hi> as to <hi>Court a Lady,</hi> eſpecially One ſo Accompliſhed both with an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power, and with a Bewitching Beauty.</p>
            <q>Et ſi qua latent, Meliora putat, <bibl>
                  <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Was not this a Brisk Madam, and well worth a Prelate, yea a Cardinals Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: The Subſtance of this Account, (though here dreſs'd up in other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) may be ſeen in the <hi>Scarlet Gown</hi> Author, <hi>pag.</hi> 21. who ſays further, That this <hi>Benedetto</hi> Preſented this Lady with Rich Love-Tokens, wherewith at length he <hi>Got into Her</hi>—Favor: But above all (ſaith the ſaid <hi>Italian</hi>) with One Amourous Bribe more than Ordinary, and moſt to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked; which matter (as that Author Relates it) was manag'd after this manner, Our <hi>Odeſchalcho,</hi> going one Day (as he did often) to pay his Reſpects to this his Lady <hi>Don Olympia,</hi> about the Coronation of her Brother in Law <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> the <hi>Tenth,</hi> a Goldſmith came at that very time, and ſhewed <hi>Her</hi> a very fair Cupboard of Rich and Modiſh Plate to Sell, and perhaps prompting the Lady to Buy it, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52972:32"/>
much to the Grace and Honour of that Great Days Solemnity: <hi>Olympia</hi> Vieweth it thorough and thorough in the preſence of this <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> (Her Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour) and other Lords, and no doubt had more than a Months Mind to it, but how to compaſs it without her own Coſt and Coin, was her preſent Project, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this, She firſt highly commends eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Veſſel by it ſelf, both Mettal, Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Luſtre, and then all in the whole, ſaying, It was a goodly and curious Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board of the New Faſhion'd Plate, but ſhe was a <hi>Poor Widow</hi> (ſhe ſhould have ſaid, a <hi>Rich Harlot</hi>) ſo pretending ſhe was not able to Purchaſe it; laſtly, upon this ſhe withdraws immediately to her Chamber, leaving the By-ſtander <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> (who admired all for her ſake) to make out ſome better proof (than yet he had done in all his former Gifts) of his Cordial Affections to Her. This <hi>Prelate,</hi> being but (as the ſame Author calls him) a <hi>Man of mean</hi> Undeſtanding, was the more eaſily Inſnared with the wily Wit of a Woman, which, at a pinch, doth uſually exceed that of a Man (who Requires more Deliberation) even of ſuch as have deeper Reaches and Capacities than our ſhallow <hi>Odeſchalcho:</hi> Hereupon, under this ſuddain Surprize, he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52972:32"/>
calls the Goldſmith to him, Asks the Price of the Plate, 'twas below his Honour in his Amorous Expectations to bid him lower than was Asked, he paid down Eight Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns for it, and without more Adoe, ſent it in to the Lady, as a Preſent from Him, to her in her Chamber, that this <hi>Gift</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith) might make Room for himſelf thither alſo: <hi>Don Olympia</hi> was ſo Tranſported (both with the Succeſs of her Craft, and with the Poſſeſſion of ſo much Plate, all coſting her Nothing, ſave only Caſting a Figure about a Credulous Fool,) that Immediately ſhe went to the Pope where ſhe was <hi>Domina, Faec totum,</hi> and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe had free Acceſs Night and Day, See <hi>Scarlet Gown,</hi> pag. 81. <hi>at the bottom,</hi>) Begs of him for <hi>Odeſchalcho,</hi> not only the <hi>Clerkſhip</hi> in the Chamber, but ſoon after a <hi>Scarlet Gown</hi> alſo. How far this <hi>She-Don</hi> Help'd him with her Hand (if not in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet by Proxy) into <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, I know not, 'tis enough to know here that <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi>'s Familiar Converſe with this <hi>Famous</hi> Woman, but Infamous Whore, gives Ground enough to beleive, that <hi>He</hi> was <hi>Defective in Morals,</hi> and therefore was under a Neceſſity to <hi>Eeek</hi> that out <hi>with Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonials:</hi> No wonder then, if ſuch a Man of <hi>Immorality</hi> ſhould become (as it were) a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52972:33"/>
very Compound of <hi>Ceremony:</hi> His <hi>Election</hi> to the Chair <hi>conſiſted of Ceremony;</hi> his <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> in the Chair <hi>conſiſted of Ceremony;</hi> but above all, his whole Worſhip and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion in the matters of Religion <hi>conſiſteth of Ceremony;</hi> only a Word or Two as a By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blow upon this laſt, it being beſide the Scope of our preſent Deſign. This preſent Popes Worſhip is drawn forth in ſuch an <hi>Antick</hi> and <hi>Pedantick</hi> Dreſs, ſo far from the Simplicity of the Goſpel, that no thinking Mind can look upon <hi>Popery</hi> to be any better than <hi>Foppery,</hi> ſure I am, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is far paſt her <hi>Meridian,</hi> ſeeing ſhe can ſcarce be now ſeen for the length of her own Shadow, the <hi>Shadows of her Evening</hi> are ſtretched out, in turning <hi>Doctrine</hi> into <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> into <hi>Ceremony,</hi> and though the <hi>Hedg of her Ceremonies</hi> may fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably <hi>protect Carrion-Crows,</hi> yet is it <hi>pricking and Vexatious enough to harmleſs Doves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to Wave that in this place, and come to that Compound of Ceremonies, manag'd by a <hi>Maſter of Ceremonies,</hi> at the <hi>Election</hi> of this preſent <hi>Pope:</hi> No ſooner was his Predeceſſor, <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the <hi>Tenth</hi> Dead, (for though the Keys of <hi>Heaven, Hell</hi> and <hi>Purgatory,</hi> hang at the Popes Girdle, yet there's the Miſchief, the Key of the <hi>Grave</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:52972:33"/>
was by ſome Miſhap or other drop'd from it, otherwiſe the Pope had been equally as <hi>Immortal</hi> as <hi>Infallible,</hi>) but the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Cardinals (having Nine Mornings after <hi>his</hi> Death Sung Dirges for the Repoſe of his Soul, and preparing themſelves with Holy Water, Incenſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) did all Repair to the Conclave, and with them Two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Ceremonies, and the Secratary of the College, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were all cloſe ſhut up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in order to Elect a New Pope: Then Proceſſions came Thick and Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold from all Churches and Monaſteries, Singing, <hi>[Veni Creator,</hi> &amp;c. Come Holy Ghoſt, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> Round about the Conſiſtory, Imploring the Inſpirations of the Spirit to come upon the Cardinals: The firſt Step or Ceremony, was, The Three chief Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the ſeveral Orders, with the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal-Chamberlain, took an Exact Survey of all the parts of the Conclave to ſee that all be cloſe, and ſhut up on all ſides, as if they would ſhut out the Holy Ghoſt from coming among them; for upon the Death of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>Fourth,</hi> when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave could not agree (being divided and Rent in pieces by the Feuds and Factions of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Intereſt) about the Election of a Succeſſor, one of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals (perhaps ſuppoſing that they were
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52972:34"/>
too cloſe ſhut up in the Conclave,) Cryed, <hi>You muſt Order the Uncovering of the Roof of the Conſiſtory, to make way for the Holy Ghoſt to come down upon us:</hi> The Conclave puts ſo much ſtreſs upon this ſame <hi>Ceremony,</hi> that not ſtrictly to obſerve it, is a Nullity of the Election.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Ceremony</hi> at the Election of this Pope, was, The Maſter of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, (after a Recital of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals Priviledges, which each Swore to Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, in caſe he were choſen Pope,) Rings a Bell and calls them all to Maſs, at which they Sang the Hymn, <hi>[Veni Creator Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,]</hi> and the Prayer of the Holy Ghoſt, to Implore His Illumination upon them: But I am afraid they could not find one <hi>Promiſe</hi> to ground their <hi>Prayer</hi> upon, for the promiſe of the Spirits coming is only to thoſe that Seek him <hi>in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> and that are found <hi>in Due Order,</hi> and not in ſuch Diſorders as Uſually attend the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave, which once gave occaſion to an Old Cardinal of <hi>Sicily,</hi> (who, after long Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, coming to a Popes Election, and finding nothing but Animoſities, Factions and Fractions among them,) to complain, ſaying, <hi>Num ad Hunc Modum fiunt pontifices Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s?</hi> &amp;c. I expected that fervent Prayers, as in Times of Old, ſhould have
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52972:34"/>
procured ſome fit Man to be pointed out by the Holy Ghoſt to us for a <hi>Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> but (ſaith he) If promiſing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards for Penſionary Votes, If Cajoling, Curſing and Threatning Revenge be your way of Canvaſing your Elections, then farwel for me, and ſo the good Old Man Returned Home to his Countrey, and could never be perſwaded to ſee <hi>Rome</hi> any more.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Ceremony,</hi> was, To Elect a Pope by <hi>Scrutiny,</hi> (waving the Two other ways of <hi>Inſpiration</hi> or <hi>Compromiſe,</hi>) which they thus managed, Each Cardinal hath a Liſt of all the Cardinals Names given to him, he Wrote down in a peice of Paper, whom he would have choſen, went to the Altar, puts his Scroll into the Golden Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice ſtanding thereupon, and ſo Return'd to his place, when all had ſo done, the <hi>Prims Biſhop</hi> took out all the Papers, delivered them to the <hi>Prime Deacon,</hi> who unfolded them all, and without mentioning the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> Read aloud the Names of the <hi>Elected:</hi> The <hi>Prime Prieſt</hi> Reckoning the Voices, pronounced the <hi>Majority</hi> of Votes to fall upon <hi>Cardinal Odeſchalcho:</hi> Hereupon he Rang a Silver Bell, and a Pan of Coals was brought in, and all the Paper Billets, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Names of all the Cardinals were Written, were Burnt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:52972:35"/>
               <hi>Good God,</hi> How far the Ancient Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is now Run from the Primitive Pattern? How far is that Church at this Day Run a Whoring? more like <hi>Babylons Whore,</hi> than <hi>Sions Spouſe,</hi> who both Ask'd and Received Directions from the Bleſſed Bridegroom, how ſhe might follow the Footſteps of <hi>Chriſts</hi> (not <hi>Antichriſts</hi>) Flock: I would gladly Ask of any Man, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe (and many more, for Brevity, omitted) ſilly <hi>Apiſh</hi> as well as <hi>Popiſh Tricks</hi> and <hi>Trinkets,</hi> were put into practice at the Election of St. <hi>Matthias</hi> into Traiterous <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>'s <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> Act. 1.20. <hi>to</hi> 26. The pure Simplicity of that Primitive Ordination makes our Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Eleventh</hi> look more like an <hi>Unholy Apoſtate,</hi> than any <hi>Holy Apoſtle,</hi> whoſe <hi>Succeſſor</hi> he yet preſumes to be Reckoned, who in Truth is rather a <hi>Succeſſor</hi> of <hi>Judas</hi> in betraying <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as he is the <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> than any of the Holy <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who were fervent follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Sacred Footſteps of their Sweet Saviour, and who Commands us <hi>to follow them no farther, than they follow Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.1. They make that <hi>Holy Child Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Regula Regulans,</hi> or Rule Ruling, and themſelves only the <hi>Regula Regulata,</hi> the <hi>Rule Ruled,</hi> they would not have us to follow the Dark Side of the <hi>Cloud</hi> of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52972:35"/>
as the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> did, and were Drowned, but the White-ſide thereof, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did, and were Saved. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we ever find that St. <hi>Peter</hi> paſs'd under thoſe Comick and Theatrical Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies when called to his Apoſtleſhip, or ever ſo Prefer'd or Enrich'd any of his <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews</hi> or Baſtards, as the <hi>Pope</hi> (his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Succeſſor) doth now.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth Ceremony</hi> wherewith this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Pope had his Pompous Inauguration at his Election, was, Still more like <hi>Apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> than <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> to wit, No ſooner was the Majority of Votes (even Two parts of Three) acknowledged to fall upon our Cardinal <hi>Odeſchalcho,</hi> through the Almighty Influence of his Old <hi>Grateful</hi> as well as Humble Servant, <hi>Don Olympia,</hi> who could not, with either <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Advantage,</hi> ſo ſoon forget her Stately Cupboard of curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Silver Plate, well knowing, her laſting Gratitude to Him would be an Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to others in that Court, to make their Addreſſes in the ſame manner to Her. No ſooner (I ſay) was this <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> owned to be the <hi>Pope Elect</hi> Duely, though never ſo Factiouſly and Surreptitiouſly; but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the <hi>Wicket,</hi> or rather <hi>Wicked</hi> Hole (well call'd the <hi>Golden Door,</hi> through which the Hungry Cardinals Receive all their
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52972:36"/>
               <hi>Meat,</hi> as well as <hi>Air,</hi> during their, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, long Confinement,) was then bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken open, at which ſtood an Infinite Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Poor People, on whom this New Pope beſtowed his Papal Benediction, and to whom He Remitted all their Sins. The Formality of opening this <hi>Golden Door,</hi> was thus Obſerved, This New Pope came with a <hi>Golden Mallet</hi> in his Hand (all <hi>He</hi> med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles now with muſt be Gold,) His <hi>Silver Age</hi> is now turned into a <hi>Golden</hi> One, his Silver Cupboard of Plate before purchaſed, is now turned into a <hi>Golden Door,</hi> and into a <hi>Golden Mallet,</hi> yea, better than all this. Here was, by Vertue of the Philoſophers Stone, a <hi>Silver,</hi> or rather a <hi>Leaden,</hi> or <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cardinal</hi> (as <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> ſignifies) into a more Illuſtrious and <hi>Golden Pope.</hi> With this <hi>Golden Mallet</hi> he ſtrikes at the <hi>Golden Door,</hi> which while He was in Doing, there were Workmen Ordered without to Break it open, which done, all the <hi>Chips, Stones, Duſt</hi> and <hi>Dirt,</hi> (that fell from this <hi>Golden Gate,</hi> while it was in opening,) are gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, and preſerved as the choiceſt and moſt Ineſtimable Relicks; and as to the <hi>Golden Mallet</hi> which this New Pope held in his Hand, <hi>He</hi> Nobly gave to Cardinal <hi>Sfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> (according to Cuſtom) who was his great Crony and Correſpondent, ofteneſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52972:36"/>
in his Company, and eſpecially in moſt Grace and Favour with him, for Lending him ſuch an effectual Lift into <hi>Peters</hi> Chair. Now let any Man of a Sober Mind Judg, what kind of Succeſſor this preſent Pope is to <hi>Poor Peter</hi> in his Chair; the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>[Silver and Gold have I none,]</hi> Act. 3.6. But this Pope (his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Succeſſor) hath <hi>Silver</hi> for himſelf, and for his <hi>Olympia</hi> too, yea, and a <hi>Golden Mallet</hi> to give away, <hi>&amp;c. Simon Peter</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> when he would have Hired of him the Gift of Miracles, <hi>Asts</hi> 8.19, 20, 23. whereas this <hi>Pope</hi> will do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without Ready Money. St. <hi>Peter</hi> paid his Tribute to Temporal Princes, even at his Lord Chriſts Command, both for <hi>himſelf</hi> and for his <hi>Maſter, Matth.</hi> 17.24. to the laſt; But this <hi>Pope</hi> (being <hi>Antichriſt</hi>) Scorns any ſuch Diſgraceful Motion, No, 'tis below his Unholy Highneſs to pay One Penny; he Received not <hi>Peters</hi> Patrimony upon any ſuch Ignoble Terms: The <hi>Law of the Land,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That a Mans Heir is Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to pay the Debts,</hi> and to <hi>perform the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Inheritance,</hi> otherwiſe the Heir is Diſinherited, and the Inheritance Divided among the Creditors: But the Popes Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-Law ſaith, <hi>Peters Keys of Authority,</hi> with all the Profits and Emoluments, belong
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52972:37"/>
to the <hi>Pope,</hi> who holds them faſt in his Hand; but as to his <hi>Key of Doctrine,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>He</hi> Taught Univerſal Subjection to Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Governours, is a Duty no way Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon <hi>Him;</hi> theſe are great Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances to Popes, and would be unſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Burdens to our Sacred Inheritance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yet in this the Pope likes well enough to Imitate his Predeceſſor <hi>Peter</hi> in, He dearly loves to Catch with his Angling Rod ſuch Fiſhes in his <hi>Sea</hi> or <hi>See,</hi> as have a peice of <hi>Silver in their Mouths, Matth.</hi> 17.27. and it will do no Harm, if now and then a peice of Gold be found there alſo, for then will he be furniſh'd with Materials, not only for a Silver Cupboard of Plate, but likewiſe for making his <hi>Golden Doors,</hi> and his <hi>Golden Mallets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth Ceremony</hi> ſhould have been, When the <hi>Golden Door</hi> was opened, He ſhould have proceeded to the <hi>Porphiry</hi> Chair, the <hi>Chair of Exploration,</hi> where the Youngeſt <hi>Cardinal-Deacon</hi> ſhould have Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined Things and Things. But this Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary Ceremony is now a Days Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated as Superfluous and Unneceſſary, ſince commonly thoſe Popes that have been lately Elected, had given ſufficient proof by their Baſtards of their <hi>Virility,</hi> and that they were known beforehand to be of the Right <hi>Maſculin Gender,</hi> and indeed I think
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52972:37"/>
it need not be much Doubted, but rather than fail, rather than this Pope ſhould have this trouble given him, <hi>Don Olympia</hi> her ſelf might have come in with her Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and have aſſured them <hi>Viva Voce,</hi> they might undoubtedly ſpare the Labor of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploration, for ſhe hath had ſome Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Knowledg (which is the Beſt) of his Manhood and Gallantry. And now, when I think of it, I cannot but Imagine this <hi>Groping Chair</hi> a very ill adviſed Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, however upon this Account, That whereas the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> do uſually Stile their Head, <hi>The Lord God their Pope,</hi> now if as they ſay, <hi>He</hi> be indeed a <hi>God,</hi> they do but Debaſe him (if not <hi>Ungod</hi> him) in Trying whether be be a <hi>Man:</hi> Methinks the Words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with but a little Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, might ſerve the pretended <hi>Vicar of Chriſt:</hi> as the <hi>Lord</hi> did Evidence the Truth of his Reſurrection, by ſaving, <hi>[If I be a Spirit, I ſhould not have Fleſh and Bones,]</hi> Luke 24.39. So this Vicar might give a Repulſe to his <hi>Gropers,</hi> by ſaying, <hi>[If I be a God, I ſhould not have Manly Members.]</hi> There is only this Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, Chriſt was willing to be Handled, but <hi>his Vicar</hi> is <hi>unwilling,</hi> unleſs by <hi>Olympia,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Rude Ceremony was Omitted.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Sixth Ceremony</hi> (and ſo many there muſt be to comport ſtill with the number
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52972:38"/>
of the name of the Beaſt, 666.) is a <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> So it ſupplies the late omiſſion of the <hi>fifth</hi> by way of Redundancy: for this introduceth all the <hi>Splendour</hi> and <hi>Grandeur</hi> of his prime <hi>Proceſſion, Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Coronation,</hi> &amp;c. (1) His firſt <hi>Proceſſion</hi> after his <hi>Election</hi> was thus pompouſly managed: this <hi>great Man,</hi> or rather, this <hi>great God</hi> was mounted upon Mens ſhoulders in the moſt ſplended Equipage imaginable, <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in all his Glory was never Arayed with</hi> (for you muſt ſuppoſe this <hi>Pope</hi> to be the goodly <hi>Lilly,</hi> or rather the glorious and gawdy <hi>Tulip,</hi> that our Lord ſpeaks of <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.28, 29.) However <hi>ſuch</hi> as neither <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf (<hi>who was greater than Solomon,</hi> Matt. 12.42.) nor much leſs his Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> (whoſe Succeſſour this Pope pretends to be) ever took upon them the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal and pompious Grandeur. <hi>This Pope was now Arayed in Scarlet Robes, Furr'd with Ermines quite through, and Adorned with the Richeſt Gold and Silver Laces, there was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upon his Head a moſt glittering and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tripple Crown of Gold, and a moſt Rich Collor of Gold all curiouſly Enameld with the choiceſt Jewels and chiefeſt precious Stones: there were put into his Hands two Golden Keys</hi> (pretended to be the ſame, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave to <hi>Peter,</hi> and that <hi>Peter</hi> at his Death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52972:38"/>
to the <hi>Popes</hi> ſucceſſively) <hi>which are for opening</hi> and <hi>ſhatting</hi> the <hi>Gates of Heaven</hi> (a place where Himſelf is never like to come) <hi>for whom he pleaſeth:</hi> and <hi>over his Head was carried a moſt ſtately Canopy with lofty, flying, and moſt gawdy Streamers,</hi> and <hi>He Himſelf</hi> under it moſt Trim, with his Artificial Locks finely curl'd and powder'd with a Vaſt Tower or Fruz upon his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head (in the very Dreſs of the <hi>Myſtical Whore</hi>) and in all this Antick Dreſs and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantick Pageantry, this Pope was preſented to the people, who (together with his Page) made thereupon loud Acclamations: <hi>[Vive le Papa, Vive le Papa]</hi> all along as He made his Progreſs to <hi>Peters Chair:</hi> mark here, while this <hi>Apocalyptick Beaſt</hi> was thus moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon Mens ſhoulders, He was then car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried like a <hi>Conquerour,</hi> who had now made a compleat Conqueſt over the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave of his Fellow-Cardinals, and now had ſtoutly Stormed (in deſpight of all fraud and force, yea, of Fate it ſelf) the ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical Chair, and in this poſture He was not onely like King <hi>Saul, who was higher by the Head and ſhoulders than all the People,</hi> but alſo as a <hi>mighty Nimrod,</hi> who was to Trample them all under Foot, His Feet ſtanding as high as their Heads: but the moſt ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Ceremony in his paſſage from the <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52972:39"/>
Hatch</hi> or <hi>Wicket,</hi> to his Chair of State, was this, a lump of Flax was carried before Him Burning, whereat theſe words were proclaimed.</p>
            <q>—Sic Tranſit Gloria Mundi.</q>
            <p>'Tis the Prayer of prudent and pious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, that an happy Blaſt may deſcend from Heaven to blow out for ever all this Antichriſtian Glory. Even ſo Amen &amp; Amen.</p>
            <p>Thus was he brought to his <hi>Chair of State,</hi> which was likewiſe covered with <hi>Scarlet,</hi> all richly Embroidered, Fringed round about with a Gold and Silver Silk Fringe, and gloriouſly bedeckt with <hi>Golden Balls</hi> and <hi>Croſſes,</hi> and which was placed upon as <hi>Lofty</hi> and as <hi>Coſtly</hi> a Throne as was that of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> 1 Kings 10.18. Thither was he brougt upon Mens ſhoulders, and when gently taken down (for fear of hurting the good old Man) there was He <hi>ſeated,</hi> there was He <hi>conſecrated,</hi> and there was He <hi>crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. when all this <hi>ſolemnity</hi> is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, then His <hi>Herald</hi> (dreſſed up in a Garb comporting with the Pomp) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims by ſound of Trumpet, His great Lord and Maſter, to be now <hi>[the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords]</hi> and as if that were not ſufficient, <hi>He</hi> had his <hi>Paraſites</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:52972:39"/>
prepared to cry loud <hi>[God Bleſs our Lord God the Pope]</hi> Thus <hi>He,</hi> who trode under foot onely the People before, muſt now trample upon the Necks of Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Inſtance onely in <hi>poor Emperour Frederick,</hi> who was conſtrained to lay ſprawling under the <hi>proud Popes</hi> Feet, on whoſe Neck <hi>He</hi> inſolently trampled at <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice:</hi> 'Tis therefore one part of this Pompi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Magnificency, that this <hi>Magnifico</hi> hath two Swords ſtanding erect by his Chair of State at his right Hand, to denote, that not onely the <hi>Sword of Excommunication,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Civil Dominion</hi> belongs to him alſo: To ſay nothing of the number of Gawdy <hi>Beads, Agnus Deis:</hi> and abundant more <hi>Romiſh Trumpery</hi> expoſed to publick View, for the better ſetting off the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his Inauguration: I think 'twas about well, that, together with his Title aforementioned, this alſo <hi>[God of Gods.]</hi> was not ſuperadded, ſo exalted Him above the <hi>moſt High God,</hi> as well as over all <hi>Lords, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Emperours.</hi> The <hi>Roman Canon</hi> and Ceremonial Law <hi>commands</hi> the People to ſay at the <hi>Popes Inſtalment [thou art our God the Pope]</hi> and <hi>Pope Martin</hi> could calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and complaiſantly receive the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Embaſſadour ſaying <hi>[thou art the Lamb of God, that takeſt away
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52972:40"/>
the ſins of the World]</hi> ſo was this, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to all the World, that it is He <hi>who ſits in the Temple of God, exalting Himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> if not above the true God Himſelf, the Pope dare diſpence with, if not diſanul or contradict the Law of God: Sure I am, never did any mortal Man look more like <hi>proud Lucifer</hi> (who ſaid <hi>ero ficut Altiſſimus,</hi> I <hi>will be like,</hi> If not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, <hi>the moſt High,</hi> Iſa. 14.14.) than this preſent proud Pope in his pontificalibus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to View with all thoſe Additional For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities did go, all which, yet one more muſt ſtill be added, to wit, the <hi>change of his Name,</hi> his old Name [<hi>Odeſchalco</hi> the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> muſt be turned into <hi>Innocent</hi> the 11th. How <hi>Nocent</hi> this <hi>Innocent</hi> was, the ſequel will demonſtrate. Yet follows he the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of <hi>Bocea di Porco</hi> or Hog-face, who was the <hi>firſt Pope</hi> that changed his Name, thus when his Succeſſours were <hi>Cowards,</hi> they muſt be called <hi>Leo,</hi> if he were a Tyrant, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Clement,</hi> if a <hi>Ruſtick, Urbanus</hi> though never ſuch a <hi>Turbanus,</hi> or trouble World: If an Athieſt then <hi>Pious.</hi> So if never ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, or <hi>Nocent</hi> then it muſt be <hi>Innocent.</hi> The <hi>Popes</hi> of theſe later Years have been ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſhort lived, to Inſtance onely in a few of the laſt Edition, Cardinal <hi>Chigi</hi> was Elected Pope, in the year 55. <hi>April</hi> the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52972:40"/>
7th., call'd himſelf <hi>Alexander</hi> the 7th, one troubleſome enough to the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He ſoon trips off (Whether from the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God or his own good Nature, I ſhall not ſay) gave up the Ghoſt, and Reſigned up the Chair to Cardinal <hi>Roſpiglioſs,</hi> who ſucceeds him <hi>June</hi> 20th. by the Name of <hi>Clement</hi> the 9th, in the Year 67. The <hi>loſs of Candia</hi> afflicted him much more, than the <hi>burntng of London,</hi> and haſtened his Death in the Year 70. The Conclave being ſhut up above Four Months (a long time to be in the Dark, where they made day of Wax Candle, Having neither Windows nor Holes to let in light) at laſt had ſo much light as to Elect <hi>Cardinal Altieri,</hi> which was the doating Pope that Created our <hi>Cardinal Howard</hi> (who is after to be mentioned) and then Dyeth in the Year 76. having born the Name of <hi>Clement the Tenth.</hi> So gives place to our <hi>Cardinal Odeſchalco,</hi> &amp;c. what a black Character they all bear in the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Cardinals,</hi> I muſt rather requeſt the Reader to obſerve it there than to expect it here; eſpecially of this preſent Pope <hi>Don Olympias</hi> grand Favourite: but above all, I wonder at that Iriſh Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> (which Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> mentioneth in his Coſmog. laſt Edition p. 106.) who lived in the 11th, Century, contemporary with <hi>Bernard,</hi> yet
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52972:41"/>
undertook to give an account of all the Popes from that time to this day, and this He doth by <hi>Symbols and Hierogliphicks,</hi> and omitting all others, as beſide our purpoſe that which is moſt remarkable, is the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, He ſo prophetically Impoſeth upon this preſent Pope Symbolically, and in an Hieroglyphick way plainly Stiles Him, <hi>Bellus In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atiabilis,</hi> an <hi>Inſatiable Beaſt,</hi> I have been thinking ſince I found it that this <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi</hi> the <hi>Iriſh Prophet</hi> (not to meddle with his other predictions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) hath Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this character ſo congruouſly to this <hi>Odeſchalco,</hi> as if he had been the <hi>Jewiſh Prophet Malachi,</hi> who infallibly had the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Spirit,</hi> what kind of Spirit (this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Saint, a Ceſtertian Monk, Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi>) was endued with, is not eaſie to Determine, yet is there found ſuch an Admirable Harmony <hi>inter ſignum &amp; ſignatum,</hi> the <hi>Perſon</hi> and the <hi>things</hi> do Symbolize to Aſtoniſhment, as <hi>Meſſingham, Buſſier,</hi> &amp;c. do obſerve.</p>
            <q>Conveni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt Rebus Nomina Saepe Suis.</q>
            <p>That this <hi>preſent Pope</hi> ſhould be pointed out (as by the Finger) to be an <hi>Inſatiable Beaſt,</hi> above Five Hundred Years before He was Born, muſt be acknowledg'd <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52972:41"/>
Dictu.</hi> If ſeveral of the true Prophets of God did ſo Truly Foretel of <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> that <hi>He</hi> would Ariſe, and become Gods <hi>Battle-Axe</hi> to Hew down the Degenerate Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the <hi>Jews,</hi> bring them <hi>to literal Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> keep them Captive there for <hi>Seventy long Years,</hi> &amp;c. And if ſeveral of the <hi>True Apoſtles of Chriſt</hi> did ſo Truly Foretel of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> that he would Ariſe out of the <hi>Earth</hi> and out of the <hi>Sea,</hi> and become the <hi>Devils Patriarch</hi> to tread down the outward Court of formal Profeſſours, carry them Captive to <hi>Myſtical Babylon,</hi> keep them in Captivity for <hi>one thouſand two Hundred and ſixty long Years,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>both theſe,</hi> Some Hundred of Years before they both came to paſs: Why may we not call this <hi>ſtrange Prophet,</hi> (that thus long before foretold of this Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual preſent Pope, that he would Ariſe, and become an <hi>Inſatiable Beaſt</hi>) The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Malachi the Second,</hi> notwithſtanding he was one of the <hi>Monkiſh Order,</hi> I cannot but Judg His Teſtimony is therefore ſo much the ſtronger, for 'tis a received Maxim <hi>[firmum eſt probandi Genus quod etiam ab Adverſario Sumiſur, quum Veritas etiam ab Inimicis Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis probari poſſit]</hi> 'tis the ſtrongeſt kind of proof, when the very <hi>Enemies of the Truth</hi> are conſtrained to bear Witneſs to it. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Ludovicus Vives de probabilitatis Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:52972:42"/>
ſaith thus <hi>[Amici contra Amicum, &amp; Inimici pro Inimico Invincibile Teſtimonium erit]</hi> which in <hi>plain Engliſh</hi> muſt thus be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. The Teſtemony of a Papiſt againſt a Papiſt,</hi> and of a Papiſt for a Proteſtant is a Teſtimony without exception, and more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible than this <hi>Infallible Pope,</hi> againſt whom this Popiſh Monk, <hi>Malachi,</hi> beareth ſuch an undeniable Teſtimony, though his Friend as of the ſame Religion, yet Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours He Him with no better a Title, than that of an <hi>Inſatiable Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Scope of all the following <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> is no other than a <hi>Deſcent</hi> and <hi>Comment</hi> upon that <hi>Black</hi> and <hi>Beaſtly Brand,</hi> wherewith this <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prophet <hi>(Monk Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi)</hi> Stigmatiz'd <hi>him</hi> with, ſo many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years before He was in <hi>Rerum Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rà,</hi> or had any Exiſtence: Now that He hath been ſo long in his preſent Being, and hath been Acting (like the <hi>Devils</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch) his Deviliſh part in the Tragedy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Theatre of the World, ever ſince <hi>September</hi> the <hi>Twenty-Firſt,</hi> in the Year <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Six,</hi> whereon He was <hi>Conſecrated and Crowned,</hi> &amp;c. as above. <hi>Time</hi> is always the beſt <hi>Expoſitor</hi> of the moſt Abſtruce and Obſcure Prophecies; and what a full and perfect Expoſition <hi>Time</hi> it ſelf hath already made (and may hereafter make more)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52972:42"/>
upon this very Text and Title of this <hi>Iriſh Prophet Malachi,</hi> concerning this Pope, is my Task I have before me to Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In <hi>General,</hi> That this preſent Pope is a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> is as plain, as if Writ with a Beam of the Sun upon a Wall of Marble. Seeing both the <hi>Prophet Daniel,</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> do Unanimouſly call the whole Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Popes no better than <hi>Beaſts,</hi> yea, ſuch Beaſts as are beyond and above all Names, as in the <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis manifeſt enough even out of their own Authors (ſuch as Wrote the Lives of the Popes) How that many, if not moſt of them, were <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> with an Accent; yea, Beaſts rather than Men; yea, even <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> in Iniquity: See Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Coſmog. pag. 106, 107, 108. of the laſt Edition, where you have a Black-Bed Roll of their State and Story, to the number of Thirty one, which is a lucky Number, call'd an <hi>even Hitter,</hi> and is ſaid, a Knave and One and Twenty, (or in plainer Engliſh, a <hi>Knave,</hi> that ſtands for <hi>ten [Knaves]</hi> and One and Twenty more (of the ſame litter, or letter) wins all at the Game of Noddy this Chriſtmaſs time, wherein <hi>The Knave</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is turned up Trump with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: See alſo <hi>Neſs</hi>'s <hi>Diſcovery of Antichriſt,</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:52972:43"/>
pag. 56, 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, 62. where you have a Compendious Landskip of but a few of the Popes Lives (all gather'd out of their own <hi>Roman</hi> Writers) to ſhew in ſhort, what <hi>Beaſts,</hi> what <hi>Monſters of Men</hi> they have been: And that this great Truth may be <hi>Compleatly Confirmed</hi> by the Mouth of even <hi>Three Witneſſes,</hi> See alſo Dr. <hi>Scalter</hi> in his Comment upon the <hi>Second of Theſſalon.</hi> pag. 115. where he ſaith, [If a Man may be ſo bold with the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was with our Saviour (and why ſhould <hi>Chriſt</hi> be more Rudely Handel'd than <hi>Antichriſt</hi>) Asking, <hi>[Art thou He that ſhould come, or do we look for another?]</hi> The like Anſwer may moſt properly be Returned, [<hi>Go and Tell what you heard and ſeen,</hi> to wit, <hi>God is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd, the Devils are Worſhip'd, Religion is Prophan'd, Superſtition is Hallow'd, Beaſtly Luſt is Practic'd, and Parricide is not only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated, but Patroniz'd,</hi>] with much more Horrid Helliſhneſs thoſe <hi>[Parùm probi Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines]</hi> or Wicked Popes have done: Is not this the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> the <hi>Apocalyptick Beaſt,</hi> the <hi>Matchleſs Monſter,</hi> Prophecy'd of in the <hi>Word,</hi> that ſhould come into <hi>the World</hi> and play <hi>Rex,</hi> and his Pranks in it: Now 'tis below this preſent Pope to be better than his Predeceſſors, He Scorns to Degenerate from the Worſt of them, chuſing rather to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52972:43"/>
Imitate them, than Holy <hi>Peter.</hi> The <hi>Iriſh Prophet</hi> Stiles him a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> hath proved him ſo. Our next Work is to ſhew him the <hi>Inſatiable</hi> One, for <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Epithet Inſatiable</hi> hath Variety of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, according to the Variety both of its <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Object.</hi> There be various Paſſions of the Mind of Man, that are Headſtrong, Extravagant and Inſatiable, whereby Man is turned into a Beaſt, as Thus,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Paſſion</hi> of Luſt, when it grows Unruly and Ungovernable, <hi>Tranſporting</hi> the Monk out of his Monaſtery into the Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery among the Nuns, or ſuppoſe the Man a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> or a <hi>Pope,</hi> when he is Exported out of all Bonds and Bounds of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Continency, his <hi>Unruly Luſt</hi> cauſeth him Rudely to break His <hi>Vow of Chaſtity,</hi> and He hereupon Applys himſelf to his common <hi>Curtezans,</hi> or <hi>Don Olympia</hi>'s, then is the <hi>Beaſt</hi> truly Stiled <hi>Inſatiable.</hi> Or</p>
            <p>Secondly, When that Paſſion of Bloud-Thirſtineſs hath the like prevalency over the Mind of Man, makes him as Savage, and as Bloudy-Minded as a Butcher or Beaſt, inſomuch, that <hi>He</hi> Delights to Wallow in the Bloud of others, yea, to be <hi>Drunk with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52972:44"/>
the Bloud of the Saints</hi> (which is the Trick of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi>) then is the Beaſt Rightly Branded with being <hi>Inſatiable,</hi> and then 'tis High Time for good Proteſtants to put up this good Prayer, <hi>Lord, let this Drunken In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Beaſt, Spue and Fall, and never Riſe up any more.</hi> or</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (To Omit other Exorbitant Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Affections of Mankind,) the Third Caſe is, When the Connatural Paſſion of Covetouſneſs hath got ſuch a Predominancy over the Mans Mind, that it Metamorpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>him</hi> into a <hi>Muck-worm,</hi> yea, into a Mole, that Subterraneal Blind Creature, which lives altogether within the <hi>Earth</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſtleſs, as out of its Center, while out of it) and hath nothing to do with <hi>Heaven:</hi> Muſt Evermore have his Mouth and Claws full of Earth, when <hi>the Man</hi> will Extract Gain out of a very Dunghil, a Vaſt Revenue for Indulging Stews, and that as a Neceſſary Convenience, <hi>[Ad purgandos Renes]</hi> eſpecially in the Three Hot Months of the Year, when <hi>the Man</hi> doth practical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approve of that Motto, <hi>[Lucri bonus eſt odor ex re quâlibet,]</hi> and that other too, <hi>[Lucrum ò Lotio eſt Optabile,]</hi> Theſe were the Old Symbols of ſome Great Men of <hi>Rome,</hi> who thought all Gain Sweet, though Got out of the Piſs-Pot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52972:44"/>
               <hi>Great Man of</hi> Rome is no Changling from them, He is for getting the Devil and all, with his <hi>Gain from all Quarters,</hi> Iſa. 56.11. <hi>and</hi> Micah 3.3. <hi>per Totum.</hi> Then alſo is the <hi>Beaſt Inſatiable,</hi> and upon this Third Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it is, that the <hi>Prophet Malachi</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, aforeſaid, calleth in His Characters, this very <hi>Odeſchalcho</hi> (the <hi>preſent Pope) Bellua Inſatiabilis,</hi> as a late Learned Writer doth well Interpret it: Though this <hi>Beaſt of Rome</hi> hath been <hi>Inſatiable</hi> enough as is ſuppoſed, in the Firſt Caſe and Account of <hi>Inſatiability,</hi> when he look'd upon <hi>Carnal Concupiſcence</hi> with <hi>Romiſh</hi> Spectacles, and according to the Popiſh Doctrine, but a <hi>Peccadillo,</hi> a <hi>Trick of Youth,</hi> a <hi>Venial Sin;</hi> He had that Fleſh-pleaſing Circular ſaying, [<hi>Confeſs after Sin, Sin and Confeſs,</hi> in Infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,] in great Veneration, as a Sovereign Cure for a Popiſh Conſcience, and indeed, 'tis a wonder that all the <hi>World (which lays in Wickedneſs,</hi> 1 John 5.19.) will not eaſily turn <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that they may Sin, in Sins of all ſorts, with Peace, wherein they can Bleſs themſelves with Pardons prepared and to be Purchaſed: But to let that paſs, ſeeing the Jeſuits Rule, <hi>[Si non caſtè, tamen cautè]</hi> Anticipates Intelligence of ſuch Deeds of Darkneſs, till the Pond come to be Scowred again, wherein were found Thouſands of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52972:45"/>
Infants Skulls, which, as it promoted the Deſtruction of <hi>Abbeys</hi> here, ſo in Time eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, yea, of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, that <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel-Houſe of Babylon.</hi> My Work at preſent is, to give him his due Character of an <hi>Inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable Beaſt</hi> in both the other Reſpects, with a little Tranſpoſition of the Third, (as coming next to Hand into the Seconds place) to wit, both as a Greedy and as a Bloudy <hi>Inſatiable</hi> Beaſt.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Prophet Malachi</hi> (the <hi>Iriſh Monk</hi>) hath <hi>Divine Warrant</hi> to call this Pope an <hi>Inſatiable Beaſt,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah</hi> calls ſuch <hi>Prieſts (ejuſdem Farinae</hi> of the ſame Brann with this <hi>High Prieſt) Greedy Dogs, which can never have enough,</hi> Iſa. 56.10, 11. and though they were <hi>dumb Dogs and could not bark,</hi> yet could they bite well enough, perverting the Houſe of God for Prayer into a Den of Cut-Throat Thieves: How far this <hi>Pope</hi> hath been the <hi>Jewiſh Prophets Greedy Dog,</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prophets <hi>Inſatiable Beaſt,</hi> falls firſt in Order to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate: ſo His moſt <hi>Eminent</hi> and <hi>Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cheats, whereby he Gulls the ſilly People,</hi> do here follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He</hi> is (in the General) the Grand <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of the World,</hi> ſo the <hi>Pope</hi> was call'd by Doctor <hi>Morton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durelm</hi> many Years ago, whoſe Elaborate Book Diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52972:45"/>
the many Legerdemain Tricks where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with He <hi>deceiveth Nations,</hi> and all and only to pick their Pockets.</p>
            <p>May we but be let in a little to behold the Bowels of this <hi>Grand Cheat,</hi> and View but a while his <hi>Guts</hi> and <hi>Garbage,</hi> 'twill ſoon be Diſcerned that he is the <hi>Devils Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triark,</hi> bearing upon his Bannet the <hi>Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Deſolation:</hi> The time would fail to tell, How many Families this <hi>Abominable Beaſt</hi> hath made <hi>Deſolate:</hi> what elſe is the whole Cento and Fardle of Popery, but a Concatenation of Wiles to compaſs a purſe? What is the chief Deſign of this <hi>Balaam of Rome,</hi> but a continual conjuration for an <hi>Houſe-full of Gold and Silver?</hi> Witneſs his <hi>lying Legends,</hi> His <hi>Mock-Miracles, Praying for the</hi> Dead, and a Thouſand more nimble Tricks too tedious to enumerate, but above all, His <hi>Doctrine of Purgatory,</hi> The Fire whereof doth more effectually <hi>warm tke Popes Kitchin,</hi> than Torture any Soul <hi>He</hi> Damns into it. 'Tis a <hi>Cheat of Cheats:</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> points at this <hi>Pope,</hi> (who pretends to be his Succeſſor) while he ſpeaks of ſuch, as <hi>through Covetouſneſs with feigned Words,</hi> do make <hi>Merchandiſe of Men,</hi> and when He names <hi>Balaam the Son of Boſor, who loved the wages of Iniquity</hi> ſo far, until the <hi>Dumb Aſs</hi> forbad the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52972:46"/>
of the <hi>profane Prophet,</hi> yet <hi>He</hi> cannot paſs off without paſſing a Divine Doom, ſaying, <hi>whoſe Judgment now of a long time lingreth, and yet their Damnation ſlumbreth not,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.3.15, 16. How can it <hi>ſlumber</hi> long, when the cry of his cheating Tricks (together with <hi>that of Bloud</hi>) is gone up to Heaven to fletch down Gods Vengeance upon this <hi>Popes</hi> Head, and upon his whole <hi>Popedom:</hi> Let the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> alſo Joyn Iſſue in this matter with his <hi>beloved Peter,</hi> (both which are repreſented <hi>Bluſhing,</hi> as before, at ſuch pittiful pretended Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors) who ſaith likewiſe [as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres withſtood Moſes, ſo do theſe the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, Men of corrupt Minds, and Reprobate concerning the Faith: But they ſhall proceed no further, for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt to all Men, as theirs alſo was,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.8, 9. Now what were <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> but a couple of <hi>Gipſy</hi> or <hi>Aegyptian Coujurers,</hi> that cheated the People with their <hi>lying Miracles,</hi> &amp;c. And ſuch have ſome of the <hi>Popes of Rome</hi> (that <hi>Myſtical Aegypt,</hi> Rev. 11.8.) been, <hi>&amp;c. [Habemus Reos Confitentes]</hi> Popiſh Authors do acknowledg it, and did <hi>Moſes</hi> muzzle the Mouths, and made their Cheats manifeſt to all Men? How much more will the <hi>Meſſias</hi> (who is greater than <hi>Moſes,</hi> Heb. 3.3.) confound in due time
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52972:46"/>
this <hi>Grand Impoſtor.</hi> 'Tis impoſſible for any Man of a Sober Mind to think otherwiſe, eſpecially, If he caſt but a ſeeing Eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>[Taxa Comerae Apoſtolicae]</hi> the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Chamber in the Vatican at <hi>Rome,</hi> where this <hi>Pope</hi> hath opend his <hi>Pedlars Pack,</hi> expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all his Vendible Commodities (for <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Omnia Venalia</hi>) to the beſt Advantage of commending them to his Chapmans Eye, no Shop ſo well furniſhed, or affords ſuch a Tempting Proſpect in any of the Walks of the Royal Exchange Chambers, and that which gives the moſt Splendid and Decoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Luſtre is, there you have the Pope himſelf in his Grandeur, Courting in Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, good Man, <hi>He</hi> dare not truſt his Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, a pack of Knaves, He hath found them long, wou'd go Snips with their Maſter, He ha's now Learnt by His Loſs. <hi>Keep the Shop</hi> Robin, <hi>and it will keep thee.</hi> There himſelf ſtands crying in the very Language of <hi>Folly</hi> (not of <hi>Wiſdom) who ſo is ſimple, let him turn in Hither,</hi> Prov. 9.16. He Cants in his Proſelytes with Pedlars Pedantick Oratory, Coying them in with come along my <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> my Soft Pates (for you muſt ſuppoſe He is of the ſame Sentiments with that Crafty <hi>Shop-Keeper,</hi> who once Boaſted, He would not ſell all his <hi>Children and Fools,</hi> his Cuſtomers, for ſome Hundreds of Pounds
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:52972:47"/>
in the Year) come along my Corculums, look about you, Gentlemen, what lack you? Lo, here's a <hi>Gooſe-Giblet Pye,</hi> wherein every Palate may pleaſe it ſelf, what will ye buy? I am juſt now upon my laſt Legs, my long Leaſe of 1260 Years is now at its laſt Gaſp and Expiration, what, never a packing-penny among you all for a poor packing-off Pope: But are you Deſirous to know his <hi>Wares</hi> (all very Vendible to the Credulous, that never think of the Cheat) what are his Commodities in particular? I will tell you, where you have them all named, and we are not a little obliged to the <hi>Infallible Holy Ghoſt,</hi> that will take all the pains in giving us a Diſtinct Catalogue of all this <hi>Infallible Ghoſtly</hi> Fathers Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities: He tells you, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.12, 13. in <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Stately Shop, you may have for <hi>Ready Money [the Merchandiſe of Gold and Silver, precious Stones</hi> and <hi>Pearls, fine Lennen</hi> and <hi>Purple,</hi> all <hi>Silk</hi> and <hi>Scarlet, all Thyne or Sweet Wood, all manner of Veſſels of Ivory, all manner of Veſſels of precious Wood,</hi> of <hi>Braſs,</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> and of <hi>Marble;</hi> yet more, yea, and <hi>Cinnamon, Odours,</hi> and <hi>Ointments,</hi> yea, <hi>Frankincenſe, Wine</hi> and <hi>Oyl,</hi> yea, <hi>fine Flower</hi> and <hi>Wheat,</hi> yet more, there be <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and <hi>Sheep,</hi> and <hi>Horſes,</hi> (I wonder <hi>Aſſes</hi> are left out) and Chariots, and Slaves, (no doubt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:52972:47"/>
on't, but the greateſt Ware is behind) the <hi>Souls of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who will not ſay here [God bleſs us] what a Shop is this? So Capacious, and ſo Accommodated with all the choiceſt and chiefeſt Commodities, that this lower World can afford: Here's the Riches of both the <hi>Indies (Gold, Silver,</hi> and <hi>precious Stones there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi>) Here's the Riches of all Countrys and Kingdoms, betwixt <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt, North</hi> and <hi>South:</hi> Here's the very Quinteſſence and Compendium of <hi>Europe,</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> of <hi>Africk,</hi> and of <hi>America:</hi> is not this the <hi>Grand Impoſtor,</hi> that even call'd for a pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-penny to a poor Pope, who hath ſo much of Treaſure, enough to ſerve himſelf and enough to ſell to others. But I wonder <hi>He</hi> expoſeth his <hi>Scarlet</hi> to Sale, Having ſo much uſe for it to Array the <hi>Scarlet Whore:</hi> as alſo that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> ſhould be a Seller of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and above all, I wonder what price He ſets upon the <hi>Souls of Men:</hi> ſeeing our Lord Chriſt (who beſt knew the worth of Souls, becauſe He onely went to the price of Souls) <hi>Valued one Soul worth the whole World,</hi> Matth. 16.26. Surely He muſt be the <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who <hi>ſelleth Souls</hi> for Trifles: In a Word, ſurely, This Pope is <hi>Jack of all Trades:</hi> Here he is a <hi>Goldſmith,</hi> with his Gold and Silver, and it may be a <hi>Banker,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:52972:48"/>
I wiſh him to become a <hi>Bankrupt.</hi> Here he is a <hi>Jeweller,</hi> with his <hi>Pearls</hi> and <hi>Precious Stones.</hi> Here he is a <hi>Linnen-Draper,</hi> with his <hi>Fine Linnen</hi> and <hi>Purple,</hi> (I doubt He wants the <hi>Scotch-Cloth.</hi>) Here you have him a <hi>Silk-Man</hi> with his Silks of all ſorts, and fear not, but he has <hi>Satten</hi> (or <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>) enough. Here he is a <hi>Turner,</hi> that Sells all ſorts of <hi>Veſſels,</hi> wherewith he <hi>Turns,</hi> the World Upſide Down; this <hi>He</hi> effects by <hi>Veſſels of Wrath,</hi> but He Sells for <hi>Slaves</hi> the <hi>Veſſels of Mercy.</hi> Here you have him one while a <hi>Brazer</hi> with his <hi>Braſs;</hi> another while an <hi>Iron-Monger</hi> with his <hi>Iron;</hi> yea, ſometimes a <hi>Stone-Cutter,</hi> with his <hi>Marble,</hi> and why not a <hi>Tinker</hi> too, being a Kin to him, that inſtead of mending ſome Holes, made many more, yet was well paid for his pains. Here he is a <hi>Druggiſt,</hi> with his <hi>Cinnamon, Odours</hi> and <hi>Ointment,</hi> &amp;c. not one Sophiſticated Drug amongſt them all. Here he comes as a <hi>Vintner</hi> with his Bottles of <hi>Wine</hi> to <hi>comfort the Heart,</hi> and his Cruiſes of <hi>Oil</hi> to Chear and Clear the Countenance; 'tis well if there be not a Tincture of the <hi>Wine of Sodom</hi> among Hands. Yea, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than fail, <hi>He</hi> becomes a <hi>Corn-Chand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> affording you <hi>Wheat,</hi> either broken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Flour</hi> (with Bran enough in it) or in the whole Grain, but a little Muſty by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52972:48"/>
in a bad Granary or Garner, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical <hi>Chamber.</hi> Yet lower, nay rather than ſit Idle, he will come as a Ruſtick <hi>Drover</hi> to Sell <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and <hi>Sheep,</hi> and <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> (well Mouth'd and Man'd all, and made as Tame as <hi>Aſſes.</hi>) And at laſt he comes as a <hi>Coach-Maker,</hi> who has his <hi>Charots</hi> to Sell, but have a care they carry you not to <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> inſtead of <hi>Abrahams Boſom.</hi> But to Crown up the Catalogue of all his Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, Note, that which we Read <hi>Slaves,</hi> doth fignifit <hi>[Bodies,]</hi> which he Sels for <hi>Slaves,</hi> and the <hi>Souls of Men</hi> too. And ſo Laſtly, he becomes a <hi>Body-ſeller,</hi> and (to make a thorough-whole-ſale Trade, a <hi>Soul-ſeller</hi> alſo. Let us all (with <hi>Moſes</hi>) turn aſide to ſee this <hi>great Wonder,</hi> ſure I am, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did <hi>Proteus</hi> turn himſelf into ſo many <hi>Shapes,</hi> never did any <hi>Jeſuit</hi> (this <hi>Popes</hi> Creature) Convert himſelf into ſo many Callings, as His Maſter is here Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in. The Pope hath made a Monopoly of all Employs to himſelf, both in <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi> And the greateſt Merchants Shop (whoſe Riches lay not there, but in the Warehouſe) cannot, though taken both together, be compared to the <hi>Apoſtolical Chamber.</hi> One coming into a Merchants Shop (I knew the Man, a Ruſtick Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) and ſeeing no Goods therein, Bluntly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52972:49"/>
Asks the Apprentice (ſitting alone in the Shop) what was Sold there? the Malapert Youth Anſwered; We Sell <hi>Loggerheads,</hi> ſay you ſo, ſaith the Ruſtick, Then you have a Quick Market for them, ſeeing I ſee but One left in the Shop. There is no Danger of any <hi>Citizen</hi> or <hi>Countryman</hi> either <hi>Miſſing</hi> (what Wares he would be at) or <hi>Miſtakings</hi> of that Nature, for here's all things Expoſed to View. There is yet One Miſchief men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.11. where (this Rich Shop is Inventory'd) that <hi>No Man Buyeth. His Merchandiſe any more:</hi> This will break him at laſt.</p>
            <p>But let my Countrymen take theſe Two Cautions,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Have a care of a Cheat in his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Commodities: for he ſells them all in a very dark Shop, not ſuffering you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe your own Reaſon, you muſt take all upon his crack'd Credit, and comply with His price in an <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> and in a <hi>blind Obedience</hi> you muſt believe what the Pope believes, and he is no ſuch Fool as to diſcommend his own Wares, He beſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces Blindfold Buyers, <hi>Ignorance is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Merchandize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Caution is, 'Tis dangerous venturing into this <hi>Apoſtolical Chamber,</hi> leaſt this <hi>Grand Cheat</hi> pick your pockets, for
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52972:49"/>
though his Wares be naught, being all for Impoſitions, He will impoſe them upon you, and he will not truſt you to the door for fear you give him the ſlip, He muſt have <hi>Ready Money</hi> paid down upon the nail.</p>
            <p>Have a care you be not cox'd out of good Gold for bad Ware: And before you <hi>Saddle</hi> your <hi>Aſs</hi> to Ride down to this Arch Hux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Myſtical <hi>Aegypt,</hi> let me beſeech you to conſider a little in your conſidering Cap, whither it were not far better for you, to make your Buying Bargains with <hi>Chriſt</hi> than with <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for the <hi>former</hi> Invites Chapmen to buy his <hi>true Treaſure, unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Riches, Gold Tryed in the</hi> Fire, <hi>Royal Robes</hi> of his own Righteouſneſs, the choiceſt Opthalmicks or <hi>Eye-Salve,</hi> the <hi>Waters of Life,</hi> the <hi>Wine of the</hi> Spirit, the <hi>Milk</hi> of <hi>Couſolation,</hi> &amp;c. And all theſe <hi>without Money</hi> and without <hi>Price,</hi> Iſa. 55.1. Rev. 3.18. Eph. 3.8. Iſa. 66.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the <hi>latter</hi> Wheadles <hi>ſimple ones</hi> (as above) to buy his <hi>Traſh</hi> and <hi>Trumpery,</hi> yet credulous Fools muſt part with much Money, and a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious price for them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, theſe <hi>Commodities</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> as ſet down in the <hi>Catalogue</hi> under ſuch Glittering Titles, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.12, 13. <hi>Gold, Silver,</hi> &amp;c. look nothing like to <hi>Traſh</hi> and <hi>Trumpery:</hi> To this I anſwer, the Book
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52972:50"/>
of the <hi>Revelation</hi> is ſo Abſtruſe and Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, that it requires another <hi>Revelation</hi> to unfold its Myſtery: I confeſs, I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted ſome Learned Interpreters upon the place: But that which is <hi>Inſtar Omnium,</hi> and gives a None-Such Interpretation is the <hi>chief Auditor</hi> of the Apoſtolick Chamber in his Infallible Account Book.</p>
            <p>Never did the <hi>profoundeſt Interpreter</hi> (no not the Accuteſt of their own <hi>Popiſh Poſtillers</hi>) make a plainer Explanation of any Dark Scripture, than this Popes <hi>Auditor Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> hath made of <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.12.13. All the Voluminous Quirks of the moſt Mercurial <hi>Jeſuits [Cajetan, Mendoza, Salmeron,</hi> &amp;c.] are comparatively but Inſiped Stuff, and dull Deſcants to that one <hi>Auditors Record</hi> of the Romiſh Merchandiſe in this Popes Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Chamber. Yea, the <hi>Chaldee Paraphraſe,</hi> or <hi>Onkeles</hi> (ſo much cry'd up in the World) is but a <hi>Jejune Piece</hi> to it. <hi>This</hi> is the <hi>Maſter Piece</hi> of all, wherein what be the <hi>Romiſh Pearls and precious Stones,</hi> &amp;c. are made ſo <hi>Legible</hi> and <hi>Intelligible,</hi> that every common Capacity may both <hi>Apprehend</hi> and <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi> the right Notion of them.</p>
            <p>In that known Court-Rolls and Rate-Book, is Regiſtred, and made publick the common and current Price of a many choice and curious Commodities, as <hi>Pardons, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, </hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:52972:50"/>
               <hi>Licenſes, Abſolutions,</hi> &amp;c. what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you have a mind to buy: Indeed the <hi>Crys</hi> of Vendible Wares in the Streets of <hi>London [will you buy this,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and will you buy that,</hi> &amp;c.] are both [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>manifold</hi> and ſomewhat hard to be underſtood, eſpecially in ſome of the <hi>cryes:</hi> but the <hi>cryes</hi> and <hi>outcryes</hi> in the <hi>Streets of Rome,</hi> do far exceed the beſt of <hi>ours,</hi> yea that of <hi>Dainty Trotters, Curious Trotters:</hi> But they that have a mind to <hi>Trot</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> may <hi>There</hi> hear far better <hi>Crys,</hi> as this for one <hi>[will ye buy any Bodies, will ye buy any Souls of Men?]</hi> This is a Raree-Show In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and ſuch a <hi>Tickling, Tempting-Cry,</hi> as will cauſe empty Houſes, who would not Run out (though the Pot be boiling upon the Fire, and the Spit turning at it) to ſee the <hi>Wonders of the Beaſt?</hi> Revel. 13.3, 13, 14. Who would not but deſire to be a Chapman for (at leaſt to Cheap) his Rare Commodities?</p>
            <p>But becauſe it may ſeem a little below His <hi>Highneſs</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> to become a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cryer, He hath learnt the Trick of our Nimble <hi>Quacks</hi> and <hi>Don Quick-Sots;</hi> as every common <hi>Quack</hi> and <hi>Mountebank,</hi> Prints now his Bills, Hands them out <hi>Gratis</hi> with much Generoſity, yet catches <hi>Children and Fools</hi> enough to pay for them; there
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:52972:51"/>
you have ſet down, <hi>Elixir Vitae</hi> at ſo much, <hi>Elixir Salutis</hi> at ſo much, the <hi>Golden Spirit</hi> at ſo much, the <hi>Scurvy Spirit</hi> at ſo much, <hi>Sovereign Powder</hi> for ſo much, the <hi>Plaiſter,</hi> call'd <hi>All-Heal,</hi> for ſo much, and Twenty Rarities more (all <hi>Arcanums</hi>) none At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to ſuch a Secret as himſelf; every thing Expoſed is good for all things, if but a <hi>Thumb-Bottle</hi> of his Liquor be Bought, 'twill Cure all Diſeaſes; if but a little of his Balſom be Applied, 'twill Heal all Wounds. What <hi>Madmen</hi> be theſe to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Slain or Die in the midſt of ſo many Antidotes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Mountebank</hi> goes a little further, He comes forth <hi>Cum Regis Privilegio,</hi> makes Experiments upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, both in <hi>Stabbings</hi> and <hi>Poiſonings,</hi> Builds his Theatre, whereon he Expoſeth all his <hi>Cheating Tricks</hi> to Publick View, and when the Credulous come not in faſt enough to make their Markets there, his <hi>Merry-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> muſt Dance upon a Rope, play Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pretty Pranks (yet all the while more Knave than Fool) to Decoy them, and yet when all is done, few more than the Rabble are Caught in the Snare.</p>
            <p>So this <hi>Grand Quack</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Mountebank,</hi> Prints his Bills <hi>Cum Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio,</hi> commends to the Life his Curſed Wares, Acts all the parts of the former to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52972:51"/>
a Threed, yet Advances upon an Higher Stage. And indeed, His Wares have a ſtrange Operation. If but a <hi>Thumb-Bottle</hi> of his <hi>Wine of Fornication</hi> be Drunk, it will ſtrangely Intoxicate even the <hi>Kings of the Earth.</hi> And his <hi>Jeſuits Powder</hi> will work Wonders.</p>
            <p>But not to detain you in the Dark any longer, If you have a mind to be Cheated, or only to ſee his Cheats, you'l find <hi>his Printed Bills,</hi> Publiſh'd to the whole World with <hi>Antichriſts Arms</hi> ſtamp'd upon them, in his <hi>Taxa Camerae Apoſtolicae,</hi> where you have the <hi>Scarlet Whore's Adulterated</hi> Wares particularly Repreſented, both in their <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Properties, Profits</hi> and <hi>Prices,</hi> yea, and there is <hi>Morſus Diaboli,</hi> the Herb call'd <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil-bit,</hi> to wrap them up in, caſt into the Bargain.</p>
            <p>Take only an <hi>Antipharmacon,</hi> a <hi>Divine Allay</hi> and <hi>Preſervative,</hi> along with you, leaſt your Noſtrils be offended, and your Vital and Animal Spirits contract any Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Contagion, while I am (to ſatisfie your Curioſity) but a little way <hi>Digging</hi> into this <hi>ſtinking Dunghil.</hi> I have good War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for this my good Work, in laying open the Cheating Abominations of this <hi>Scarlet Coloured Beaſt.</hi> As that <hi>Man of God,</hi> great <hi>Elijah</hi> could not tell how to <hi>Ridicule</hi> enough
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:52972:52"/>
the Prophane <hi>Prieſts of Baal,</hi> 1 Kings 18.27. Much more may I <hi>Ridicule</hi> the Grand Maſter of them, and this cannot be better done, than by giving you but a brief Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skip of the <hi>Roman</hi> Merchandize, a bare <hi>Recitatim</hi> whereof is a ſufficient <hi>Refutation</hi> to any Sober and Right Thinking Mind.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtolical Chamber</hi> Poſts up its [<hi>Si Quis,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>If any one</hi> want this or that Popiſh Trumpery, they may <hi>come</hi> and be <hi>welcome</hi> at this <hi>preſent Popes</hi> Ware-houſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always they come with Money in their Hands, and come up to the current Price (by Canon-Law) of each Vendible Commodity: come along my Hearts, <hi>My Son, Give me thy Heart.</hi> You ſhall have <hi>Robin Hood</hi> Penniworths, enough for your Money in all Conſcience: becauſe you are all Friends, you ſhall all be very Kindly Uſed, and ſo <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Schedule or Liſt of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Wares, this <hi>Pope</hi> (the <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Manour</hi>) Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to Sale by Inch of Candle, take as followeth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimis, He</hi> Expoſeth his Pick-pocketing <hi>Pardons</hi> of all ſorts and ſizes, and the Prices thereof (in ſome of them) are ſet down in Black and White upon the Popes Tables hung out to Publick View, or ſomething <hi>Equivalent.</hi> As<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:52972:52"/>Firſt, A <hi>Pardon</hi> for the Third part of your Sins, equally Divided by Indifferent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for Seven Pound Ten Shillings, and if you would Buy off the other Two parts, 'twill Coſt you Two and Twenty Pound Ten Shillings, and a very Rich Penniworth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A <hi>Pardon</hi> for Forty Eight Years Sins, as you can Agree with this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Pope;</hi> He is a very <hi>Innocent,</hi> you may poſſibly Wheadle him to your own Terms with Nuts and Apples, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, A <hi>Pardon</hi> for Two Thouſand Eight Hundred Years, confirm'd by Pope <hi>Paſchal</hi> the Firſt, by <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, and by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, and now under a New Ratification by this Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eleventh; this may be had Dog-cheap, only for ſaying a few very ſhort Prayers in the right Critical Hour, betwixt the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of the Hoſt and Three <hi>Agnus Dei</hi>'s, This would keep you out of <hi>Purgatory</hi> for a long time upon eaſie Terms.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, A <hi>Pardon</hi> for Thirty Three Thouſand Years at a very low Rate, only for once going up a pair of Stairs, which, you muſt ſuppoſe, were the very ſame that Chriſt Aſcended, when he appeard before <hi>Pontius Pilate.</hi> Here's <hi>great Wages</hi> for a <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Work;</hi> and he's a Fool in Grain, that will not Purchaſe ſuch a cheap Pardon for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:52972:53"/>
ſo long a Time, provided he may have <hi>general Warranty</hi> for ſecuring his Bargain till that Time be Expir'd; and much more of this Traſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, Abſolutions</hi> of various Prices, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording the Crime committed. As</p>
            <p>Firſt, For <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> Ten Shillings and Six Pence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For <hi>Symony</hi> in a <hi>Prieſt</hi> the ſame Price, but in a <hi>Lay-Man</hi> the odd Eighteen Pence ſhall be Baited. Kindly done.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For <hi>Perjury,</hi> 'tis a Rich Penny-worth at Nine Shillings.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, For <hi>Murder,</hi> If it be a Prieſt that is Kill'd, it cannot be Dear at one [Two Pence] more than a <hi>Mark,</hi> I would never be a Prieſt there, where my Life is no higher Valued. But you may Kill your <hi>Father, Mother, Wife</hi> or <hi>Siſter,</hi> &amp;c. upon eaſier Terms, That ſhall but coſt you Ten Shillings and Six Pence.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, For <hi>Adultery,</hi> Deflouring a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin goes at Nine Shillings, but <hi>Inceſt</hi> with Mother, Siſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is cheaper, paſſing at Seven Shillings and Six Pence. And the <hi>Whore</hi> that Deſtroys her Baſtard Child ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or after Birth, hath the ſelf ſame Sum to pay.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, For <hi>Burning a Neighbours Houſe</hi> is Dog-cheap at Twelve Shillings; but for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:52972:53"/>
Burning Heretical Cities, 'tis ſeverely Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with being <hi>Canoniz'd for Saints,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, Licenſes</hi> for what you Liſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you be a Prieſt you may keep a Whore, paying only Ten Shillings and Six Pence; and if a Lay-Man it will coſt you no more; that the one may not De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride the other.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A <hi>Licenſe</hi> to be Lazy, and to become an <hi>Abby-Lubber,</hi> and ſo to be <hi>Inutile pondus Terrae,</hi> Living there like Hogs in the <hi>Stie,</hi> unuſeful to Mankind, unleſs to the <hi>Wanton Nuns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, A <hi>Licenſe</hi> to be Licentious, and to have the liberty of the Stews the Three Hot Months of the Year, there is the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Recipe</hi> preſcrib'd (with Dr. Pope's <hi>probatum eſt) ad purgandos Renes.</hi> This <hi>Grand Quack,</hi> or great <hi>Mountebank,</hi> is Tender of his <hi>Proſelytes</hi> Health, Allows this Remedy (which God never thought of, when he ſaid, <hi>'Tis not good for Man to be alone,</hi> Gen. 3.18.) to prevent his Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings (under the <hi>Vow of Chaſtity</hi>) from falling into Acute Fevers, and to ſhew how good Natured he will be to them (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering it had been his own needful Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg and Practice) you may have theſe Two laſt Licenſes (both to be <hi>Lazy</hi> and to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:52972:54"/>
be <hi>Licenticus) Gratis.</hi> Gra-Mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Kind Heart, they ſhall not coſt you a Penny.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Yet a <hi>Licenſe</hi> to <hi>Eat Fleſh in Lent,</hi> will coſt you much more, for his Un-Holineſs Infallibly Judgeth this to be a far greater Sin <hi>than to keep a Whore.</hi> Yea, and many more <hi>Indulgences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Here you may have <hi>Holy Water</hi> Chymically prepared, <hi>Secundum Artem Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolicam,</hi> for driving away the Devil, hence comes that Popiſh Proverb, to expreſs ſomething that is <hi>Hateful, [A Man loves it as well as the Devil loves Holy Water.]</hi> You muſt ſuppoſe, <hi>that Water</hi> which the Pope Conjures into the like <hi>Holineſs</hi> with his own, is able to Conjure away the ſtrongeſt Devil in Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> You may have <hi>Holy Oil,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded according to the ſame Art, only 'tis an <hi>Arcanum</hi> and <hi>Magiſterial.</hi> The Pope hath been ſo kind to let the World know how he makes his <hi>Holy Water,</hi> Piſſing it out by Conjuration; but <hi>he</hi> hath a mind to be <hi>private</hi> in Conſecrating his <hi>Holy Oil,</hi> and when he hath done his beſt to it, have a care you eat it not with a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Sallet, leaſt it be mix'd with <hi>Jeſuits Powder;</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, 'tis good enough to Liquor your Boots after your long Journey to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:52972:54"/>No doubt but it ſerves notably as an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent for (far better than for <hi>anointing the Sick</hi> to make them well) the <hi>Popes Charet Wheels,</hi> makes them run glib in all Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marine Countreys, and is now calling for a waſt over into ours; do not you hear Him at <hi>Callice,</hi> Crying, <hi>have over for</hi> Dover, <hi>have over for</hi> England: God grant Him contrary Winds, but if the <hi>Prince of the Air</hi> muſt be permitted to lend Him a lift with a <hi>Favonian</hi> or Favourable Wind, God grant, this proud Myſtical <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Aegypt,</hi> Rev. 11.8. May meet with no better a <hi>Fate</hi> and <hi>Fare,</hi> than that <hi>Litteral King of Aegypt did;</hi> who, though for ought we know to the contrary, had as fair <hi>way</hi> and <hi>weather</hi> into the midſt of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had, yet when Irrecoverably brought into an unavoidable Nooſe (which He could not Slip nor Retreat from) then <hi>God looked out of the black</hi> ſide of the Cloud (which was <hi>towards His Hoſt,</hi> as the <hi>bright ſide was toward</hi> Iſrael) with an angry Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, took off His <hi>Charet Wheels,</hi> made them (though never ſo well Oyled with <hi>His Prieſts Holy Oyl) drive Heavily,</hi> then dows'd Him with a Witneſs, and drown'd Him (too) with a Vengeance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.7.20. 22, 23, 24, 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I cannot but be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the Lord will look through this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:52972:55"/>
               <hi>black cloudy Diſpenſation,</hi> with a <hi>look of Love</hi> upon his own People (as he did upon <hi>poor perplexed Peter,</hi> Luke 22.61.) and with a <hi>look of Wrath</hi> upon this great <hi>Leviathan,</hi> His <hi>Holy Oyl</hi> ſhall fall His <hi>Chariot Wheels,</hi> and they ſhall never become as the <hi>Chariots</hi> of <hi>Aminadab, England</hi> cannot ever be a <hi>willing People</hi> to Receive Him:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Here you may have His <hi>Holy Salt</hi> alſo, this is ſoundly <hi>Conjur'd</hi> likewiſe into as good an Holineſs as that of His <hi>Holy Water,</hi> or as that of His <hi>own Holineſs:</hi> and with this <hi>Holy Stuff</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> works His Mighty Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and Wonders: What place ſoever hath this <hi>Holy Salt</hi> ſcattered upon it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Devil</hi> nor any of his <hi>evil Spirits</hi> have any power againſt it: 'Tis a wonder there ſhould be ſo many Houſes, Haunted with Hobgoblins all over His <hi>Holineſſes Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,</hi> Surely, either His <hi>Holy Salt</hi> hath loſt its efficatious Vertue, or <hi>Himſelf</hi> hath loſt the Right Art to Conſecrate it, or more likely, the Devil is in His Prieſts that they Improve it not. 'Tis a wonder this <hi>old Sc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſter</hi> doth not daſh whole handfuls of this <hi>Holy Salt</hi> in the Eyes of thoſe Raw <hi>Freſhmen</hi> (thoſe <hi>Novicet</hi> as he calls the <hi>Proteſtants</hi>) and ſo to blind them for ever. But though this will not do (<hi>His Holy Salt</hi> having loſt its Efficacy) He hath a better Trick behind
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:52972:55"/>
far more Bloudy, He would <hi>Bleed</hi> and <hi>Burn</hi> thoſe He cannot <hi>Blind:</hi> If His <hi>Holy Salt have loſt its Savour</hi> (as indeed it hath,) otherwiſe there could never have been ſo much Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, for want of Seaſoning, both among Popes and His Popelings) what is it good to, but to be <hi>caſt to the Dunghil,</hi> and to be <hi>Troden Underfoot?</hi> Matth. 5.13. <hi>England</hi> is as the <hi>Garden of Eden,</hi> never any <hi>Pope</hi> that paſſed through the <hi>Porphury Chair</hi> (ever ſince the <hi>Writ of Ejectment</hi> was by an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Hand Served upon Him to diſpoſſeſs that Devil in the Reformation) but He hath lick'd his Lips, and longed after ſome ſweet Lettuces, that Grow in this <hi>Engliſh Garden,</hi> God grant it may be, as the Law calls that Writ, an <hi>Ejectione Firmae:</hi> that this <hi>evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> (once caſt out) may not find the <hi>Houſe</hi> of our Land (which, God knows is now neither <hi>Swept</hi> of Moral Vices, nor <hi>Garniſhed,</hi> with Moral Vertues, but too much over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with Epidemical-Immortality) <hi>empty</hi> alſo of all Grace, and ſo Return with <hi>Seven worſe Spirits than the forwer,</hi> Matth. 12.43, 44, 45. I would to God, <hi>England</hi> were not ſo much like <hi>Jericho, whoſe Situation was pleaſant, but the Waters were naughty:</hi> Our freſh River of <hi>Thames</hi> ſeems to Run ſo near the ſalt Waters of <hi>Tybur</hi> (ever ſince the <hi>Beaſt fouled our Fountains with his Feet,</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:52972:56"/>
Ezek. 34, 18.) that they taſt a little <hi>Brackiſh</hi> and ſomewhat Imbib'd with the <hi>Salt-Sea of Rome,</hi> 'Tis too much Tinged with the <hi>Tincture</hi> of its <hi>Holy Salt,</hi> Oh where is that <hi>Eliſha,</hi> that will take a Cruſe of <hi>better Salt</hi> (than this <hi>Popes Holy Salt</hi> is) happily to hand in, that our <hi>Waters may be Healed,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Kings 2.19, 20, 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Here is expoſed to Sale the <hi>Holy Milk</hi> of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> which, ſome of the Popes Doctours affirm, is as Sovereign and Salvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical as the Bloud of her Son our Saviour. However, 'Tis commended moſt Highly for never-failing to cure Conſumptions, far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the Milk of an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> or that of the <hi>Red-Cow.</hi> What Fools are the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Phtiſical Popelings, that have ſuch a Ready Cure by them, yet ſo many dye of a <hi>Conſumption,</hi> which is ſo <hi>Ranting</hi> and <hi>Regnant</hi> a Diſeaſe in thoſe <hi>Hot Climates:</hi> Nay, What a Fool is the Conſumptive <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt</hi> himſelf, who doth not by this truſty trick diſapoint the Divine Doom paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon him, what need he Fear <hi>[that the Lord ſhall CONSUME Him with the Spirit of his Mouth.]</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.8. Seeing an Hearty Draught of this <hi>Holy Milk</hi> will cure the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: This Pope might then ſay as one of his Holy Predeceſſours once ſaid, I will have my Will <hi>[Al deſpito di dio]</hi> in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:52972:56"/>
of God; But the miſcheif is, neither the Pope nor his Popelings dare take a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doſe of this Salutiferous Antidote, for fear of marring the General Market hereof, 'tis a long time ſince the Bleſſed Virgin gave her Milk, and they can expect none in her Glorified Breaſts, the <hi>old Stock</hi> (ſuppoſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one take but a little ſup, though that is not enough) muſt needs be far ſpent in above Sixteen Hundred Years, and where or how theſe Traders make their <hi>old Store</hi> bring in <hi>new,</hi> I know not, unleſs that <hi>Image</hi> of the Virgin (which bid <hi>Bernard Good Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> at his entrance into the Church, and whom that Father Rebuked, becauſe She a Woman, took upon her (contrary to the Truly Apoſtolical Canon) to ſpeak in the Church, might ſupply, for that Idol of Stone might equally and as Probably have <hi>Milk in its Breaſt</hi> as well as a <hi>Voice in its Mouth:</hi> But that which ſpoil'd the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this freſh ſupply of <hi>Holy Milk,</hi> was the Diſcovery of a crafty Prieſt that was crept into the Hollow Belly of this Holy Image, and that gave Holy <hi>Bernard</hi> the Hearty Salutation, and ſure I am, there could not be much <hi>Holy Milk</hi> in ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate Prieſts Breaſt, who durſt put ſuch an affronting Cheat upon ſo Holy a Father. But ſuppoſe there were ſupply then, 'tis
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:52972:57"/>
above 500 Years ago, and this cry <hi>[will ye have any holy Milk,</hi> &amp;c.] that Milk-ſtreet Market muſt needs be down ere now, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their <hi>Milk-Maids</hi> (whereof they cannot have many, while the Indulged Stews afford his Unholineſs ſuch a vaſt Revenue) are now ſurely ſitting upon their Empty Pales: But I had forgot my ſelf that the Beaſt can work Wonders, and can multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that <hi>Holy Milk</hi> (though but little from the Bleſſed Virgin) as well as Chriſt did the <hi>Barly Leaves;</hi> Yea, He hath done it to ſuch an overflow, that the Prieſts (all the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom over) do expoſe this <hi>Holy Milk</hi> to Sale, all pretending that theirs is the very Milk of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> which, were all they have in their Conſecrated Dairy's gathered together into one place, <hi>Solomons</hi> prodigious <hi>Molten</hi> Sea could not poſſibly contain it. Nay, hereby they put the greateſt Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon the Holy Mother of our Lord (whom they pretend to Adore) in making Her ſuch a <hi>Milk-Beaſt,</hi> as <hi>Ten</hi> of the beſt Cows in <hi>Holland</hi> cannot give the like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity in Ten Years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item, Holy-Bread</hi> is here to be had: The Pope (good Man) takes care for your Table, and to furniſh it ſo far as <hi>Holy Water, Holy Oyl, Holy Salt, Holy Milk,</hi> and <hi>Holy Bread</hi> will go: But ſurely all theſe do but
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:52972:57"/>
look like a Lent Dinner, I hope his Holineſs keeps a better Table for Himſelf: If you be a <hi>Water Drinker,</hi> here's the beſt of the Kind, <hi>Holy Water</hi> for you, of the Popes own <hi>making,</hi> I ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Conſecrating:</hi> If you be a <hi>Milk-Sop,</hi> Here's the beſt of the Kind, Holy <hi>Milk,</hi> the ſelf ſame your Saviour Sucked out of the ſelf-ſame Breaſts, when he was a Child, and who will not be content with the ſame Fare that Bred the Bleſſed Babe of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> the <hi>Holy Child Jeſus,</hi> and becauſe the <hi>Maſter</hi> of this <hi>Lent-Feaſt,</hi> will not undervalue you as a ſort of ſorry Sucklings, He is ſo <hi>Kind-hearted</hi> as to allow you <hi>Bread</hi> to your <hi>Milk,</hi> that you may <hi>ſup</hi> it and not <hi>ſuck</hi> it, is not <hi>biting</hi> and <hi>ſupping</hi> good Fare? eſpecially, of <hi>Holy Bread</hi> and <hi>Holy Milk.</hi> You muſt not expect a Glaſs of Wine, for I find not any <hi>Holy Wine</hi> in the <hi>Popes Ware-ſhop.</hi> Perhaps he and his <hi>Prieſts</hi> Monopolizes it wholly to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for in the Euchariſt, the Cup is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to you of the Laity, you muſt ſuck <hi>Wine</hi> out of the <hi>Bread,</hi> If you would have it, and can catch it.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt you grudge that you have onely Bread (though it be but courſe Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley Bread, ſuch as you were never poſſibly brought up with) 'tis however <hi>Holy Bread,</hi> and the <hi>Holier,</hi> and ſo more ſatisfactory,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:52972:58"/>
becauſe (as this <hi>Mart-Maſter</hi> tells you) 'tis a <hi>Fragment</hi> of thoſe ſame <hi>Five Loaves</hi> wherewith <hi>Chriſt fed the Multitude,</hi> and picked out of the Twelve Baskets <hi>(that were taken away)</hi> by ſome of the Popes nimbleſt Snips, but I wonder how they have kept it from Moulding ever ſince, The <hi>Moulded Bread</hi> wherewith the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> cheated <hi>Joſhua,</hi> was not ſo many <hi>Hours</hi> old, as this <hi>Holy Bread</hi> is <hi>Years,</hi> at this Day. If it be <hi>Sound Bread</hi> that is ſhewn you, take heed you be not cheated with it, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> was with the <hi>Mouldy:</hi> But you will ſay, why is <hi>Holy Salt</hi> prepared for the Table, when the forementioned Fare needs it not? <hi>Anſwer,</hi> You muſt know 'tis not ſet there for Faſhion-ſake onely, as ordinarily, for</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Here you may have <hi>Holy Fiſh</hi> too, and of the ſelf-ſame <hi>two Fiſhes</hi> wherewith Chriſt Fed the Multitude alſo, the <hi>Bread</hi> and the <hi>Fiſh</hi> were taken out of the ſame Baskets; and if you ſuppoſe it <hi>Freſh Fiſh,</hi> then there is uſe for your Salt, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent your Second Objection about the uſe of your <hi>Oyl,</hi> you muſt rather ſuppoſe it <hi>Holy Fiſh</hi> Salted with that <hi>Holy Salt,</hi> (it could never have otherwiſe kept ſo long ſweet for this Sixteen Centuries) and then your <hi>Holy Oyl</hi> will make your <hi>Holy Fiſh</hi> (ſo called) ſlip down the better, and be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:52972:58"/>
enough, and what would you have more, is not here enough for a <hi>Four Penny Ordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Beſides this Belly-Timber, here you are Treated with a Numberleſs Number of <hi>Rarieties.</hi> As</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Aſſes</hi> Tail upon which Chriſt Rode; not a word of his <hi>Ears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Joſephs Breeches</hi> both Thread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare and out of Faſhion, they will do you neither Credit nor Service.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A Feather from the Cock that Crew, and awaken'd <hi>Peters</hi> Conſcience; yet this Startles not <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor for his Apoſtacy; as alſo a Feather from <hi>Grabriels</hi> Wing, taken up at ſuch a time when as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels caſt their Feathers.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Choice Hair Cloth, the ſame as <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> wore, good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the Pope to do Penance in, for forcing the Witneſſes into Sack-Cloth.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Whole Cart Loads of <hi>Apoſtles Bones,</hi> ſometimes thoſe of a Thief (as once) drops in among them; good for I know not what.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Sold at a very Reaſonable Rate,</p>
            <p>Firſt, An Holy Rag clip'd off from Chriſts Seamleſs Coat; 'tis a wonder how the Pope got it from the Soldier to whom it fell by caſting Lots, and 'tis a wonder they
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:52972:59"/>
have not clip'd it all away by, this time.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Holy Relick of the very <hi>Slippers</hi> Chriſt wore, when He, being wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with <hi>walking about doing Good,</hi> put off his Shoes, for the eaſe of his Feet, ſurely they were made of well Tan'd Leather, that laſts ſtill, and are not Rotten to Dirt ere this Day, and I wonder the Pope doth expoſe them, and not Monopolize them to himſeif, for they cannot want a Vertue to Cure his Gouty Golls: 'Tis ſtrange we hear nothing of his Shooes (in the Popes Warehouſe) the Latchets whereof, <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> (though the <hi>Greateſt Born of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>) thought himſelf Unworthy to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe, <hi>Matth</hi> 11.11. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The very <hi>Linnen Cloth</hi> with which <hi>Chriſt</hi> was wrap'd in the Sepulchre, as likewiſe that wherewith Chriſt wiped his Diſciples Feet. I am thinking the Man that Cries in our Streets, <hi>[Here's your ſtrong laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Linnen Cloth,]</hi> might do good Service in this <hi>Romiſh</hi> Market.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The very <hi>Needles, Thread, Work-Basket</hi> and <hi>Sciſſers,</hi> of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> which would be excellently uſeful for an Exchange-ſhop, and could not ſail to bring in a whole ſhoal of Chapmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How the Pope comes by all theſe Rich Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:52972:59"/>
for all kind of Cuſtomers, is the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion? But the Infallible Tradition of the Church muſt be the Satisfactory and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencing Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Laſtly, Here you may have, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your Heart wiſhes, or Need doth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Is it any of thoſe many things men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.12, 13. Rich all, here they are to be had. Want you <hi>Holy Bells</hi> (Baptized with God-Fathers and God-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) God Bleſs our Empty New Erected Steeples, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or want you <hi>Holy Beads,</hi> made of <hi>Glaſs, Wood, Stone, Coral</hi> or <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; Holy Wax</hi> for your Candles; <hi>Holy Knives</hi> for Cutting Hereticks Throats; or <hi>Holy Roſes,</hi> this <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> time, a Rare <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> for <hi>Princes;</hi> or what elſe ſoever, all is Holy that comes from his Unholineſs; and all have a Power to drive away the Devil, yet the Devil takes moſt of thoſe that are taken with theſe <hi>[Piae Fraudes] Holy Cheats.</hi> None of their <hi>Names are Writ in the Lambs Book,</hi> Revel. 13.8. God Bleſs every good <hi>Engliſhman</hi> from the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his Cheating Tricks.</p>
            <p>Having taken a ſhort proſpect of the <hi>Craft</hi> of this <hi>Inſatiable Beaſt</hi> (to keep cloſe ſtill unto the <hi>Iriſh Malachi</hi>'s Character of this <hi>preſent Pope</hi>) let us now take a brief View of his <hi>Cruelty.</hi> He is a moſt Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:52972:60"/>
               <hi>Beaſt,</hi> his <hi>Infallible Unholineſs</hi> is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by an Infallible Hand (the Spirit of Truth himſelf) in his moſt Horrible Accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trements, no leſs than <hi>Seven Heads to Plot. with,</hi> for the more <hi>crafty</hi> carrying on of all his <hi>Gainful Cheats,</hi> and no leſs than <hi>Ten Horns</hi> to <hi>puſh his Plots endway with,</hi> and to puſh all down (that ſtand in his way) with <hi>Unparrallel'd Cruelty.</hi> To pretermit all former Bloudy Plots in foregoing Ages of this preſent Popes Predeceſſors, againſt all Proteſtant Countries, ever ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and againſt <hi>England</hi> in particular, both in <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi>'s, <hi>King James</hi>'s, and in <hi>King Charles</hi>'s the Firſt's Time. I ſhall confine my ſelf to Characterize this <hi>Inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Beaſt,</hi> the <hi>Devils Patriarch,</hi> that now Poſſeſſeth the <hi>Roman Omnipotency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Name is <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Eleventh,</hi> who after his Inſtalment, was Arrayed with a White <hi>Surplice,</hi> wherein he Worſhip'd that God which had now Conſtituted him the <hi>Univerſal</hi> Monarch; in this White Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ſeem'd as pure as <hi>Innocence</hi> it ſelf, there was nothing ſurely under it, but <hi>Meekneſs, Gentleneſs,</hi> and Lamb-like <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</hi> You might then ſtroke the <hi>Beaſt, He</hi> would not ſpurn you, you might put your Hand into his very Mouth, <hi>He</hi> by no means would Bite you. No, <hi>He</hi> had newly put
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:52972:60"/>
on the Name of <hi>Innocent,</hi> and He was (what ever he had been while a <hi>Cardinal</hi>) now become an <hi>Innocent Pope,</hi> a Toothleſs <hi>Innocent</hi> Milk-Sop, that would neither Kick, nor Fling, nor Scratch, nor Bite; but the miſchief was, <hi>He</hi> ſoon after going to his Court-Office, <hi>De propagandi Fide</hi> to a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult</hi> there, coming thither without his White Garment (that Reach'd down to his Foot) His <hi>Red Shoes,</hi> and <hi>Red Stockins,</hi> were there Unhappily Diſcovered. At that <hi>Conſult He</hi> Declar'd his Determinations, That he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd <hi>(Adjuvante Diabolo)</hi> to Reduce all the Heretical Countreys in <hi>Europe</hi> into the Subjection of His <hi>Roman See,</hi> and He ſaid (for a flying Argument) 'twas below <hi>both</hi> his <hi>Higneſs</hi> and his <hi>Holineſs</hi> to prove ſuch a poor Puny, as his Predeceſſors, in playing ſuch ſmall Games as they had done; He would (for his part) <hi>Take New Meaſures,</hi> and <hi>Make ſuch Methods,</hi> as neither <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Devil</hi> could be able to Diſapoint him of his Deſign. Whereupon for the better <hi>Propoga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Popiſh Faith,</hi> He <hi>propoſeth</hi> theſe following Expedients, and not only ſo, but <hi>Impoſeth</hi> them alſo upon that his <hi>Privy-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> who dare not gain-ſay their God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt Propoſal Impoſed,</hi> was this, <hi>Go forth</hi> you my <hi>Emiſſaries,</hi> and Debauch the Heretical Countreys, Foiſt your <hi>Looſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:52972:61"/>
(Calculated for, and Accomodated to, the Depraved Natures of Mankind in general) this will ſoon bring Men to <hi>Looſe Practices;</hi> 'Tis found by Experience (ſaith He in great Gravity, comporting with his <hi>Grandeur</hi>) a <hi>Proſperous Bait</hi> to Catch, and a <hi>Powerful Hook</hi> to Hold whole Shoals of Proſelites. I am a <hi>Fiſher of Men,</hi> as my Predeceſſor <hi>Peter</hi> was, yet I have a Trick, which He (ſimple Fiſher-man) never thought of, or Practic'd; I can make Men <hi>Atheiſts</hi> in their Lives, and then they will turn <hi>Papiſts</hi> the ſooner, for ſtopping the Mouths of their Natural Conſciences (which will be Barking) the better with my precious Pardons, whereby I can make the worſt of Sins Venial, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Expedient</hi> propounded by this Pope there was this, You <hi>Jeſuits</hi> muſt be my <hi>Locuſts,</hi> my <hi>Beutefeaus</hi> to go into the Courts of all theſe Kingdomes, and ſet them all on a light Fire (in Warring one againſt another) that my Religion (which hath grown very cold ever ſince Unhappy <hi>Luther</hi> call'd the <hi>Pope, Antichriſt</hi>) may be warmed again with thoſe very <hi>Flames</hi> that I (by you my Engines) have kindled. You know, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath made me a <hi>Fiſher of Men,</hi> as before, and I find it beſt Fiſhing in <hi>Troubled Waters.</hi> Nay, I am the true <hi>Salamander,</hi> that can beſt
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:52972:61"/>
live in the Flames, of Foreign and Secular Princes Contentions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Propoſal</hi> was, to <hi>Depoſe thoſe Kings that will not Truckle,</hi> and to <hi>Expoſe</hi> their Kingdomes, <hi>primo occupaturo,</hi> the firſt that can win it, let them wear it, I will warrant the Aſſault of the Aggreſſor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fourth nimble Trick he Propoſed was, ſaying, Though I have a Thauſand more Reaching and Effectual Knacks to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, yet ſeeing you know them all ſo well, 'tis ſuperfluous to mention more, ſave onely this, which is, <hi>Inſtar Omnium.</hi> You muſt in Reducing all others, Begin with that <hi>Stubborn Kingdome of England,</hi> which hath been more fatal to my Tripple Crown than all other Kingdomes, and when you have made a <hi>Breakfaſt</hi> of that, then make your <hi>Dinner</hi> of this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and your <hi>Supper</hi> of that, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo <hi>go on</hi> and my <hi>Bleſſing go with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ended the <hi>Seraphical</hi> or rather <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical</hi> Oration of this <hi>Innocent</hi> Grave old Gentleman that never did, nor ever will do Harm to any.</p>
            <p>This done, the Damnable Popiſh Plot was in all its Parts and Paragraphs contrived, &amp;c. The Romiſh Fry of <hi>Prieſts and Jeſuits,</hi> (who were ſoon Hatch'd and grew Fledge under his Holineſs's Wing) came Flying over in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:52972:62"/>
great Wild-gooſe Flocks into <hi>England,</hi> we may ſuppoſe they came fully furniſhed with their <hi>Pick-Iccks</hi> of <hi>Pardons,</hi> with their <hi>Pad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks</hi> of <hi>Auricular Confeſſion,</hi> and all other uſeful Engines to promote their Helliſh <hi>Project,</hi> the Sum whereof in the general was, to Subvert the Eſtabliſh'd Government and Religion of this Kingdom, and to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame to the <hi>Foppery</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> yea, and 'twas concluded at the Conſult (which theſe Romiſh Emiſſaries came to Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh) that no manner of Tolleration ſhould be granted to any ſort of Proteſtants, but all ſuch ſhould be Extirpated <hi>Root &amp; Branch,</hi> and if all other means failed, it ſhould be effected by <hi>Fire and Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cheif Conſpirators, who deſigned, and were engaged to carry on this Bloudy project, muſt be thus Ranked in a laſting Record.</p>
            <p>☞ <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Fountain of theſe Bitter Waters, and Original of all, was this <hi>Preſent Pope Innocent</hi> the 11th, who in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>[de propaganda Fide]</hi> conſiſting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 350 Perſons, (all fit Tools for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Work) and held about <hi>December</hi> 1677. as ſoon as he was well warm in <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, He Plots (even in that cold Seaſon) work Hot enough for poor <hi>England:</hi> Then was it He belchd out that <hi>nocent</hi> rather than <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:52972:62"/>
Oration aforementioned, Declaring fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that this Kingdome was a part of St. <hi>Peters Patrimony,</hi> and was forfeited to the Holy See, by the Hereſy both of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and ſo muſt be diſpoſed of as he thought meet: though this <hi>Pope</hi> was the <hi>primus motor,</hi> the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> or great Wheel that moved all the lower Orbs, and ſet all the leſſer Wheels on Work, yet let us take a ſhort view of his Under-Engines, before we more fully give him his due Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, upon this <hi>laſt</hi> (which at the <hi>laſt day</hi> will be a great) <hi>Account</hi> alſo, to wit, his <hi>Plots,</hi> as before, his <hi>Cheats,</hi> in the one a <hi>crafty Fox,</hi> in the other a <hi>cruel Tyger,</hi> and ſurely whoever were the Inſtruments, the Members, the Hands and the Feet for Acting this Bloudy Plot, to Reduce <hi>England</hi> to the Roman Rotten Religion, we ſhall find <hi>Him</hi> the Head and Principal Agent. My Deſign is here to ſet the Saddle upon the Right Horſe: 'Tis a Thouſand pitties, that the <hi>petty larceners</hi> ſhould <hi>be Hang'd</hi> and <hi>Beheaded,</hi> (though that be no more than what both <hi>Diſtributive</hi> and <hi>Commutative Juſtice</hi> moſt Juſtly Required) and the grand Thief (that ſet them all on work) eſcape Scot-free. How many did pity thoſe poor mercenary Rogues that were Executed for that Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Cowardly Murther of that Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:52972:63"/>
Patriot <hi>Eſquire Thinn,</hi> when they ſaw <hi>Count Conniſmark,</hi> the great Rogue, (that ſet his ſilly Vaſſals on Work) to be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. but there is a [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a <hi>Vengeance</hi> (even in the Judgment of no better than <hi>Barbarians,</hi> Act. 28.4.) <hi>which will not ſuffer</hi> either the <hi>one</hi> or the <hi>other long to live;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>God of Juſtice</hi> hath peremptorily ſaid, that the <hi>Bloudy</hi> and <hi>Deceitful Men ſhall not live out half their days,</hi> Pſal. 55.23.</p>
            <p>Take here a Diſtinct Liſt and Catalogue of the <hi>chief</hi> Plotters in this Late and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Plot, and View them from Head to Foot, from <hi>Top to Toe,</hi> as they ſtand Ranked in our Engliſh Records, and Orderly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred for everlaſting Remembrance.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This <hi>Preſent Pope Innocent the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth,</hi> the <hi>Maſter of all the Miſrule</hi> and <hi>Matchleſs Miſchief:</hi> as the Philoſopher ſaith of <hi>Finis,</hi> 'tis <hi>primus Intentione,</hi> but <hi>ultimus Executione;</hi> So muſt I ſay of this <hi>Fino Filth,</hi> He is the <hi>firſt in Intention,</hi> (his Curſed Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter being the principal end propoſed in this preſent Diſcourſe) yet muſt He come <hi>laſt in Execution,</hi> not onely in the <hi>Method</hi> of this <hi>Platform,</hi> but alſo (for ought I yet ſee) in the <hi>Meaſures</hi> of Gods <hi>Providence:</hi> For the <hi>Law of Juſtice</hi> (compared to the Cobweb that catches the leſſer Flyes, but cannot keep the great ones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is too
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:52972:63"/>
               <hi>Low</hi> and Short Handed (as to Man) to Reach ſo High and ſo Far as the <hi>Great Goff of Rome,</hi> Yet ſurely <hi>in due Seaſon His Sin ſhall find him out</hi> by the great God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.23. unto whom we muſt leave Him, for He is the <hi>God of Vengeance, Juſtice is His,</hi> and <hi>He will Repay,</hi> Deut. 32.35.43. Rom. 12.19.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Cardinal Howard,</hi> by Birth both an <hi>Engliſh Man,</hi> and <hi>Brother</hi> to the Great <hi>Duke of Norfolk;</hi> So one of the Popes firſt and fitteſt Engines to Betray <hi>England</hi> into His <hi>Holineſſes</hi> Hands, that thereby this <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> might the more Merit Saint <hi>Peters Chair</hi> upon this Popes Departure from it, and then this Sweet Bit (our Land) would prove a Sowceing Augmentation to <hi>Peters Patrimony:</hi> Therefore, as the Pope was <hi>Lord High Admiral</hi> in the whole <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> So, it was concluded by the <hi>Cabal</hi> in the Colledg <hi>de propaganda fide,</hi> that this ſame <hi>Engliſh Cardinal,</hi> ſhould be his <hi>Vice Admiral,</hi> and hereupon He was diſpatch'd away from <hi>Rome</hi> to be the <hi>Popes Legatus a Latere,</hi> or a <hi>None Such Nuncio</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> upon ſuch an unparalleld Errand, as never any <hi>Embaſſadour</hi> durſt undertake, which was to take poſſeſſion of <hi>it</hi> in this Popes Name, as if it had been elaps'd into his Hands for want of either Heir or Poſſeſſour, though,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:52972:64"/>
Bleſſed be God it hath both, and needs none of the <hi>Popes falſe Claims,</hi> or <hi>foul uſurpations:</hi> and to make this Cardinal more brisk in his exploit, the Pope Creates Him <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury</hi> (as if <hi>there</hi> had been a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy too) and, that <hi>Sees Vaſt Revenue</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing look'd upon as too little a Bribe for ſo Heroick an undertaker, the <hi>Pope</hi> ordains Him Forty Thouſand Crowns <hi>per Annum</hi> out of His own Coffers (where there is <hi>Gold and Silver enough,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 18.12, 13.) as a neceſſary ſupplement to that pittiful Arch-Biſhoprick (the Beſt and Richeſt in <hi>England</hi>) that He might be had in more Veneration, and the better Support His Authoritative Grandieur: And as if this alone were below this <hi>Innocent Harmleſs Pope</hi> (like another <hi>proud Haman</hi>) to lay His Violent Hands onely upon our <hi>Mordecai</hi> (the <hi>Biſhop of Canterbury,</hi> as well as <hi>King Charles the Second</hi>) to Diſpoſſeſs them both of their <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Miter,</hi> but He daringly Diſpoſſeſſeth (ſo far as the good will of the evil Beaſt would ſtretch) moſt of our other <hi>Biſhops,</hi> promoting His own Popelings as ſo many <hi>Interlopers</hi> in their places, as Father <hi>Perrot</hi> to <hi>York, Corker</hi> to <hi>London, Whitebread</hi> to <hi>Wincheſter, Strange</hi> to <hi>Durham: Godder</hi> to <hi>Salisbury, Napper</hi> to <hi>Norwich,</hi> &amp;c. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all thoſe Biſhops (whom this Pope
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:52972:64"/>
would have <hi>turned out</hi> to Grazing, unleſs they could have <hi>turned in</hi> to Him) whether His <hi>Name</hi> and His <hi>Nature</hi> do correſpond well herein, and whether they would not have had hereupon far greater Reaſon to brand Him (as in Scripture, <hi>this is King Ahaz</hi>) ſaying likewiſe, this is <hi>Pope Nocent,</hi> rather than <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> the <hi>Eleventh:</hi> All muſt Truckle to <hi>Cardinal Howard</hi> His Nuncio.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Johannes Paulus de Oliva,</hi> comes in next to play his pranks, and as He had been the Father <hi>General of the Jeſuits</hi> in all Lands, ſo this <hi>Pope</hi> Conſtitutes <hi>Him</hi> his <hi>Rere-Admiral,</hi> to <hi>Mann</hi> and to Mannage a right <hi>Romes</hi> Great <hi>Man of War,</hi> the <hi>Provincial</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> in ſo noble an Attack: but is Attacking in a Military manner, proper Work for an <hi>Olivas,</hi> whoſe Name carries an <hi>Olive Leaf</hi> (that Badg of Peace) in its Mouth, but it ſeems, He will be like his Great Maſter, <hi>Pope Nocent-Innocent,</hi> there is <hi>War in his Heart.</hi> Which minds me of a Story concerning the foregoing <hi>Pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the Tenth,</hi> who bare for part of his Arms <hi>[a Dove with an Olive Branch in her Mouth]</hi> Whereupon our Turn Coat and Runagate <hi>Doctor Baily</hi> wittily Quibbles up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Oliva vera,</hi> profoundly perverting it to <hi>Oliverus,</hi> and highly Courted that Protector
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:52972:65"/>
with his Seraphick Compariſon of the <hi>Olive</hi> and <hi>Oliver.</hi> See his Life of <hi>Fiſher,</hi> p. 260, 261. 'Tis the genuine Character of a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> to have <hi>Honey</hi> (or the <hi>Olive of Peace</hi>) in <hi>his Mouth,</hi> and to have deſigned (yea Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated) Swords and Daggers in his Heart. Oh <hi>brave Olive,</hi> Oh <hi>brave Oliver,</hi> the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Sword that ſhould have been Sheath'd in our Bowels, Reached to <hi>Rome,</hi> and was held in this Brave <hi>Olivas</hi> Hand.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Pedro Jeronimo de Corduba,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial of the Jeſuits in <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> the Pope muſt have here a <hi>Paul</hi> (as His Third Engine) and a <hi>Peter</hi> (as this Fourth) engaged with Himſelf herein, though both <hi>Jeſuits</hi> (without whom no Miſchief in all <hi>Europe</hi> can be managed, the <hi>Hand of Joab</hi> or <hi>Jeſuite</hi> is in all) to make this <hi>Damnable</hi> and <hi>Diabolical Plot</hi> more like <hi>Apoſtolical:</hi> That Work which this Pope cut out for him, was to be a <hi>Grand Pilot</hi> in his Countrey, and to give the Plot a lift endways, both with <hi>Money</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> under the notion of Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims: and where <hi>this</hi> Popiſh <hi>Pedro</hi> or <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> plaid his pranks like a right Beautifeu to Sow his Seed of Contention betwixt that Crown and this, thereby the more to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the further Progreſs of the Plot.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>La Cheſe</hi> a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> too, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor to the <hi>French King</hi> (and ſo muſt be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:52972:65"/>
Privy to all his Royal Deſigns) <hi>He</hi> was alſo a <hi>Grand Pilot</hi> in that Countrey, whoſe hands were directed to Steer a right Courſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by that conceited Coxcomb, our <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who was hang'd for his pains in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying his own Native Countrey.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Another Jeſuite (I have not his Name, and indeed 'tis not worth enquiry) who is Confeſſour to the <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> muſt Create Fends betwixt <hi>Him</hi> and our King: That, with all theſe pretty Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, we might be wheadled into a Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing abroad, while they by their <hi>Engliſh Jeſuits,</hi> &amp;c. could cut our Throats at Home: Mark here, what a Sacred Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is Six, with them there muſt be Six of Forreign Aſſiſtants (the Number of the Beaſt is Three Sixes as before) and ſtill <hi>Jeſuits</hi> every where muſt be the <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of Cruelty, though the Pope be the hand to Improve them: I the leſs wonder at this, ſince I Read that paſſage in the Jeſuit <hi>Muffeius,</hi> writing the Life of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Loyala</hi> their Founder, He there Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly confeſſeth, that their <hi>Father Imitated the Devil in uſing Tricks to Convert</hi> (or rather <hi>Pervert) Diſciples,</hi> &amp;c. You may Swear, that all the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> do <hi>Patrizare</hi> and will <hi>Try</hi> the <hi>Devils Tricks</hi> with the beſt of <hi>Juglers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:52972:66"/>But are our Jeſuits in <hi>England</hi> aſleep all this while? No, the Pope hath <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Tools as well as <hi>Forreign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Popes Domeſtick Engines employed here, were Theſe</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Provincial of the Jeſuits,</hi> for the Time being in <hi>England,</hi> who was <hi>White-Bread,</hi> who would have made Brownbread and Brann of us, but he <hi>fell into his own Pit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Benedictine Monks</hi> at the <hi>Savoy.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Savoys</hi> Country was call'd <hi>Malvoy,</hi> becauſe it was peſterd ſo notoriouſly with Theeves as made it <hi>Mala Via</hi> or <hi>Malvoy,</hi> that is, a <hi>Dangerous Paſſage,</hi> but when the Thieves were Rooted out, its Name was changed into <hi>Salvoy</hi> or <hi>Savoy,</hi> the way <hi>thence</hi> to <hi>Somerſet-houſe,</hi> makes the Application more eaſie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Seminary Prieſts,</hi> who were Sowing their <hi>Tares among</hi> the Wheat (like the <hi>Envious one</hi> their Father) all over the Land, they being about the Number of <hi>Eighteen Hundred,</hi> a large black Regiment under Roman Colours.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Many <hi>Lay-Papiſts both of the Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> (too well known to need naming) who had all Commiſſions Sealed by Brave <hi>Oliva</hi> aforementioned, both for Civil and Military Employ, and ſent them
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:52972:66"/>
by <hi>this Pope,</hi> as the Higheſt Marks of his Favour.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Multitudes, Multitudes of the Lay-Papiſts</hi> among the <hi>Commonalty.</hi> Even all the Papiſts in <hi>England</hi> could not chuſe but be Engaged in ſo Glorious and Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Matter; and this is the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, If not only their General Principles Imbibed with their Religion, but alſo the Popes particular Teſt (for Anathematizing us Hereticks) Impoſed Univerſally on them, be but well conſidered.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, For ſtill we muſt have the Six in Adoration of Six Hundred Sixty Six, <hi>&amp;c. All the Engliſh Covents beyond Sea,</hi> (as St. <hi>Omors,</hi> &amp;c.) muſt be almoſt drain'd Dry, and Tranſported <hi>Incognito</hi>'s hither, to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roberate the better carrying on of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Cauſe, which was now become as Catholick as their <hi>Religion,</hi> having likewiſe all the moſt Eminent of the Popiſh Clergy in <hi>Europe</hi> Engaged to help at a Dead Lift, and to Lift <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Rome.</hi> Hereby this Plot became the Unanimous Act of the whole <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, whoſe <hi>Infallible</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> Head (this Pope) Adjur'd them to it, upon the forfeiture of their Fathers Bleſſing. Though we may not Imagine every Individual Popeling could know the whole Intrigue (for there might be a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:52972:67"/>
Wheel within a Wheel) yet in the Lump they pay to this Pope their <hi>Blind Obedience,</hi> however the Guilt both of the parts, and of the whole, falls upon the <hi>Innocent</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of this Pope, which all his <hi>Holy Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> cannot waſh off, and make him as <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> as his Name, ſhould he Conjure <hi>Tibur</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now when His Holineſs had thus well furniſhed his Holy Cauſe with <hi>Men</hi> (a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Set of Sixes, a <hi>Jury</hi> of Twelve, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay, <hi>All Good Men and True,</hi> No, not ſo much as the <hi>Foreman himſelf</hi>) His next Care is to be ſupply'd with <hi>Money,</hi> the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news</hi> of His <hi>Holy War,</hi> and though his own private Exchequer be <hi>Puteus In exhauſtus</hi> (as he once ſaid of <hi>England,</hi> when it was his <hi>Aſs</hi> to Ride on, and therefore would fain beſtride her ſoft Back again,) an <hi>Inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible Fountain,</hi> yet the Old Crafty Fox liked better to get ſome Bearers, well knowing that many Hands make lighter Work. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon by his <hi>Apoſtolical Command,</hi> as well as <hi>Example.</hi> A Vaſt and Prodigious <hi>Fund</hi> was quickly Erected for ſo Great and Pious a Work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Pope himſelf,</hi> to be a good Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to others, conveys into his Sacred Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury by <hi>Paulus de Oliva,</hi> or <hi>Paul Olive, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Thouſand Crowns,</hi> I wonder He made it
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:52972:67"/>
not even <hi>Twelve,</hi> and the <hi>Crown's, Pounds;</hi> His own full Coffers <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.12. might well enough have born it beſides; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining of <hi>England</hi> to His Revenue would well enough have Countervail'd that Coſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Catholick King</hi> (His Eldeſt Son) of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhames his <hi>Holy Father,</hi> in Advancing Ten Thouſand Pounds by <hi>Peter Jeronimus;</hi> thus his <hi>Indian</hi> Gold was Expend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> His <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Son of France</hi> (to ſhew himſelf the better <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or rather <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi>) Advanceth Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pound more by Father <hi>Le Cheeſe,</hi> what a ſhame it is, that His Holineſs ſhould be out done by both his Sons, when it was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly His Cauſe, and He would have Run away with the Profit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I wonder we hear nothing of the <hi>Emperors Charity,</hi> was it becauſe he was too <hi>Nigardly,</hi> or becauſe the <hi>Male-Contents</hi> of <hi>Hungary</hi> kept his Coffers Empty; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, divers conſiderable Sums were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Coleman</hi> by Foreign Miniſters, among whom, <hi>He</hi> from <hi>Germany</hi> might be one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> But the <hi>Engliſh Jeſuits</hi> (ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Emperor</hi> to be too <hi>Narrow Soul'd,) Ex Abundanti,</hi> ſupply'd all Defects, they
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:52972:68"/>
having Threeſcore Thouſand Pound <hi>per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> Eſtate in Land here, and an Hundred Thouſand Pound Ready Caſh, a conſtant Running Stock in the way of their <hi>Trade,</hi> which (you know) is the <hi>Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The <hi>Benedictine Monks</hi> (not to be thruſt out as Rotten) contribute out of their Bleſſed Treaſure, Six Thouſand Pound to purchaſe the Popes <hi>Benediction,</hi> whom <hi>they</hi> alſo exceeded in their Benevolence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> God Bleſs us, here's the Third Six again, and ſo we have got the <hi>exact Number of the Beaſt,</hi> Six, and Six, and Six, or Six Hundred Sixty Six, and to make up this Number compleat, the <hi>Engliſh Catholick</hi> (as well as <hi>Romon) Grandees</hi> were free Contributors of moſt <hi>Ample Benevolencies</hi> to this ſo Great and ſo Glorious a Work.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had this <hi>Innocent</hi> Pope thus provided Himſelf (though He as to his part, comes off but <hi>Stingily</hi>) with <hi>quantum ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit</hi> (or rather <hi>ſuffocat,</hi> as to Juſtice <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi>) both of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Money:</hi> He then ſends forth His hungry <hi>Beagles</hi> to Hunt the <hi>harmleſs Hare,</hi> that never gave them the leaſt provocation: but He <hi>muſt</hi> do it, 'tis the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> to worry the Harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and 'tis the <hi>cuſtome</hi> (which is a ſecond nature) of this <hi>Innocent Pope</hi> to be notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <hi>Nocent</hi> to the <hi>Innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:52972:68"/>The <hi>Firſt Innocent,</hi> He Aſſaults with his greedy Hounds, is no leſs than <hi>our King</hi> (God Bleſs Him) <hi>Grove</hi> and <hi>Tickering</hi> are hired to ſhoot Him, <hi>Conyers</hi> and <hi>Anderton</hi> to ſtab Him, <hi>four Iriſh Ruffians</hi> to <hi>Godfrey</hi> Him, Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi> to poyſon Him: <hi>Out of the way with Him, any way</hi> (they cry) ſince He will not <hi>comply with our Plot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Duke of York</hi> ſhall fare no better, unleſs He will turn Tenant to this <hi>Innocent</hi> Pope for his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as well as for his <hi>Religion,</hi> and pardon the Murtherers of his Brother, the Burners of the City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Maſſacrers of the People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe their Horrid and Helliſh Plot had taken <hi>Wind</hi> by <hi>Doctor Oats</hi>'s Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions given in to <hi>Juſtice Godfrey</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their Bloudy Deſigns, both of Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Duke of York</hi> too, If he would not comply, and upon His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Murther,</hi> of Firing <hi>Weſtminſter, Wap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, Rotherith</hi> and <hi>Southwark,</hi> as they had done <hi>London,</hi> and to lay all upon the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> &amp;c. as likewiſe of making a <hi>General Maſſacre</hi> at the ſame time by a ſecret liſted Army of Five Hundred Thouſand Cut-Throats, whereof the Lord <hi>Bellaſis</hi> was to be General, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were all Diſcovered) this <hi>good Magiſtrate</hi> muſt have his Mouth ſtoped from telling Tales, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein the Pope
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:52972:69"/>
ſucceeded ſo far as to make this Man the <hi>Firſt Martyr of our Religion, and a fair Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of our Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like was Attempted upon <hi>Juſtice Arnold,</hi> though no other Crime was found in either, ſave a faithful Diſcharge of their Oath and Duty. Nor againſt <hi>Juſtice Pye</hi> neither, yet <hi>Bodnam</hi> the Papiſt prevail'd to knock down his <hi>Clay-Cruſt</hi> with his Bill, whereby this <hi>good Pye</hi> (a ſerviceable Diſh in <hi>Hereford-ſhire</hi>) was Deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>Popes Agents</hi> (being now Fleſh'd in Proteſtants Bloud, yet unable to <hi>ſtifle the Plot,</hi> when it once was Declared by both Houſes of Parliament that there was a Traiterous Deſign of the Pope to Subject this Kingdom to his Tyrannical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by theſe Five pernicious Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> whereof <hi>Stafford</hi> lately Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted was, &amp;c.) do then club their Wits, not onely with this <hi>Pope</hi> (the Devils Eldeſt Son) but even with the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf, how they might handſomly <hi>Sham</hi> it, and this they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the very Fire to Accompliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Then began they to play their Popiſh pranks in <hi>Blaſting</hi> the <hi>Kings Evidence,</hi> Sir <hi>Dennis Aſhburnham,</hi> the Saint <hi>Oniers Boys,</hi> are brought in to Accuſe <hi>Doctor Oats</hi> of <hi>Perjury,</hi> as <hi>Lane and Osborn</hi> did of <hi>Sodomy,</hi> the like <hi>pranks againſt France, Bedloe, Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:52972:69"/>
&amp;c. but their Bowl Runs not here without a Rub for their Deſign of Subborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Alderman Brook</hi> and Captain <hi>Bury,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcovered, this Diſcover'd alſo that all the aforeſaid Tools were but the <hi>Popes</hi> or the <hi>Devils</hi> Trunks through which he ſpake, as he uſed to do in his <hi>Dumb Images,</hi> which the Father of Lyes taught to ſay what he liſted, yet muſt be his <hi>Oracles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> They, being Non-plus'd herein alſo by the Over-ruling Hand of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin new Methods by the Popes Advice (and indeed, what ſhould direct Hands and Feet but the Head) then thought of ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Plot from their own ſhoulders by Forging ſeveral <hi>Sham-Plots,</hi> all to be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered upon the Proteſtants: thus at a pinch they are <hi>Ingenioſe nequam,</hi> wickedly witty.</p>
            <q>Heu quantum ſubitis caſibus Ingenium.</q>
            <p>Yet this was but to new Vamp a pair of their old Boots, for that Impious Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth, taught his Popiſh Prieſts, that when they had by the Powder Plot blown up the King <hi>(James)</hi> Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, to Father that filthy Fact upon the <hi>Puritans:</hi> the Father of Lyes is put hard to his Trumps, when he is ſo low Run,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:52972:70"/>
that he hath no new Tricks in his Tinkers Budget to ſtop holes with, but is forced to bring forth his old Baffoold Stratagems. However He is Reſolved to drive this Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers nail (new pointed) ſo far as it would go with his Hammer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Order</hi> to this, They ſtart many <hi>Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plots,</hi> wherewith they indeed began betimes, even in 1661 (as Captain <hi>Yarranton</hi> Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, when the Crown was ſcarce warm upon our <hi>King Charles</hi> his Head: but that and all other Succeſſively, were but low Games compared to this, for then they had not ſuch a Damnable Plot Diſcovered to Palliate as now, even this Plot of Plots that was Hatched at <hi>Rome</hi> as ſoon as this <hi>Innocent</hi> Pope ſtorm'd <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, his <hi>Miter</hi> was ſcarce warm upon his Head (put upon him in the Year 1676.) but preſently the Devil enters into him (as if he had taken <hi>Judas</hi>'s Sop) and ſets both his <hi>Head</hi> and his <hi>Heart</hi> to contrive this Bloudy Deſign, which for two full Years (like that <hi>ſtrange River</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in Hiſtory) Ran underground, before it brake forth and was Diſcovered in the Year 1678. Now when that Devil and his Deeds of Darkneſs was brought to Light (though long wrap'd up in <hi>Samuels</hi> Mantle) by the Father of Lights, who always over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoots Satan in in his own Bow, theſe white
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:52972:70"/>
Witches would fain Conjure him down with multiplyd Sham-plots: Indeed, one begetting another <hi>Corruptio Unius</hi> was <hi>Generatio Alterius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> was, The <hi>Clapping up of Mr.</hi> Clapool <hi>into the Tower,</hi> before their plot was Diſcovered, that they might have him at Hand to Father the Kings Murder upon, ſo ſoon as he ſhould fall by their Hands, whereas all the Treaſon that can be charg'd upon this modeſt Gentleman, is, that he hath led a Retired Life for many Years, and onely ſeekt to betray the Secrets of Nature by hard Study, as alſo that he Marryed <hi>Olivers Jewel,</hi> which render'd him more fit to Faſten their Deſigns upon.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> was, A Raiſing of the Report, that <hi>Juſtice Godfrey</hi> was a Papiſt (one of their Creatures ſaid ſo much to my ſelf) and that he was Murdered by the Proteſtants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This, by <hi>Nevils</hi> means, was made the common Diſcourſe in every Coffehouſe, to amuſe the Nation, and to give them a Diverſion from the Papiſts. The now Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> knows it to be true.</p>
            <p>Of the ſame Bran was a later Report that Juſtice <hi>Godfrey</hi> Hangd himſelf, for which <hi>N. T.</hi> was Pillory'd, both could not be true, if the one, then not the other, whereas nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is true, for he neither Hangd himſelf, nor dyed he by Proteſtants but by Papiſts
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:52972:71"/>
Hands: ſtill the Death of one Sham-plot gave Life to another, and one Bafled begat another to the end of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>The time would fail (as Room I am ſure doth) to Reckon all <hi>Romes Plots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third</hi> was (to omit <hi>Netervils</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to Suborn Captain <hi>Bury</hi> and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Brooks,</hi> &amp;c.) The Duke of <hi>Buck.</hi> was an Eye-ſore for ſaying (I ſuppoſe) he would never turn Papiſt, <hi>till they</hi> can eat up the Devil, as, they ſay, they do God in their Hoſt.</p>
            <p>For this they firſt Accuſe him of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and this failing, of <hi>Sodomy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> was, The Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was their greateſt ſtumbling Block, becauſe His Sagacity had ſo oft Countermined their Deviliſh Deſigns, Hereupon, Plots upon Plots were laid againſt his Life: both by Men and Women, in City and Country.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth</hi> was, Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> had (while in Commiſſion) been a Thorn in their Sides, for daily Ferreting the Foxes out of their Holes, where they had Earth'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and openly Condemning their Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries to the Flames of a <hi>Purgatory</hi>-fire above ground: no wonder then, if they at that time ſought to blaſt his Reputation, as they (to wit, <hi>Monſon,</hi> whom he had committed to <hi>Newgate</hi>) and <hi>Nevil,</hi> aforementioned,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:52972:71"/>
               <hi>(alias Paine)</hi> do now ſeek to Deſtroy his Life, the Preſervation whereof the <hi>whole Nation,</hi> yea, the whole <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Intereſt are obliged to Pray for, He being an Active Inſtrument in Gods Hand for the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Sixth</hi> (and ſtill this <hi>Miſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> Runs all in <hi>Sixes</hi> both in the <hi>Real</hi> and in the <hi>Sham-plots,</hi> in the <hi>former</hi> and in the <hi>latter</hi> Diſtribution.) was a <hi>Plot of Plots,</hi> a Wickedneſs with a Witneſs indeed: which (in ſome ſenſe) was worſe than either the <hi>Iriſh</hi> or <hi>Pariſian Maſſacre,</hi> wherein good Men onely loſt their lives, but herein they muſt loſe their <hi>Reputations</hi> too, as Branded with Rebellion to Poſterity. 'Twas worſe than the Cruelty of <hi>Nero,</hi> who only wiſh'd all the People had but one Neck, that <hi>He</hi> might cut them all off at one Blow: but here was more than a <hi>bare wiſh,</hi> a <hi>crafty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour</hi> to blow up all the Proteſtant Lords (the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> &amp;c.) All the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Yeamonry</hi> in <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> at one Blaſt, by fixing High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon them all Univerſally: and when the Knife was at our Throats, God ſent Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> to turn up the botton of <hi>Mad-dame Celliers Meal-Tab,</hi> where all the Bran of this Brutiſh Intreague was Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, <hi>Cum multis aliis quae nunc perſcribere longum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:52972:72"/>Theſe and a Thouſand more pretty <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> Pranks hath this Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth</hi> plaid in poor <hi>England,</hi> though not in his <hi>Perſon,</hi> yet by his <hi>Proxy,</hi> whatever His Slaves and Vaſſals have Acted here, even <hi>Matchleſs Villanies,</hi> All have been by an <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> and by a <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> to his <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> (or rather <hi>Apoſtatical</hi>) Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; but ſurely that Servant who will be Hang'd for his Maſter, or for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Fault more than his own, muſt needs have more of <hi>Blind Charity,</hi> than of a <hi>Solid Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>☞ One would Admire, that any Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Breaſt could be ſo Capacious as to contain in it ſo much <hi>Villanous Venom</hi> as this <hi>Innocent Pope</hi> hath poured out upon <hi>England;</hi> but is here all? No, <hi>Scotland, France, Ireland</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> yea, and all other Proteſtant Countries, muſt likewiſe be Wounded with the Poiſonful Sting of this <hi>Fiery Flying Serpent,</hi> this <hi>Great Red Dragon,</hi> Mounted aloft upon the Higheſt Theatre in the Chriſtian World, hath his proſpect into all theſe places, and, as if He <hi>True Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisk,</hi> Kills down-right with his very <hi>Looks,</hi> His <hi>Looks</hi> are Top-full of Faſcination. To tell diſtinctly how he hath Bewitched with his bare <hi>Looks</hi> all thoſe Lands aforenamed, would Require another Volum. Take here
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:52972:72"/>
only a very Brief Landskip hereof, which yet may ſerve to ſatisfie, that this pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Head is Top-full of Poiſon, and this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Head of the Church Transfuſeth a Fatal Poiſon into all the parts of the Body; his <hi>Venom</hi> is as <hi>Univerſal</hi> as his <hi>Headſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Firſt,</hi> For <hi>Scotland,</hi> He ſent ſeveral Jeſuits to Preach there under the Notion of Presbyterians, who Induſtriouſly Blew up the Coals of Diſcontent among that People, knowing that <hi>Oppreſſion maketh Wiſe Men Mad,</hi> Aggravating to them their Unbeara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Burdens under Epiſcopal Tyranny, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeing them to Vindicate their Religion and Liberty with the Sword, and promiſing them in the <hi>Popes</hi> Name, That they ſhould be Aſſiſted with Eight Thouſand Catholicks to overturn the Government.</p>
            <p>Oh how did this Pope Laugh in his Lawn Sleeves, to ſee himſelf ſo <hi>Succeſsful.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Oats Narrative, Art.</hi> 1, 74, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to <hi>France,</hi> How far this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocene</hi> Pope hath been <hi>Nocent there,</hi> How far his <hi>Tincture</hi> of <hi>Lucifer</hi> hath turn'd his <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Son into <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> may be Legibly Read, even in Capital Letters, in the <hi>Bloudy Whales</hi> upon the Backs of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> but moſt of all in that <hi>Deteſtable Teſt,</hi> which wounds not their <hi>Bodies</hi> only, but their <hi>Souls</hi> alſo, unleſs they will <hi>Abjure</hi> the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:52972:73"/>
Religion, <hi>Anathematize</hi> all Proteſtants, this hath Turn'd out of <hi>France</hi> many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the Tendereſt part of that People into Foreign Countries, though <hi>it</hi> be ſo Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrically contrary to the Sacred <hi>Edicts of Nauts,</hi> ſo ſolemnly Sworn to by the <hi>French King.</hi> Yet this Pope, by his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency, dare Abſolve him from this Oath, and Undertakes to make Sin a Duty. See Sir <hi>William Waller</hi>'s <hi>Account of the preſent State of the Proteſtants there.</hi> And ſee alſo, <hi>The Politicks of France.</hi> And whether all this Conteſt betwixt the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> about the <hi>Regalia</hi>'s, be not all a Juggle, (ſeeing the poor Proteſtants are among hands ſo ſevearly Perſecuted, and peſtilent Jeſuits ſo Cordially Embraced,) Time will Declare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to <hi>Ireland,</hi> Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, <hi>Narrat.</hi> pag. 65, 66. That this <hi>Innocent Pope</hi> ſent his <hi>Bloudy Iriſh Hounds, Commiſſions, Arms,</hi> and <hi>Eight Hundred Thouſand Crowns,</hi> that they might cut the Throats of the Proteſtants again, as they had done by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Innocent</hi> Popes Order in One Thouſand Six Hundred Forty One. The Death of the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſhould lead this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Dance, the Pope looſes of his Bloud-Hounds (Four Jeſuits) who Undertook to Diſpatch the Duke, Twenty Five Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:52972:73"/>
               <hi>Iriſh</hi> were to Riſe, and play their Old Bloudy Game, wherein they were Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, and Artificial Gameſters. Theſe were to Join with a <hi>French Army</hi> to be Landed there, and as good Gameſters of that Kind as they, ſo fall on to their Old Trade of Maſſacring, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, ſome of thoſe <hi>Iriſh Cattel</hi> had a Diſpenſation from this Pope to take the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> provided they promiſe to Betray their Garriſons, and other Truſts. So that when you ſee a Papiſt ſwallow thoſe Oaths, you may Swear 'tis with ſuch a <hi>proviſo,</hi> He hath ſome Truſt or other to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Holland,</hi> There this <hi>Innocent</hi> Pope hath ſet his Foul Foot (of the <hi>Beaſt</hi>) to purpoſe, in ſending his <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Son,</hi> moſt Unchriſtianly to Scourge them for their Hereſie, and to over-run their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey with his Rapacious Army; and had not God Almighty put an Hook into the Jaw of that Proud <hi>Leviathan</hi> at <hi>Utrech,</hi> He had laid their Land under an Abſolute Deſolation. To ſay nothing of <hi>His</hi> Intrigue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Influences to plunge <hi>them</hi> and <hi>us</hi> into a War to Waſt and Weaken each other that He might the eaſier worry <hi>us</hi> both: To ſay nothing of <hi>Hungary</hi> and other parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> nor of the Three <hi>Northern
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:52972:74"/>
Crowns;</hi> in all which he hath throughly, tryed the ſame Truſty Tricks of <hi>Divide, and Command,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet while this Pope is thus <hi>Malevolent;</hi> and <hi>Miſchievous</hi> abroad (embroiling all Countries with his Contagious Evomitions) He is all this while Mighty Magnificent and Magiſterial at Home, ſtrutting about in that <hi>Splendour and Grandeur,</hi> as if He were more than a <hi>Mortal Man</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> one of the <hi>Immortal Angels</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> Reſembling the <hi>Angelical Nature,</hi> not onely in <hi>Innocency,</hi> in his Name <hi>Innocent,</hi> but alſo in <hi>Luſtre and Glory,</hi> as to his Garb and Deportment. Grant Him to be one of the Angels Order, yet undervalue him not, by reckoning him among the Inferior Rank. No, let him be Reputed no leſs than <hi>proud Lucifer,</hi> a Prince or Principality among them, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14 14 As to his <hi>Innocency,</hi> Angel like, I can ſay, little of it, and ſure I am nor no body elſe (unleſs ſome of his Sycophants who can be content to lick up his <hi>Slaver,</hi> as once one <hi>Parafite</hi> did a Tyrants) no further than his Name <hi>[Innocent]</hi> will be the Guarranty: To be <hi>Nocent in Nature</hi> (as the premiſies have proved him) and to be <hi>Innocent in Name,</hi> is to make himſelf a compleat lump of Contradiction: However this <hi>Whore of Babylon</hi> can exactly Imitate <hi>Solomons Whore</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:52972:74"/>
in <hi>wiping her Mouth,</hi> and ſaying I have not done thoſe miſchiefs in all thoſe Lands afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned: But as to this Splendour and Glory, Angel-like, I have more to ſay than I have room for, as to his <hi>Roman Grandeur,</hi> never was <hi>Jaddus</hi> (the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> of the Jews) ſo Richly Arrayed for <hi>Glory and Beauty,</hi> when <hi>Great Alexander</hi> met him and fell down to Worſhip him for a god, as this <hi>Roman Pontifex</hi> in all his pompious pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calibus is, either ſitting in his Chair of State, or ſtanding upright, or ſtrutting about. The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> moſt graphically Deſcribes <hi>this Anointed Cherub, that Seats himſelf in the Holy Mountain of God, &amp; ſits as God</hi> (that is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree above an <hi>Angel) covering himſelf with every pretious Stone,</hi> the <hi>Rubys,</hi> the <hi>Diamonds,</hi> the <hi>Jaſper,</hi> the <hi>Saphire</hi> and <hi>Emerauld,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.2.13, 14, 15, to 20. Oh what a glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and glorious Scarlet coloured Beaſt is this, thus bedeckt with Radiant Jewels. No wonder if they give him this Canting Courtſhip [<hi>Thou art the prime of all Biſhops, the Heir of the Apoſtles, an Abel for primacy</hi> (ſure I am, not for Religion) <hi>a Noah for Government</hi> (not for Righteouſneſs) <hi>an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham for Patriarkſhip</hi> (not for Piety) <hi>a Melchiſedeck for Order, an Aaron for Dignity, a Moſes for Authority, a Samuel for Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a Peter for Power,</hi> yea, <hi>a Chriſt for
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:52972:75"/>
Unction,</hi> but none of them for <hi>Holineſs,</hi> though that be his Title: No wonder if his pickthanks go yet higher, in calling him <hi>their Lord God, their Creator in whom they muſt Believe, and whom they muſt Obey upon pain of Damnation</hi>] no wonder if they ſay to this their God three times <hi>[Oh Thou that takeſt away the Sins of the World, have Mercy on us. Thou canſt make a Sin to be no Sin, &amp; contra]</hi> No wonder if Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <hi>Kiſs the great Toe</hi> of their <hi>Great God,</hi> in a Country where God hath Toes, which <hi>Moſes</hi> (who came neareſt him) could not Diſcern, and much leſs Kiſs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.12, 15. No wonder if Kings and Emperours <hi>hold the Stirrop,</hi> to this God, when weary with walking, and would Ride, one Beaſt upon the back of another, no wonder if <hi>Odeſchal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> thought his Name too baſe for a <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Octavian</hi> did, when choſen Pope at Eighteen Years old, caſt off his <hi>Name</hi> becauſe <hi>Heath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi> and calls himſelf <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth,</hi> but he proved ſuch <hi>a God</hi> as uſed to drink Healths to the Devil, and in his Diceing would Pray, that <hi>Jupiter, Venus,</hi> and all the Devils would help him.</p>
            <p>This was a <hi>Mad Jack</hi> indeed, and as <hi>Bad a God,</hi> who ſhould be All good.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:52972:75"/>To conclude, come my Country-men, how can you like to Worſhip ſuch a God, (who is rather a <hi>Devil</hi> Incarnate, or the <hi>Devils Patriarch</hi>) can you ſtoop to <hi>kiſs his ſtinking Toe,</hi> can you <hi>hold his Stirrup</hi> (as too many are doing) till he get upon your own Backs and Ride you to the Devil, Grave <hi>Biſhop Uſhar</hi> feard a Maſſacre approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that this very Pope would be the chief Agent in it? Can you Court in a blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Villain, who will certainly cut your Throats? Can you like to Trade with ſuch a Cheat (that is as <hi>Crafty</hi> as <hi>Cruel,</hi> having as much of the Fox as of the Lyon) in his <hi>Traſh and Trumpery</hi> afore mentioned? This Pope had great hopes of Reentry into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by his hopeful Plot, hereupon <hi>Cotting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Bones were brought to be Buried <hi>here,</hi> to take poſſeſſion of it as <hi>Jacob</hi> did in like matner of <hi>Canaan:</hi> Indeed, the <hi>late Comet</hi> frighted him into ſuch a <hi>cold Sweat,</hi> as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Dutch Stove could bring warmth into him again, and the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> laid by the Prophetick Hen in <hi>Campideglis</hi> Garden ſtun'd him a little; But now he Recovered with <hi>warm Cloaths</hi> and hot Cordials again, yet I hope 'tis but a lightning before his fall: God forbid, that the Imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi> ſhould again Truckle to the Miter
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:52972:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and Tripple Crown of this Pope: <hi>Eraſmus</hi> Satyrical Drollery prevailed againſt the Pope, as well as <hi>Luthers Argumentative Gravity,</hi> I wiſh the like Efficacy to this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and let all good People ſay, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52972:76"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
